<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<manuscript xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" manuscript-id="20" name="" title="KRU_Chapter_20_DJHrev" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="../xsd/digfir_manuscript.xsd">
<chapter number="20" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-chapter-20" title="CHAPTER 20: International Trade, Capital Flows, and Exchange Rates" start-numbering-at="3" numbered="true">
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-sec1-1a" block_type="intro" title="Chapter Introduction" numbered="false" level="1" print_page="569">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_569" block_type="page_start">569</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p1" block_type="chapter_title">International Trade, Capital Flows, and Exchange Rates</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p2" block_type="chapter_number"><phrase block_type="chap">CHAPTER</phrase> <phrase block_type="chapnum">20</phrase></p>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-bx3-1" block_type="bx3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p3" block_type="co-t"><image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-img-1" alt="image" src="images/world_view_icon.jpg"/> <strong>THE EVERYWHERE PHONE</strong></p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-fig-1" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-img-2" alt="image" src="images/KrugESS4e_CO20a.jpg"/>
<asset_source>ImagineChina/Corbis</asset_source>
</figure>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-fig-2" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-img-3" alt="image" src="images/KrugESS4e_CO20b.jpg"/>
<caption>The production and consumption of smartphones are examples of today&#8217;s hyperglobal world with its soaring levels of international trade.</caption>
<asset_source>Vlad Teodor/Shutterstock</asset_source>
</figure>
</box>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-exp1-1" block_type="mn1">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p4" block_type="obj-h"><strong>What You Will Learn in This Chapter</strong></p>
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-list-1" type="unordered" block_type="greensquare">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p5" block_type="obj-bl">How comparative advantage leads to mutually beneficial international trade</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p6" block_type="obj-bl">The sources of international comparative advantage</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p7" block_type="obj-bl">Who gains and who loses from international trade, and why the gains exceed the losses</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p8" block_type="obj-bl">How <strong>tariffs</strong> and <strong>import quotas</strong> cause inefficiency and reduce total surplus</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p9" block_type="obj-bl">The meaning of the <strong>balance of payments accounts</strong> and the determinants of international capital flows</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p10" block_type="obj-bl">The role of the <strong>foreign exchange market</strong> and the <strong>exchange rate</strong></p></li>
</list>
</box>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-exp2-1" block_type="mn2">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p11" block_type="fg1-t"><image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-img-4" alt="image" src="images/learningcurve_logo_cmyk.jpg"/> &#124; interactive activity</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p12" block_type="co-txt-ni"><phrase block_type="dropcap">&#8220;W</phrase>E FELL IN LOVE WHEN I was nineteen / Now we&#8217;re staring at a screen.&#8221; These lyrics, from Arcade Fire&#8217;s 2013 hit song &#8220;Reflektor,&#8221; describe an era in which everyone does indeed seem to be staring at the screen of a smartphone. Apple introduced its first iPhone in 2007, and since then the iPhone and its competitors have become ubiquitous.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p13" block_type="co-txt">They&#8217;re everywhere&#8212;but where do smartphones come from? If you answered &#8220;America,&#8221; because Apple is an American company, you&#8217;re mostly wrong: Apple develops products, but outsources nearly all manufacturing of those products to other companies, mainly overseas. But it&#8217;s not really right to say &#8220;China&#8221; either, even though that&#8217;s where iPhones are assembled. You see, assembly&#8212;the last phase of iPhone production, in which the pieces are put together in the familiar metal-and-glass case&#8212;only accounts for a small fraction of the phone&#8217;s value. </p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p14" block_type="co-txt">In fact, a study of the iPhone 4 estimated that of the average factory price of &#36;229 per phone, only around &#36;10 stayed in the Chinese economy. A substantially larger amount went to Korean manufacturers, who supplied the display and memory chips. There were also substantial outlays for raw materials, sourced all over the world. And the biggest share of the price&#8212;more than half&#8212;consisted of Apple&#8217;s profit margin, which was largely a reward for research, development, and design.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p15" block_type="co-txt">So where do iPhones come from? Lots of places. And the case of the iPhone isn&#8217;t unusual: the car you drive, the clothing you wear, even the food you eat are generally the end products of complex <em>supply chains</em> that span the globe.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p16" block_type="co-txt">Has this always been true? Yes and no. Large-scale international trade isn&#8217;t new. By the early twentieth century, middle-class residents of London already ate bread made from Canadian wheat and beef from the Argentine Pampas, while wearing clothing woven from Australian wool and Egyptian cotton.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p17" block_type="co-txt">In recent decades, however, new technologies for transportation and communication have interacted with pro-trade policies to produce an era of <em>hyperglobalization</em> in which international trade has soared thanks to complex chains of production like the one that puts an iPhone in front of your nose. As a result, now, more than ever before, we must have a full picture of international trade to understand how national economies work.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p18" block_type="co-txt">This chapter examines the interaction of national economies. We begin with a discussion of the economics of international trade. With that foundation established, we move on to discuss how trade and capital flows are part of the balance of payments accounts. Finally, we look at the various factors that influence exchange rates.</p>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-sec1-1" block_type="h1" title="" chapter="20" numbered="true" level="1" print_page="570">
<section-metadata><section-title>Comparative Advantage and International Trade</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_570" block_type="page_start">570</p>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-exp3-1" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p19" block_type="mn-gl-def">Goods and services purchased from other countries are <strong>imports;</strong> goods and services sold to other countries are <strong>exports.</strong></p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p20" block_type="txt-ni">The United States buys smartphones&#8212;and many other goods and services&#8212;from other countries. At the same time, it sells many goods and services to other countries. Goods and services purchased from abroad are <strong>imports;</strong> goods and services sold abroad are <strong>exports.</strong></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p21" block_type="txt">As illustrated by the opening story, imports and exports have taken on an increasingly important role in the U.S. economy. Over the last 55 years, both imports into and exports from the United States have grown faster than the U.S. economy. Panel (a) of <link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-fig-3">Figure 20-1</link> shows how the values of U.S. imports and exports have grown as a percentage of gross domestic product (GDP). Panel (b) shows imports and exports as a percentage of GDP for a number of countries. It shows that foreign trade is significantly more important for many other countries than it is for the United States. (Japan is the exception.)</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-fig-3" block_type="figure" numbered="true" number="20-1" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<caption><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-fig-3"><phrase block_type="fig-label"><phrase block_type="fig"><strong>FIGURE</strong></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_num"><strong>20-1</strong></phrase></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_title">The Growing Importance of International Trade</phrase></link></caption>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-img-5" alt="image" src="images/KrugESS4e_fig_20_01.jpg"/>
<caption>Panel (a) illustrates the fact that over the past 55 years, the United States has exported a steadily growing share of its GDP to other countries and imported a growing share of what it consumes. Panel (b) demonstrates that international trade is significantly more important to many other countries than it is to the United States, with the exception of Japan.</caption>
<asset_source><em>Data from:</em> Bureau of Economic Analysis [panel (a)] and World Development Indicators [panel (b)].</asset_source>
</figure>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-exp3-2" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p22" block_type="mn-gl-def"><strong>Globalization</strong> is the phenomenon of growing economic linkages among countries.</p>
</box>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-exp3-3" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p23" block_type="mn-gl-def"><strong>Hyperglobalization</strong> is the phenomenon of extremely high levels of international trade.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p24" block_type="txt">Foreign trade isn&#8217;t the only way countries interact economically. In the modern world, investors from one country often invest funds in another nation; many companies are multinational, with subsidiaries operating in several countries; and a growing number of individuals work in a country different from the one in which they were born. The growth of all these forms of economic linkages among countries is often called <strong>globalization.</strong> Certain sectors of the economy are characterized by extremely high levels of international trade. This <strong>hyperglobalization</strong> is often the result of supply chains of production that span the globe, in which each stage of a good&#8217;s production takes place in a different country&#8212;all made possible by advances in communication and transportation technology.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_571" block_type="page_start">571</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p25" block_type="txt">To understand why international trade occurs and why economists believe it is beneficial to the economy, let&#8217;s begin with a review of the concept of comparative advantage.</p>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-sec2-1" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="20" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="571">
<section-metadata><section-title>Production Possibilities and Comparative Advantage, Revisited</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p26" block_type="txt-ni">To produce phones, any country must use resources&#8212;land, labor, capital, and so on&#8212;that could have been used to produce other things. The potential production of other goods a country must forgo to produce a phone is the opportunity cost of that phone.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p27" block_type="txt">In some cases, it&#8217;s easy to see why the opportunity cost of producing a good is especially low in a given country. Consider, for example, shrimp&#8212;much of which now comes from seafood farms in Vietnam and Thailand. It&#8217;s a lot easier to produce shrimp in Vietnam, where the climate is nearly ideal and there&#8217;s plenty of coastal land suitable for shellfish farming, than it is in the United States. </p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p28" block_type="txt">Conversely, other goods are not produced as easily in Vietnam as in the United States. For example, Vietnam doesn&#8217;t have the base of skilled workers and technological know-how that makes the United States so good at producing many high-technology goods. So the opportunity cost of a ton of shrimp, in terms of other goods such as aircraft, is much less in Vietnam than it is in the United States.</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-fig-4" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="right" width="medium" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-img-6" alt="image" src="images/KrugESS4e_20UN01.jpg"/>
<caption>The opportunity cost of assembling smartphones in China is lower, giving it a comparative advantage.</caption>
<asset_source>Shutterstock</asset_source>
</figure>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p29" block_type="txt">In other cases, matters are a bit less obvious. It&#8217;s as easy to assemble smartphones in the United States as it is in China, and Chinese electronics workers are, if anything, less efficient than their U.S. counterparts. But Chinese workers are a lot less productive than U.S. workers in other areas, such as automobile and chemical production. This means that diverting a Chinese worker into assembling phones reduces output of other goods less than diverting a U.S. worker into assembling phones. That is, the opportunity cost of assembling phones in China is less than it is in the United States.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p30" block_type="txt">Notice that we said the opportunity cost of <em>assembling</em> phones. As we&#8217;ve seen, most of the value of a &#8220;Chinese made&#8221; phone actually comes from other countries. For the sake of exposition, however, let&#8217;s ignore that complication and consider a hypothetical case in which China makes phones from scratch.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p31" block_type="txt">So we say that China has a comparative advantage in producing smartphones. Let&#8217;s repeat the definition of comparative advantage from <link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch02.xml">Chapter 2</link>: <em>A country has a comparative advantage in producing a good or service if the opportunity cost of producing the good or service is lower for that country than for other countries.</em></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p32" block_type="txt"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-fig-5">Figure 20-2</link> provides a hypothetical numerical example of comparative advantage in international trade. We assume that only two goods are produced and consumed, phones and Ford trucks, and that there are only two countries in the world, the United States and China. The figure shows hypothetical production possibility frontiers for the United States and China.</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-fig-5" block_type="figure" numbered="true" number="20-2" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<caption><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-fig-5"><phrase block_type="fig-label"><phrase block_type="fig"><strong>FIGURE</strong></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_num"><strong>20-2</strong></phrase></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_title">Comparative Advantage and the Production Possibility Frontier</phrase></link></caption>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-img-7" alt="image" src="images/KrugESS4e_fig_20_02.jpg"/>
<caption>The U.S. opportunity cost of 1 million phones in terms of trucks is 1,000: for every 1 million phones, 1,000 trucks must be forgone. The Chinese opportunity cost of 1 million phones in terms of trucks is 250 for every additional 1 million phones, only 250 trucks must be forgone. As a result, the United States has a comparative advantage in truck production, and China has a comparative advantage in phone production. In autarky, each country is forced to consume only what it produces: 50,000 trucks and 50 million phones for the United States; 25,000 trucks and 100 million phones for China.</caption>
</figure>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-exp3-4" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p33" block_type="mn-gl-def">The <strong>Ricardian model of international trade</strong> analyzes international trade under the assumption that opportunity costs are constant.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p34" block_type="txt">As in <link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch02.xml">Chapter 2</link>, we simplify the model by assuming that the production possibility frontiers are straight lines, rather than the more realistic bowed-out shape. The straight-line shape implies that the opportunity cost of a phone in terms of trucks in each country is constant&#8212;it does not depend on how many units of each good the country produces. The analysis of international trade under the assumption that opportunity costs are constant, which makes production possibility frontiers straight lines, is known as the <strong>Ricardian model of international trade,</strong> named after the English economist David Ricardo, who introduced this analysis in the early nineteenth century.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p35" block_type="txt">In <link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-fig-5">Figure 20-2</link> we show a situation in which the United States can produce 100,000 trucks if it produces no phones, or 100 million phones if it produces no trucks. Thus, the slope of the U.S. production possibility frontier, or <em>PPF,</em> is &#8722; 100,000/100 = &#8722;1,000. That is, to produce an additional million phones, the United States must forgo the production of 1,000 trucks.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_572" block_type="page_start">572</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p36" block_type="txt">Similarly, China can produce 50,000 trucks if it produces no phones or 200 million phones if it produces no trucks. Thus, the slope of China&#8217;s <em>PPF</em> is &#8722; 50,000/200 = &#8722; 250. That is, to produce an additional million phones, China must forgo the production of 250 trucks.</p>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-exp3-5" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p37" block_type="mn-gl-def"><strong>Autarky</strong> is a situation in which a country does not trade with other countries.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p38" block_type="txt">Economists use the term <strong>autarky</strong> to refer to a situation in which a country does not trade with other countries. We assume that in autarky the United States chooses to produce and consume 50 million phones and 50,000 trucks. We also assume that in autarky China produces 100 million phones and 25,000 trucks.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p39" block_type="txt">The trade-offs facing the two countries when they don&#8217;t trade are summarized in <link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-tab-1">Table 20-1</link>. As you can see, the United States has a comparative advantage in the production of trucks because it has a lower opportunity cost in terms of phones than China has: producing a truck costs the United States only 1,000 phones, while it costs China 4,000 phones. Correspondingly, China has a comparative advantage in phone production: 1 million phones costs only 250 trucks, while it costs the United States 1,000 trucks.</p>
<table id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-tab-1" block_type="table" numbered="false" caption-placement="Top" data-href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-tab-1" data-target="_pop">
<table_caption><strong><phrase block_type="tbl">TABLE</phrase> <phrase block_type="tbl_num">20-1</phrase></strong> <phrase block_type="tbl_title">U.S. and Chinese Opportunity Costs of Phones and Trucks</phrase></table_caption>
<tbody>
<tr class="tbl-hdr-bg">
<td></td>
<td><strong>U.S. Opportunity Cost</strong></td>
<td></td>
<td><strong>Chinese Opportunity Cost</strong></td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tbl-rborder tbl-ljust"><strong>1 million phones</strong></td>
<td class="tbl-ljust">1,000 trucks</td>
<td>&#62;</td>
<td class="tbl-ljust">250 trucks</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-dark">
<td class="tbl-rborder tbl-ljust"><strong>1 truck</strong></td>
<td class="tbl-ljust">1,000 phones</td>
<td>&#60;</td>
<td class="tbl-ljust">4,000 phones </td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p40" block_type="txt">As we learned in <link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch02.xml">Chapter 2</link>, each country can do better by engaging in trade than it could by not trading. A country can accomplish this by specializing in the production of the good in which it has a comparative advantage and exporting that good, while importing the good in which it has a comparative disadvantage.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p41" block_type="txt">Let&#8217;s see how this works.</p>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-sec2-2" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="20" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="572">
<section-metadata><section-title>The Gains from International Trade</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p42" block_type="txt-ni"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-fig-6">Figure 20-3</link> illustrates how both countries can gain from specialization and trade, by showing a hypothetical rearrangement of production and consumption that allows <em>each</em> country to consume more of <em>both</em> goods. Again, panel (a) represents the United States and panel (b) represents China. In each panel we indicate again the autarky production and consumption assumed in <link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-fig-5">Figure 20-2</link>.</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-fig-6" block_type="figure" numbered="true" number="20-3" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<caption><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-fig-6"><phrase block_type="fig-label"><phrase block_type="fig"><strong>FIGURE</strong></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_num"><strong>20-3</strong></phrase></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_title">The Gains from International Trade</phrase></link></caption>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-img-8" alt="image" src="images/KrugESS4e_fig_20_03.jpg"/>
<caption>Trade increases world production of both goods, allowing both countries to consume more. Here, each country specializes its production as a result of trade: the United States concentrates on producing trucks, and China concentrates on producing phones. Total world production of both goods rises, which means that it is possible for both countries to consume more of both goods.</caption>
</figure>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_573" block_type="page_start">573</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p43" block_type="txt">Once trade becomes possible, however, everything changes. With trade, each country can move to producing only the good in which it has a comparative advantage&#8212;trucks for the United States and phones for China. Because the world production of both goods is now higher than in autarky, trade makes it possible for each country to consume more of both goods.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p44" block_type="txt"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-tab-2">Table 20-2</link> sums up the changes as a result of trade and shows why both countries can gain. The left part of the table shows the autarky situation, before trade, in which each country must produce the goods it consumes. The right part of the table shows what happens as a result of trade. After trade, the United States specializes in the production of trucks, producing 100,000 trucks and no phones; China specializes in the production of phones, producing 200 million phones and no trucks.</p>
<table id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-tab-2" block_type="table" numbered="false" caption-placement="Top" data-href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-tab-2" data-target="_pop">
<table_caption><strong><phrase block_type="tbl">TABLE</phrase> <phrase block_type="tbl_num">20-2</phrase></strong> <phrase block_type="tbl_title">How the United States and China Gain from Trade</phrase></table_caption>
<tbody>
<tr class="tbl-hdr-bg">
<td colspan="2" rowspan="2" class="tbl-rborder"></td>
<td colspan="2" class="tbl-rborder tbl-bborder"><strong>In Autarky</strong></td>
<td colspan="3" class="tbl-rborder tbl-rborder"><strong>With Trade</strong></td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-hdr-bg">
<td class="tbl-rborder"><strong>Production</strong></td>
<td class="tbl-rborder"><strong>Consumption</strong></td>
<td class="tbl-rborder"><strong>Production</strong></td>
<td class="tbl-rborder"><strong>Consumption</strong></td>
<td><strong>Gains from trade</strong></td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td rowspan="2" class="tbl-rborder tbl-bborder tbl-ljust">United States</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder tbl-bborder tbl-ljust">Million phones</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder tbl-bborder">50</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder tbl-bborder">50</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder tbl-bborder">0</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder tbl-bborder">75</td>
<td class="tbl-bborder">&#43;25</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-dark">
<td class="tbl-rborder tbl-ljust">Trucks</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder">50,000</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder">50,000</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder">100,000</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder">62,500</td>
<td class="tbl-bborder">&#43;1 2,500</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-dark">
<td rowspan="2" class="tbl-rborder tbl-ljust">China</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder tbl-ljust tbl-bborder">Million phones</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder tbl-bborder">100</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder tbl-bborder">100</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder tbl-bborder">200</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder tbl-bborder">125</td>
<td class="tbl-bborder">&#43;25</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-dark">
<td class="tbl-rborder tbl-ljust">Trucks </td>
<td class="tbl-rborder">25,000</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder">25,000</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder">0</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder">37,500</td>
<td>&#43;12,500</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p45" block_type="txt">The result is a rise in total world production of both goods. As you can see in the <link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-tab-2">Table 20-2</link> column at far right showing consumption with trade, the United States is able to consume both more trucks and more phones than before, even though it no longer produces phones, because it can import phones from China. China can also consume more of both goods, even though it no longer produces trucks, because it can import trucks from the United States.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_574" block_type="page_start">574</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p46" block_type="txt">The key to this mutual gain is the fact that trade liberates both countries from self-sufficiency&#8212;from the need to produce the same mixes of goods they consume. Because each country can concentrate on producing the good in which it has a comparative advantage, total world production rises, making a higher standard of living possible in both nations.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p47" block_type="txt">In this example we have simply assumed the post-trade consumption bundles of the two countries. In fact, the consumption choices of a country reflect both the preferences of its residents and the <em>relative prices</em>&#8212;the prices of one good in terms of another in international markets. Although we have not explicitly given the price of trucks in terms of phones, that price is implicit in our example: China sells the United States the 75 million phones the U.S. consumes in return for the 37,500 trucks China consumes, so 1 million phones are traded for 500 trucks. This tells us that the price of a truck on world markets must be equal to the price of 2,000 phones in our example.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p48" block_type="txt">One requirement that the relative price must satisfy is that no country pays a relative price greater than its opportunity cost of obtaining the good in autarky. That is, the United States won&#8217;t pay more than 1,000 trucks for one million phones from China, and China won&#8217;t pay more than 4,000 phones for each truck from the United States. Once this requirement is satisfied, the actual relative price in international trade is determined by supply and demand&#8212;and we&#8217;ll turn to supply and demand in international trade in the next section. However, first let&#8217;s look more deeply into the nature of the gains from trade.</p>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-sec2-3" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="20" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="574">
<section-metadata><section-title>Comparative Advantage versus Absolute Advantage</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p49" block_type="txt-ni">It&#8217;s easy to accept the idea that Vietnam and Thailand have a comparative advantage in shrimp production: they have a tropical climate that&#8217;s better suited to shrimp farming than that of the United States (even along the Gulf Coast), and they have a lot of usable coastal area. So the United States imports shrimp from Vietnam and Thailand. In other cases, however, it may be harder to understand why we import certain goods from abroad.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p50" block_type="txt">U.S. imports of phones from China are a case in point. There&#8217;s nothing about China&#8217;s climate or resources that makes it especially good at assembling electronic devices. In fact, it almost surely would take fewer hours of labor to assemble a smartphone or a tablet in the United States than in China.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p51" block_type="txt">Why, then, do we buy phones assembled in China? Because the gains from trade depend on <em>comparative advantage,</em> not absolute advantage. Yes, it would take less labor to assemble a phone in the United States than in China. That is, the productivity of Chinese electronics workers is less than that of their U.S. counterparts. But what determines comparative advantage is not the amount of resources used to produce a good but the opportunity cost of that good&#8212;here, the quantity of other goods forgone in order to produce a phone. And the opportunity cost of phones is lower in China than in the United States.</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-fig-7" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="right" width="medium" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-img-9" alt="image" src="images/KrugESS4e_20UN02.jpg"/>
<caption>The tropical climates of Vietnam and Thailand give them a comparative advantage in shrimp production.</caption>
<asset_source>Pornchai Kittiwongsakul/AFP/Getty Images</asset_source>
</figure>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p52" block_type="txt">Here&#8217;s how it works: Chinese workers have low productivity compared with U.S. workers in the electronics industry. But Chinese workers have even lower productivity compared with U.S. workers in other industries. Because Chinese labor productivity in industries other than electronics is relatively very low, producing a phone in China, even though it takes a lot of labor, does not require forgoing the production of large quantities of other goods. </p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p53" block_type="txt">In the United States, the opposite is true: very high productivity in other industries (such as automobiles) means that assembling electronic products in the United States, even though it doesn&#8217;t require much labor, requires sacrificing lots of other goods. So the opportunity cost of producing electronics is less in China than in the United States. Despite its lower labor productivity, China has a comparative advantage in the production of many consumer electronics, although the United States has an absolute advantage.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_575" block_type="page_start">575</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p54" block_type="txt">The source of China&#8217;s comparative advantage in consumer electronics is reflected in global markets by the wages Chinese workers are paid. That&#8217;s because a country&#8217;s wage rates, in general, reflect its labor productivity. In countries where labor is highly productive in many industries, employers are willing to pay high wages to attract workers, so competition among employers leads to an overall high wage rate. In countries where labor is less productive, competition for workers is less intense and wage rates are correspondingly lower.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p55" block_type="txt">The following Global Comparison shows that there is a strong relationship between overall levels of productivity and wage rates around the world. Because China has generally low productivity, it has a relatively low wage rate. Low wages, in turn, give China a cost advantage in producing goods where its productivity is only moderately low, like consumer electronics. As a result, it&#8217;s cheaper to produce these goods in China than in the United States.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p56" block_type="txt">The kind of trade that takes place between low-wage, low-productivity economies like China and high-wage, high-productivity economies like the United States gives rise to two common misperceptions.</p>
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-list-2" type="ordered" block_type="numbered">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p57" block_type="nl-first">The <em>pauper labor fallacy</em> is the belief that when a country with high wages imports goods produced by workers who are paid low wages, this must hurt the standard of living of workers in the importing country.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p58" block_type="nl-last">The <em>sweatshop labor fallacy</em> is the belief that trade must be bad for workers in poor exporting countries because those workers are paid very low wages by our standards.</p></li>
</list>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p59" block_type="txt">Both fallacies miss the nature of gains from trade: it&#8217;s to the advantage of both countries if the poorer, lower-wage country exports goods in which it has a comparative advantage, even if its cost advantage in these goods depends on low wages. That is, both countries are able to achieve a higher standard of living through trade.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_576" block_type="page_start">576</p>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-bx4-1" block_type="bx4-h">
<box-metadata><box-title><image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-img-10" alt="image" src="images/World_icon_no_type.jpg"/> <phrase block_type="gc1">GLOBAL</phrase> <phrase block_type="gc2">COMPARISON</phrase></box-title></box-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p60" block_type="bx4-t"><strong>Productivity and Wages Around the World</strong></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p61" block_type="bx4-txt-ni"><phrase block_type="dropcap">I</phrase>s it true that both the pauper labor argument and the sweatshop labor argument are fallacies? Yes, it is. The real explanation for low wages in poor countries is low overall productivity.</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-fig-8" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="right" width="medium" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-img-11" alt="image" src="images/KrugESS4e_20UN03.jpg"/>
<asset_source><em>Data from:</em> The Conference Board; Penn World Table 8.0.</asset_source>
</figure>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p62" block_type="bx4-txt">The graph shows estimates of labor productivity, measured by the value of output (GDP) per worker, and wages, measured by the hourly compensation of the average worker, for several countries in 2012. Both productivity and wages are expressed as percentages of U.S. productivity and wages; for example, productivity and wages in Japan were 70&#37; and 101&#37;, respectively, of their U.S. levels. You can see the strong positive relationship between productivity and wages. The relationship isn&#8217;t perfect. For example, Norway has higher wages than its productivity might lead you to expect. But simple comparisons of wages give a misleading sense of labor costs in poor countries: their low wage advantage is mostly offset by low productivity.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p64" block_type="txt">It&#8217;s particularly important to understand that buying a good made by someone who is paid much lower wages than most U.S. workers doesn&#8217;t necessarily imply that you&#8217;re taking advantage of that person. It depends on the alternatives. Because workers in poor countries have low productivity across the board, they are offered low wages whether they produce goods exported to America or goods sold in local markets. A job that looks terrible by rich-country standards can be a step up for someone in a poor country.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p65" block_type="txt">International trade that depends on low-wage exports can nonetheless raise the exporting country&#8217;s standard of living. This is especially true of very-low-wage nations. For example, Bangladesh and similar countries would be much poorer than they are&#8212;their citizens might even be starving&#8212;if they weren&#8217;t able to export goods such as clothing based on their low wage rates. </p>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-sec2-4" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="20" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="576">
<section-metadata><section-title>Sources of Comparative Advantage</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p66" block_type="txt-ni">International trade is driven by comparative advantage, but where does comparative advantage come from? Economists who study international trade have found three main sources of comparative advantage:</p>
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-list-3" type="ordered" block_type="numbered">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p67" block_type="nl-first">International differences in <em>climate</em></p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p68" block_type="nl-mid">International differences in <em>factor endowments</em></p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p69" block_type="nl-last">International differences in <em>technology</em></p></li>
</list>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p70" block_type="txt-3"><phrase block_type="h3"><strong>Differences in Climate</strong></phrase> One key reason the opportunity cost of producing shrimp in Vietnam and Thailand is less than in the United States is that shrimp need warm water&#8212;Vietnam has plenty of that, but America doesn&#8217;t. In general, differences in climate play a significant role in international trade. Tropical countries export tropical products like coffee, sugar, bananas, and shrimp. Countries in the temperate zones export crops like wheat and corn. Some trade is even driven by the difference in seasons between the northern and southern hemispheres: winter deliveries of Chilean grapes and New Zealand apples have become commonplace in U.S. and European supermarkets.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p71" block_type="txt-3"><phrase block_type="h3"><strong>Differences in Factor Endowments</strong></phrase> Canada is a major exporter of forest products&#8212;lumber and products derived from lumber, like pulp and paper&#8212;to the United States. These exports don&#8217;t reflect the special skill of Canadian lumberjacks. Canada has a comparative advantage in forest products because its forested area is much greater compared to the size of its labor force than the ratio of forestland to the labor force in the United States.</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-fig-9" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="right" width="medium" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-img-12" alt="image" src="images/KrugESS4e_20UN04.jpg"/>
<caption>A greater endowment of forestland gives Canada a comparative advantage in forest products.</caption>
<asset_source>Johner Images/Alamy</asset_source>
</figure>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p72" block_type="txt">Forestland, like labor and capital, is a <em>factor of production:</em> an input used to produce goods and services. (Recall that the factors of production are land, labor, physical capital, and human capital.) Due to history and geography, the mix of available factors of production differs among countries, providing an important source of comparative advantage. The relationship between comparative advantage and factor availability is found in an influential model of international trade, the <em>Heckscher&#8211;Ohlin model,</em> developed by two Swedish economists in the first half of the twentieth century.</p>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-exp3-6" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p73" block_type="mn-gl-def">The <strong>factor intensity</strong> of production of a good is a measure of which factor is used in relatively greater quantities than other factors in production.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p74" block_type="txt">Two key concepts in the model are <em>factor abundance</em> and <em>factor intensity.</em> Factor abundance refers to how large a country&#8217;s supply of a factor is relative to its supply of other factors. Factor intensity refers to the fact that producers use different ratios of factors of production in the production of different goods. For example, oil refineries use much more capital per worker than clothing factories. Economists use the term <strong>factor intensity</strong> to describe this difference among goods: oil refining is capital-intensive, because it tends to use a high ratio of capital to labor, but phone production is labor-intensive, because it tends to use a high ratio of labor to capital.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_577" block_type="page_start">577</p>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-exp3-7" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p75" block_type="mn-gl-def">According to the <strong>Heckscher&#8211;Ohlin model,</strong> a country has a comparative advantage in a good whose production is intensive in the factors that are abundantly available in that country.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p76" block_type="txt">According to the <strong>Heckscher&#8211;Ohlin model,</strong> <em>a country that has an abundant supply of a factor of production will have a comparative advantage in goods whose production is intensive in that factor.</em> So a country that has a relative abundance of capital will have a comparative advantage in capital-intensive industries such as oil refining, but a country that has a relative abundance of labor will have a comparative advantage in labor-intensive industries such as phone production.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p77" block_type="txt">The basic intuition behind this result is simple and based on opportunity cost. The opportunity cost of a given factor&#8212;the value that the factor would generate in alternative uses&#8212;is low for a country when it is relatively abundant in that factor. Relative to the United States, China has an abundance of low-skilled labor. As a result, the opportunity cost of the production of low-skilled, labor-intensive goods is lower in China than in the United States.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p78" block_type="txt">The most dramatic example of the validity of the Heckscher&#8211;Ohlin model is world trade in clothing. Clothing production is a labor-intensive activity: it doesn&#8217;t take much physical capital, nor does it require a lot of human capital in the form of highly educated workers. So you would expect labor-abundant countries such as China and Bangladesh to have a comparative advantage in clothing production. And they do.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p79" block_type="txt">The fact that international trade is the result of differences in factor endowments helps explain another fact: international specialization of production is often <em>incomplete.</em> That is, a country often maintains some domestic production of a good that it imports. A good example of this is the United States and oil. Saudi Arabia exports oil to the United States because Saudi Arabia has an abundant supply of oil relative to its other factors of production; the United States exports medical devices to Saudi Arabia because it has an abundant supply of expertise in medical technology relative to its other factors of production. But the United States also produces some oil domestically because the size of its domestic oil reserves in Texas, Alaska, and now, increasingly, its oil shale reserves elsewhere, makes it economical to do so.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p80" block_type="txt">In our supply and demand analysis in the next section, we&#8217;ll consider incomplete specialization by a country to be the norm. We should emphasize, however, that the fact that countries often incompletely specialize does not in any way change the conclusion that there are gains from trade.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p81" block_type="txt-3"><phrase block_type="h3"><strong>Differences in Technology</strong></phrase> In the 1970s and 1980s, Japan became by far the world&#8217;s largest exporter of automobiles, selling large numbers to the United States and the rest of the world. Japan&#8217;s comparative advantage in automobiles wasn&#8217;t the result of climate. Nor can it easily be attributed to differences in factor endowments: aside from a scarcity of land, Japan&#8217;s mix of available factors is quite similar to that in other advanced countries. Instead, Japan&#8217;s comparative advantage in automobiles was based on the superior production techniques developed by its manufacturers, which allowed them to produce more cars with a given amount of labor and capital than their American or European counterparts.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p82" block_type="txt">Japan&#8217;s comparative advantage in automobiles was caused by differences in technology&#8212;the techniques used in production.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p83" block_type="txt">The causes of differences in technology are somewhat mysterious. Sometimes they seem to be based on knowledge accumulated through experience&#8212;for example, Switzerland&#8217;s comparative advantage in watches reflects a long tradition of watchmaking. Sometimes they are the result of a set of innovations that for some reason occur in one country but not in others. Technological advantage, however, is often transitory. By adopting lean production, American auto manufacturers have now closed much of the gap in productivity with their Japanese competitors. In addition, Europe&#8217;s aircraft industry has closed a similar gap with the U.S. aircraft industry. At any given point in time, however, differences in technology are a major source of comparative advantage.</p>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-bx2-1" block_type="bx-2-h">
<box-metadata><box-title><phrase block_type="title">ECONOMICS</phrase> <phrase block_type="number"><em>in Action</em></phrase><image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-img-13" alt="image" src="images/world_view_icon.jpg"/></box-title></box-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p84" block_type="bx-2-t"><strong>How Hong Kong Lost Its Shirts</strong></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_578" block_type="page_start">578</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p85" block_type="bx2-first"><phrase block_type="dropcap">T</phrase>he rise of Hong Kong was one of the most improbable-sounding economic success stories of the twentieth century. When a communist regime took over China in 1949, Hong Kong&#8212;which was still a British colony&#8212;became in effect a city without a hinterland, largely cut off from economic relations with the territory just over the border. Since Hong Kong had until that point made a living largely by serving as a point of entry into China, you might have expected the city to languish. Instead, however, Hong Kong prospered, to such an extent that today the city&#8212;now returned to China, but governed as a special autonomous region&#8212;has a GDP per capita comparable to that of the United States.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p86" block_type="bx2-txt">During much of its ascent, Hong Kong&#8217;s rise rested, above all, on its clothing industry. In 1980 Hong Kong&#8217;s garment and textile sectors employed almost 450,000 workers, close to 20&#37; of total employment. These workers overwhelmingly made apparel&#8212;shirts, trousers, dresses, and more&#8212;for export, especially to the United States.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p87" block_type="bx2-txt">Since then, however, the Hong Kong clothing industry has fallen sharply in size&#8212;in fact, it has almost disappeared. So, too, have Hong Kong&#8217;s apparel exports. <link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-fig-10">Figure 20-4</link> shows Hong Kong&#8217;s share of U.S. apparel imports since 1989, along with the share of a relative newcomer to the industry, Bangladesh. As you can see, Hong Kong has more or less dropped off the chart, while Bangladesh&#8217;s share has risen significantly in recent years.</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-fig-10" block_type="figure" numbered="true" number="20-4" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="right" width="medium" border="true"/>
<caption><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-fig-10"><phrase block_type="fig-label"><phrase block_type="fig"><strong>FIGURE</strong></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_num"><strong>20-4</strong></phrase></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_title">Education, Skill Intensity, and Trade</phrase></link></caption>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-img-14" alt="image" src="images/KrugESS4e_fig_20_04.jpg"/>
<asset_source><em>Data from:</em> U.S. International Trade Administration.</asset_source>
</figure>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p88" block_type="bx2-txt">Why did Hong Kong lose its comparative advantage in making shirts, pants, and so on? It wasn&#8217;t because the city&#8217;s garment workers became less productive. Instead, it was because the city got better at other things. Apparel production is a labor-intensive, relatively low-tech industry; comparative advantage in that industry has historically always rested with poor, labor-abundant economies. Hong Kong no longer fits that description; Bangladesh does. Hong Kong&#8217;s garment industry was a victim of the city&#8217;s success.</p>
</box>
<box title="Quick Review" numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-bx5-1" block_type="sr-1-h">
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-list-4" type="unordered" block_type="redbullet">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p89" block_type="sr1-bl"><strong>Imports</strong> and <strong>exports</strong> account for a growing share of the U.S. economy and the economies of many other countries.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p90" block_type="sr1-bl">The growth of international trade and other international linkages is known as <strong>globalization.</strong> Extremely high levels of international trade are known as <strong>hyperglobalization.</strong></p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p91" block_type="sr1-bl">International trade is driven by comparative advantage. <strong>The Ricardian model of international trade</strong> shows that trade between two countries makes both countries better off than they would be in <strong>autarky&#8212;</strong>that is, there are gains from international trade.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p92" block_type="sr1-bl">The main sources of comparative advantage are international differences in climate, factor endowments, and technology.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p93" block_type="sr1-bl">The <strong>Heckscher&#8211;Ohlin model</strong> shows how comparative advantage can arise from differences in factor endowments: goods differ in their <strong>factor intensity,</strong> and countries tend to export goods that are intensive in the factors they have in abundance.</p></li>
</list>
</box>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-bx6-1" block_type="sr2-h">
<box-metadata><box-title><phrase block_type="title">Check Your Understanding</phrase> <phrase block_type="number">20-1</phrase></box-title></box-metadata>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-cyuquestion-1" block_type="q_cyu" number="1">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p94" block_type="sr2-nl-first"><phrase block_type="qnum">1.</phrase> In the United States, the opportunity cost of 1 ton of corn is 50 bicycles. In China, the opportunity cost of 1 bicycle is 0.01 ton of corn.</p>
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-list-5" type="ordered" block_type="loweralpha">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p95" block_type="sr2-nl-lvl2">Determine the pattern of comparative advantage.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p96" block_type="sr2-nl-lvl2">In autarky, the United States can produce 200,000 bicycles if no corn is produced, and China can produce 3,000 tons of corn if no bicycles are produced. Draw each country&#8217;s production possibility frontier assuming constant opportunity cost, with tons of corn on the vertical axis and bicycles on the horizontal axis.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p97" block_type="sr2-nl-lvl2">With trade, each country specializes its production. The United States consumes 1,000 tons of corn and 200,000 bicycles; China consumes 3,000 tons of corn and 100,000 bicycles. Indicate the production and consumption points on your diagrams, and use them to explain the gains from trade.</p></li>
</list>
</question>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-cyuquestion-2" block_type="q_cyu" number="2">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p98" block_type="sr2-nl-mid"><phrase block_type="qnum">2.</phrase> Explain the following patterns of trade using the Heckscher&#8211;Ohlin model.</p>
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-list-6" type="ordered" block_type="loweralpha">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p99" block_type="sr2-nl-lvl2">France exports wine to the United States, and the United States exports movies to France.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p100" block_type="sr2-nl-lvl2">Brazil exports shoes to the United States, and the United States exports shoe-making machinery to Brazil.</p></li>
</list>
</question>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p101" block_type="sr2-nl-fn">Solutions appear at back of book.</p>
</box>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-sec1-2" block_type="h1" title="" chapter="20" numbered="true" level="1" print_page="579">
<section-metadata><section-title>Supply, Demand, and International Trade</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_579" block_type="page_start">579</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p102" block_type="txt-ni">Simple models of comparative advantage are helpful for understanding the fundamental causes of international trade. However, to analyze the effects of international trade at a more detailed level and to understand trade policy, it helps to return to the supply and demand model. We&#8217;ll start by looking at the effects of imports on domestic producers and consumers, then turn to the effects of exports.</p>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-sec2-5" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="20" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="579">
<section-metadata><section-title>The Effects of Imports</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p103" block_type="txt-ni"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-fig-11">Figure 20-5</link> shows the U.S. market for phones, ignoring international trade for a moment. It introduces a few new concepts: the <em>domestic demand curve,</em> the <em>domestic supply curve,</em> and the domestic or autarky price.</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-fig-11" block_type="figure" numbered="true" number="20-5" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<caption><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-fig-11"><phrase block_type="fig-label"><phrase block_type="fig"><strong>FIGURE</strong></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_num"><strong>20-5</strong></phrase></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_title">Consumer and Producer Surplus in Autarky</phrase></link></caption>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-img-15" alt="image" src="images/KrugESS4e_fig_20_05.jpg"/>
<caption>In the absence of trade, the domestic price is <em>P<sub>A</sub></em>, the autarky price at which the domestic supply curve and the domestic demand curve intersect. The quantity produced and consumed domestically is <em>Q<sub>A</sub></em>. Consumer surplus is represented by the blue-shaded area, and producer surplus is represented by the red-shaded area.</caption>
</figure>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-exp3-8" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p104" block_type="mn-gl-def">The <strong>domestic demand curve</strong> shows how the quantity of a good demanded by domestic consumers depends on the price of that good.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p105" block_type="txt">The <strong>domestic demand curve</strong> shows how the quantity of a good demanded by residents of a country depends on the price of that good. Why &#8220;domestic&#8221;? Because people living in other countries may demand the good, too. Once we introduce international trade, we need to distinguish between purchases of a good by domestic consumers and purchases by foreign consumers. So the domestic demand curve reflects only the demand of residents of our own country.</p>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-exp3-9" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p106" block_type="mn-gl-def">The <strong>domestic supply curve</strong> shows how the quantity of a good supplied by domestic producers depends on the price of that good. </p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p107" block_type="txt">Similarly, the <strong>domestic supply curve</strong> shows how the quantity of a good supplied by producers inside our own country depends on the price of that good. Once we introduce international trade, we need to distinguish between the supply of domestic producers and foreign supply&#8212;supply brought in from abroad.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p108" block_type="txt">In autarky, with no international trade in phones, the equilibrium in this market would be determined by the intersection of the domestic demand and domestic supply curves, point <em>A.</em> The equilibrium price of phones would be <em>P<sub>A</sub>,</em> and the equilibrium quantity of phones produced and consumed would be <em>Q<sub>A</sub></em>. As always, both consumers and producers gain from the existence of the domestic market. In autarky, consumer surplus would be equal to the area of the blue-shaded triangle in <link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-fig-11">Figure 20-5</link>. Producer surplus would be equal to the area of the red-shaded triangle. And total surplus would be equal to the sum of these two shaded triangles.</p>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-exp3-10" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p109" block_type="mn-gl-def">The <strong>world price</strong> of a good is the price at which that good can be bought or sold abroad.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p110" block_type="txt">Now let&#8217;s imagine opening up this market to imports. To do this, we must make an assumption about the supply of imports. The simplest assumption, which we will adopt here, is that unlimited quantities of phones can be purchased from abroad at a fixed price, known as the world price of phones. <link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-fig-12">Figure 20-6</link> shows a situation in which the <strong>world price</strong> of a phone, <em>P<sub>W</sub>,</em> is lower than the price of a phone that would prevail in the domestic market in autarky, <em>P<sub>A</sub>.</em></p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-fig-12" block_type="figure" numbered="true" number="20-6" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<caption><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-fig-12"><phrase block_type="fig-label"><phrase block_type="fig"><strong>FIGURE</strong></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_num"><strong>20-6</strong></phrase></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_title">The Domestic Market with Imports</phrase></link></caption>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-img-16" alt="image" src="images/KrugESS4e_fig_20_06.jpg"/>
<caption>Here the world price of phones, <em>P<sub>W</sub></em>, is below the autarky price, <em>P<sub>A</sub></em>. When the economy is opened to international trade, imports enter the domestic market, and the domestic price falls from the autarky price, <em>P<sub>A</sub></em>, to the world price, <em>P<sub>W</sub></em>. As the price falls, the domestic quantity demanded rises from <em>Q<sub>A</sub></em> to <em>Q<sub>D</sub></em> and the domestic quantity supplied falls from <em>Q<sub>A</sub></em> to <em>Q<sub>S</sub></em>. The difference between domestic quantity demanded and domestic quantity supplied at <em>P<sub>W</sub></em>, the quantity <em>Q<sub>D</sub></em> &#8722; <em>Q<sub>S</sub></em>, is filled by imports.</caption>
</figure>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_580" block_type="page_start">580</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p111" block_type="txt">Given that the world price is below the domestic price of a phone, it is profitable for importers to buy phones abroad and resell them domestically. The imported phones increase the supply of phones in the domestic market, driving down the domestic market price. Phones will continue to be imported until the domestic price falls to a level equal to the world price.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p112" block_type="txt">The result is shown in <link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-fig-12">Figure 20-6</link>. Because of imports, the domestic price of a phone falls from <em>P<sub>A</sub></em> to <em>P<sub>W</sub>.</em> The quantity of phones demanded by domestic consumers rises from <em>Q<sub>A</sub></em> to <em>Q<sub>D</sub>,</em> and the quantity supplied by domestic producers falls from <em>Q<sub>A</sub></em> to <em>Q<sub>S</sub>.</em> The difference between the domestic quantity demanded and the domestic quantity supplied, <em>Q<sub>D</sub></em> &#8722; <em>Q<sub>S</sub>,</em> is filled by imports.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p113" block_type="txt">Now let&#8217;s turn to the effects of imports on consumer surplus and producer surplus. Because imports of phones lead to a fall in their domestic price, consumer surplus rises and producer surplus falls. <link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-fig-13">Figure 20-7</link> shows how this works. We label four areas: <em>W, X, Y,</em> and <em>Z.</em> The autarky consumer surplus we identified in <link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-fig-11">Figure 20-5</link> corresponds to <em>W,</em> and the autarky producer surplus corresponds to the sum of <em>X</em> and <em>Y.</em> The fall in the domestic price to the world price leads to an increase in consumer surplus; it increases by <em>X</em> and <em>Z,</em> so consumer surplus now equals the sum of <em>W, X,</em> and <em>Z.</em> At the same time, producers lose <em>X</em> in surplus, so producer surplus now equals only <em>Y.</em></p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-fig-13" block_type="figure" numbered="true" number="20-7" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<caption><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-fig-13"><phrase block_type="fig-label"><phrase block_type="fig"><strong>FIGURE</strong></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_num"><strong>20-7</strong></phrase></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_title">The Effects of Imports on Surplus</phrase></link></caption>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-img-17" alt="image" src="images/KrugESS4e_fig_20_07.jpg"/>
<caption>When the domestic price falls to <em>P<sub>W</sub></em> as a result of international trade, consumers gain additional surplus (areas <em>X</em> &#43; <em>Z</em>) and producers lose surplus (area <em>X</em>). Because the gains to consumers outweigh the losses to producers, there is an increase in the total surplus in the economy as a whole (area <em>Z</em>).</caption>
</figure>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p114" block_type="txt">The table in <link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-fig-13">Figure 20-7</link> summarizes the changes in consumer and producer surplus when the phone market is opened to imports. Consumers gain surplus equal to the areas <em>X</em> &#43; <em>Z.</em> Producers lose surplus equal to <em>X.</em> So the sum of producer and consumer surplus&#8212;the total surplus generated in the phone market&#8212;increases by <em>Z.</em> As a result of trade, consumers gain and producers lose, but the gain to consumers exceeds the loss to producers. This is an important result. We have just shown that opening up a market to imports leads to a net gain in total surplus, which is what we should have expected given the proposition that there are gains from international trade.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_581" block_type="page_start">581</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p115" block_type="txt">However, we have also learned that although the country as a whole gains, some groups&#8212;in this case, domestic producers of phones&#8212;lose as a result of international trade. As we&#8217;ll see shortly, the fact that international trade typically creates losers as well as winners is crucial for understanding the politics of trade policy.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p116" block_type="txt">We turn next to the case in which a country exports a good.</p>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-sec2-6" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="20" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="581">
<section-metadata><section-title>The Effects of Exports</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p117" block_type="txt-ni"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-fig-14">Figure 20-8</link> shows the effects on a country when it exports a good, in this case trucks. For this example, we assume that unlimited quantities of trucks can be sold abroad at a given world price, <em>P<sub>W</sub>,</em> which is higher than the price that would prevail in the domestic market in autarky, <em>P<sub>A</sub>.</em></p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-fig-14" block_type="figure" numbered="true" number="20-8" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<caption><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-fig-14"><phrase block_type="fig-label"><phrase block_type="fig"><strong>FIGURE</strong></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_num"><strong>20-8</strong></phrase></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_title">The Domestic Market with Exports</phrase></link></caption>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-img-18" alt="image" src="images/KrugESS4e_fig_20_08.jpg"/>
<caption>Here the world price, <em>P<sub>W</sub></em>, is greater than the autarky price, <em>P<sub>A</sub></em>. When the economy is opened to international trade, some of the domestic supply is now exported. The domestic price rises from the autarky price, <em>P<sub>A</sub></em>, to the world price, <em>P<sub>W</sub></em>. As the price rises, the domestic quantity demanded falls from <em>Q<sub>A</sub></em> to <em>Q<sub>D</sub></em> and the domestic quantity supplied rises from <em>Q<sub>A</sub></em> to <em>Q<sub>S</sub></em>. The portion of domestic production that is not consumed domestically, <em>Q<sub>S</sub></em> &#8722; <em>Q<sub>D</sub></em>, is exported.</caption>
</figure>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p118" block_type="txt">The higher world price makes it profitable for exporters to buy trucks domestically and sell them overseas. The purchases of domestic trucks drive the domestic price up until it is equal to the world price. As a result, the quantity demanded by domestic consumers falls from <em>Q<sub>A</sub></em> to <em>Q<sub>D</sub></em> and the quantity supplied by domestic producers rises from <em>Q<sub>A</sub></em> to <em>Q<sub>S</sub></em>. This difference between domestic production and domestic consumption, <em>Q<sub>S</sub></em> &#8722; <em>Q<sub>D</sub></em>, is exported.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p119" block_type="txt">Like imports, exports lead to an overall gain in total surplus for the exporting country but also create losers as well as winners. <link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-fig-15">Figure 20-9</link> shows the effects of truck exports on producer and consumer surplus. In the absence of trade, the price of each truck would be <em>P<sub>A</sub></em>. Consumer surplus in the absence of trade is the sum of areas <em>W</em> and <em>X,</em> and producer surplus is area <em>Y.</em> As a result of trade, price rises from <em>P<sub>A</sub></em> to <em>P<sub>W</sub>,</em> consumer surplus falls to <em>W,</em> and producer surplus rises to <em>Y</em> &#43; <em>X</em> &#43; <em>Z.</em> So producers gain <em>X</em> &#43; <em>Z,</em> consumers lose <em>X,</em> and, as shown in the table accompanying the figure, the economy as a whole gains total surplus in the amount of <em>Z.</em></p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-fig-15" block_type="figure" numbered="true" number="20-9" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<caption><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-fig-15"><phrase block_type="fig-label"><phrase block_type="fig"><strong>FIGURE</strong></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_num"><strong>20-9</strong></phrase></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_title">The Effects of Exports on Surplus</phrase></link></caption>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-img-19" alt="image" src="images/KrugESS4e_fig_20_09.jpg"/>
<caption>When the domestic price rises to <em>P<sub>W</sub></em> as a result of trade, producers gain additional surplus (areas <em>X</em> &#43; <em>Z</em>) but consumers lose surplus (area <em>X</em>). Because the gains to producers outweigh the losses to consumers, there is an increase in the total surplus in the economy as a whole (area <em>Z</em>).</caption>
</figure>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_582" block_type="page_start">582</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p120" block_type="txt">We have learned, then, that imports of a particular good hurt domestic producers of that good but help domestic consumers, whereas exports of a particular good hurt domestic consumers of that good but help domestic producers. In each case, the gains are larger than the losses.</p>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-sec2-7" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="20" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="583">
<section-metadata><section-title>International Trade and Wages</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_583" block_type="page_start">583</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p121" block_type="txt-ni">So far we have focused on the effects of international trade on producers and consumers in a particular industry. For many purposes this is a very helpful approach. However, producers and consumers are not the only parts of society affected by trade&#8212;so are the owners of factors of production. In particular, the owners of labor, land, and capital employed in producing goods that are exported, or goods that compete with imported goods, can be deeply affected by trade.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p122" block_type="txt">Moreover, the effects of trade aren&#8217;t limited to just those industries that export or compete with imports because <em>factors of production can often move between industries.</em> So now we turn our attention to the long-run effects of international trade on income distribution&#8212;how a country&#8217;s total income is allocated among its various factors of production.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p123" block_type="txt">To begin our analysis, consider the position of Maria, an accountant at West Coast Phone Production, Inc. If the economy is opened up to imports of phones from China, the domestic phone industry will contract, and it will hire fewer accountants. But accounting is a profession with employment opportunities in many industries, and Maria might well find a better job in the automobile industry, which expands as a result of international trade. So it may not be appropriate to think of her as a producer of phones who is hurt by competition from imported parts. Rather, we should think of her as an accountant who is affected by phone imports only to the extent that these imports change the wages of accountants in the economy as a whole.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p124" block_type="txt">The wage rate of accountants is a <em>factor price&#8212;</em>the price employers have to pay for the services of a factor of production. One key question about international trade is how it affects factor prices&#8212;not just narrowly defined factors of production like accountants, but broadly defined factors such as capital, unskilled labor, and college-educated labor.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p125" block_type="txt">Earlier we described the Heckscher&#8211;Ohlin model of trade, which states that comparative advantage is determined by a country&#8217;s factor endowment. This model also suggests how international trade affects factor prices in a country: compared to autarky, international trade tends to raise the prices of factors that are abundantly available and reduce the prices of factors that are scarce.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p126" block_type="txt">We won&#8217;t work this out in detail, but the idea is simple. The prices of factors of production, like the prices of goods and services, are determined by supply and demand. If international trade increases the demand for a factor of production, that factor&#8217;s price will rise; if international trade reduces the demand for a factor of production, that factor&#8217;s price will fall.</p>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-exp3-11" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p127" block_type="mn-gl-def"><strong>Exporting industries</strong> produce goods and services that are sold abroad.</p>
</box>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-exp3-12" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p128" block_type="mn-gl-def"><strong>Import-competing industries</strong> produce goods and services that are also imported.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p129" block_type="txt">Now think of a country&#8217;s industries as consisting of two kinds: <strong>exporting industries,</strong> which produce goods and services that are sold abroad, and <strong>import-competing industries,</strong> which produce goods and services that are also imported from abroad. Compared with autarky, international trade leads to higher production in exporting industries and lower production in import-competing industries. This indirectly increases the demand for factors used by exporting industries and decreases the demand for factors used by import-competing industries.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p130" block_type="txt">In addition, the Heckscher&#8211;Ohlin model says that a country tends to export goods that are intensive in its abundant factors and to import goods that are intensive in its scarce factors. <em>So international trade tends to increase the demand for factors that are abundant in our country compared with other countries, and to decrease the demand for factors that are scarce in our country compared with other countries. As a result, the prices of abundant factors tend to rise, and the prices of scarce factors tend to fall as international trade grows.</em></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p131" block_type="txt">In other words, international trade tends to redistribute income toward a country&#8217;s abundant factors and away from its less abundant factors.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_584" block_type="page_start">584</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p132" block_type="txt">U.S. exports tend to be human-capital-intensive (such as high-tech design and Hollywood movies) while U.S. imports tend to be unskilled-labor-intensive (such as phone assembly and clothing production). This suggests that the effect of international trade on the U.S. factor markets is to raise the wage rate of highly educated American workers and reduce the wage rate of unskilled American workers.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p133" block_type="txt">This effect has been a source of much concern in recent years. <em>Wage inequality</em>&#8212;the gap between the wages of high-paid and low-paid workers&#8212;has increased substantially over the last 30 years. Some economists believe that growing international trade is an important factor in that trend. If international trade has the effects predicted by the Heckscher&#8211;Ohlin model, its growth raises the wages of highly educated American workers, who already have relatively high wages, and lowers the wages of less educated American workers, who already have relatively low wages. But keep in mind another phenomenon: trade reduces the income inequality between countries as poor countries improve their standard of living by exporting to rich countries.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p134" block_type="txt">How important are these effects? In some historical episodes, the impacts of international trade on factor prices have been very large. As we explain in the following Economics in Action, the opening of transatlantic trade in the late nineteenth century had a large negative impact on land rents in Europe, hurting landowners but helping workers and owners of capital.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p135" block_type="txt">The effects of trade on wages in the United States have generated considerable controversy in recent years. Most economists who have studied the issue agree that growing imports of labor-intensive products from newly industrializing economies, and the export of high-technology goods in return, have helped cause a widening wage gap between highly educated and less educated workers in this country. However, most economists believe that it is only one of several forces explaining the growth in American wage inequality.</p>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-bx2-2" block_type="bx-2-h">
<box-metadata><box-title><phrase block_type="title">ECONOMICS</phrase> <phrase block_type="number"><em>in Action</em></phrase><image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-img-20" alt="image" src="images/world_view_icon.jpg"/></box-title></box-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p137" block_type="bx-2-t"><strong>Trade, Wages, and Land Prices in the Nineteenth Century</strong></p>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-exp2-2" block_type="mn2">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p136" block_type="fg1-t"><image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-img-21" alt="image" src="images/launchpad_logo_cmyk.jpg"/> &#124; interactive activity</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p138" block_type="bx2-first"><phrase block_type="dropcap">B</phrase>eginning around 1870, there was an explosive growth of world trade in agricultural products, based largely on the steam engine. Steam-powered ships could cross the ocean much more quickly and reliably than sailing ships. Until about 1860, steamships had higher costs than sailing ships, but after that costs dropped sharply. At the same time, steam-powered rail transport made it possible to bring grain and other bulk goods cheaply from the interior to ports. The result was that land-abundant countries&#8212;the United States, Canada, Argentina, and Australia&#8212;began shipping large quantities of agricultural goods to the densely populated, land-scarce countries of Europe.</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-fig-16" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="right" width="medium" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-img-22" alt="image" src="images/KrugESS4e_20UN05.jpg"/>
<caption>International trade redistributes income toward a country&#8217;s abundant factors and away from its less abundant factors.</caption>
<asset_source>Archive Images/Alamy</asset_source>
</figure>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p139" block_type="bx2-txt">This opening up of international trade led to higher prices of agricultural products, such as wheat, in exporting countries and a decline in their prices in importing countries. Notably, the difference between wheat prices in the midwestern United States and England plunged.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p140" block_type="bx2-txt">The change in agricultural prices created winners and losers on both sides of the Atlantic as factor prices adjusted. In England, land prices fell by half compared with average wages; landowners found their purchasing power sharply reduced, but workers benefited from cheaper food. In the United States, the reverse happened: land prices doubled compared with wages. Landowners did very well, but workers found the purchasing power of their wages dented by rising food prices.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_585" block_type="page_start">585</p>
<box title="Quick Review" numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-bx5-2" block_type="sr-1-h">
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-list-7" type="unordered" block_type="redbullet">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p141" block_type="sr1-bl">The intersection of the <strong>domestic demand curve</strong> and the <strong>domestic supply curve</strong> determines the domestic price of a good. When a market is opened to international trade, the domestic price is driven to equal the <strong>world price.</strong></p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p142" block_type="sr1-bl">If the world price is lower than the autarky price, trade leads to imports and the domestic price falls to the world price. There are overall gains from international trade because the gain in consumer surplus exceeds the loss in producer surplus.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p143" block_type="sr1-bl">If the world price is higher than the autarky price, trade leads to exports and the domestic price rises to the world price. There are overall gains from international trade because the gain in producer surplus exceeds the loss in consumer surplus.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p144" block_type="sr1-bl">Trade leads to an expansion of <strong>exporting industries,</strong> which increases demand for a country&#8217;s abundant factors, and a contraction of <strong>import-competing industries,</strong> which decreases demand for its scarce factors.</p></li>
</list>
</box>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-bx6-2" block_type="sr2-h">
<box-metadata><box-title><phrase block_type="title">Check Your Understanding</phrase> <phrase block_type="number">20-2</phrase></box-title></box-metadata>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-cyuquestion-3" block_type="q_cyu" number="1">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p145" block_type="sr2-nl-first"><phrase block_type="qnum">1.</phrase> Due to a strike by truckers, trade in food between the United States and Mexico is halted. In autarky, the price of Mexican grapes is lower than that of U.S. grapes. Using a diagram of the U.S. domestic demand curve and the U.S. domestic supply curve for grapes, explain the effect of the strike on the following.</p>
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-list-8" type="ordered" block_type="loweralpha">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p146" block_type="sr2-nl-lvl2">U.S. grape consumers&#8217; surplus</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p147" block_type="sr2-nl-lvl2">U.S. grape producers&#8217; surplus</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p148" block_type="sr2-nl-lvl2">U.S. total surplus</p></li>
</list>
</question>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-cyuquestion-4" block_type="q_cyu" number="2">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p149" block_type="sr2-nl-last"><phrase block_type="qnum">2.</phrase> What effect do you think the strike will have on Mexican grape producers? Mexican grape pickers? Mexican grape consumers? U.S. grape pickers?</p>
</question>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p150" block_type="sr2-nl-fn">Solutions appear at back of book.</p>
</box>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-sec1-3" block_type="h1" title="" chapter="20" numbered="true" level="1" print_page="585">
<section-metadata><section-title>The Effects of Trade Protection</section-title></section-metadata>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-exp3-13" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p151" block_type="mn-gl-def">An economy has <strong>free trade</strong> when the government does not attempt either to reduce or to increase the levels of exports and imports that occur naturally as a result of supply and demand.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p152" block_type="txt-ni">Ever since David Ricardo laid out the principle of comparative advantage in the early nineteenth century, most economists have advocated <strong>free trade.</strong> That is, they have argued that government policy should not attempt either to reduce or to increase the levels of exports and imports that occur naturally as a result of supply and demand.</p>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-exp3-14" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p153" block_type="mn-gl-def">Policies that limit imports are known as <strong>trade protection</strong> or simply as <strong>protection.</strong></p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p154" block_type="txt">Despite the free-trade arguments of economists, however, many governments use taxes and other restrictions to limit imports. Less frequently, governments offer subsidies to encourage exports. Policies that limit imports, usually with the goal of protecting domestic producers in import-competing industries from foreign competition, are known as <strong>trade protection</strong> or simply as <strong>protection.</strong></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p155" block_type="txt">Let&#8217;s look at the two most common protectionist policies, <em>tariffs</em> and <em>import quotas,</em> then turn to the reasons governments follow these policies.</p>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-sec2-8" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="20" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="585">
<section-metadata><section-title>The Effects of a Tariff</section-title></section-metadata>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-exp3-15" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p156" block_type="mn-gl-def">A <strong>tariff</strong> is a tax levied on imports.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p157" block_type="txt-ni">A <strong>tariff</strong> is a form of excise tax, one that is levied only on sales of imported goods. For example, the U.S. government could declare that anyone bringing in phones must pay a tariff of &#36;100 per unit. In the distant past, tariffs were an important source of government revenue because they were relatively easy to collect. But in the modern world, tariffs are usually intended to discourage imports and protect import-competing domestic producers rather than as a source of government revenue.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p158" block_type="txt">The tariff raises both the price received by domestic producers and the price paid by domestic consumers. Suppose, for example, that our country imports phones, and a phone costs &#36;200 on the world market. As we saw earlier, under free trade the domestic price would also be &#36;200. But if a tariff of &#36;100 per unit is imposed, the domestic price will rise to &#36;300, because it won&#8217;t be profitable to import phones unless the price in the domestic market is high enough to compensate importers for the cost of paying the tariff.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p159" block_type="txt"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-fig-17">Figure 20-10</link> illustrates the effects of a tariff on imports of phones. As before, we assume that <em>P<sub>W</sub></em> is the world price of a phone. Before the tariff is imposed, imports have driven the domestic price down to <em>P<sub>W</sub>,</em> so that pre-tariff domestic production is <em>Q<sub>S</sub>,</em> pre-tariff domestic consumption is <em>Q<sub>D</sub></em>, and pre-tariff imports are <em>Q<sub>D</sub></em> &#8722; <em>Q<sub>S</sub>.</em></p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-fig-17" block_type="figure" numbered="true" number="20-10" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<caption><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-fig-17"><phrase block_type="fig-label"><phrase block_type="fig"><strong>FIGURE</strong></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_num"><strong>20-10</strong></phrase></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_title">The Effect of a Tariff</phrase></link></caption>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-img-23" alt="image" src="images/KrugESS4e_fig_20_10.jpg"/>
<caption>A tariff raises the domestic price of the good from <em>P<sub>W</sub></em> to <em>P<sub>T</sub></em>. The domestic quantity demanded shrinks from <em>Q<sub>D</sub></em> to <em>Q<sub>DT</sub></em>, and the domestic quantity supplied increases from <em>Q<sub>S</sub></em> to <em>Q<sub>ST</sub></em>. As a result, imports&#8212;which had been <em>Q<sub>D</sub></em> &#8722; <em>Q<sub>S</sub></em> before the tariff was imposed&#8212;shrink to <em>Q<sub>DT</sub></em> &#8722; <em>Q<sub>ST</sub></em> after the tariff is imposed.</caption>
</figure>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p160" block_type="txt">Now suppose that the government imposes a tariff on each phone imported. As a consequence, it is no longer profitable to import phones unless the domestic price received by the importer is greater than or equal to the world price plus the tariff. So the domestic price rises to <em>P<sub>T</sub>,</em> which is equal to the world price, <em>P<sub>W</sub>,</em> plus the tariff. Domestic production rises to <em>Q<sub>ST</sub>,</em> domestic consumption falls to <em>Q<sub>DT</sub>,</em> and imports fall to <em>Q<sub>DT</sub></em> &#8722; <em>Q<sub>ST</sub>.</em></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_586" block_type="page_start">586</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p161" block_type="txt">A tariff, then, raises domestic prices, leading to increased domestic production and reduced domestic consumption compared to the situation under free trade. <link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-fig-18">Figure 20-11</link> shows the effects on surplus. There are three effects:</p>
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-list-9" type="ordered" block_type="numbered">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p162" block_type="nl-first">The higher domestic price increases producer surplus, a gain equal to area <em>A.</em></p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p163" block_type="nl-mid">The higher domestic price reduces consumer surplus, a reduction equal to the sum of areas <em>A, B, C,</em> and <em>D.</em></p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p164" block_type="nl-last">The tariff yields revenue to the government. How much revenue? The government collects the tariff&#8212;which, remember, is equal to the difference between <em>P<sub>T</sub></em> and <em>P<sub>W</sub></em> on each of the <em>Q<sub>DT</sub></em> &#8722; <em>Q<sub>ST</sub></em> units imported. So total revenue is (<em>P<sub>T</sub></em> &#8722; <em>P<sub>W</sub></em>) &#215; (<em>Q<sub>DT</sub></em> &#8722; <em>Q<sub>ST</sub></em>). This is equal to area <em>C.</em></p></li>
</list>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-fig-18" block_type="figure" numbered="true" number="20-11" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<caption><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-fig-18"><phrase block_type="fig-label"><phrase block_type="fig"><strong>FIGURE</strong></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_num"><strong>20-11</strong></phrase></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_title">A Tariff Reduces Total Surplus</phrase></link></caption>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-img-24" alt="image" src="images/KrugESS4e_fig_20_11.jpg"/>
<caption>When the domestic price rises as a result of a tariff, producers gain additional surplus (area <em>A</em>), the government gains revenue (area <em>C</em>), and consumers lose surplus (areas <em>A</em> &#43; <em>B</em> &#43; <em>C</em> &#43; <em>D</em>). Because the losses to consumers outweigh the gains to producers and the government, the economy as a whole loses surplus (areas <em>B</em> &#43; <em>D</em>).</caption>
</figure>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p165" block_type="txt">The welfare effects of a tariff are summarized in the table in <link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-fig-18">Figure 20-11</link>. Producers gain, consumers lose, and the government gains. But consumer losses are greater than the sum of producer and government gains, leading to a net reduction in total surplus equal to areas <em>B</em> &#43; <em>D.</em></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p166" block_type="txt">An excise tax creates inefficiency, or deadweight loss, because it prevents mutually beneficial trades from occurring. The same is true of a tariff, where the deadweight loss imposed on society is equal to the loss in total surplus represented by areas <em>B</em> &#43; <em>D.</em></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p167" block_type="txt">Tariffs generate deadweight losses because they create inefficiencies in two ways:</p>
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-list-10" type="ordered" block_type="numbered">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p168" block_type="nl-first">Some mutually beneficial trades go unexploited: some consumers who are willing to pay more than the world price, <em>P<sub>W</sub>,</em> do not purchase the good, even though <em>P<sub>W</sub></em> is the true cost of a unit of the good to the economy. The cost of this inefficiency is represented in <link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-fig-18">Figure 20-11</link> by area <em>D.</em></p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p169" block_type="nl-mid">The economy&#8217;s resources are wasted on inefficient production: some producers whose cost exceeds <em>P<sub>W</sub></em> produce the good, even though an additional unit of the good can be purchased abroad for <em>P<sub>W</sub>.</em> The cost of this inefficiency is represented in <link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-fig-18">Figure 20-11</link> by area <em>B.</em></p></li>
</list>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_587" block_type="page_start">587</p>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-sec2-9" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="20" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="587">
<section-metadata><section-title>The Effects of an Import Quota</section-title></section-metadata>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-exp3-16" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p170" block_type="mn-gl-def">An <strong>import quota</strong> is a legal limit on the quantity of a good that can be imported.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p171" block_type="txt-ni">An <strong>import quota,</strong> another form of trade protection, is a legal limit on the quantity of a good that can be imported. For example, a U.S. import quota on Chinese phones might limit the quantity imported each year to 50 million units. Import quotas are usually administered through licenses: a number of licenses are issued, each giving the license-holder the right to import a limited quantity of the good each year.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p172" block_type="txt">A quota on sales has the same effect as an excise tax, with one difference: the money that would otherwise have accrued to the government as tax revenue under an excise tax becomes license-holders&#8217; revenue under a quota&#8212;also known as quota rents.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p173" block_type="txt">Similarly, an import quota has the same effect as a tariff, with one difference: the money that would otherwise have been government revenue becomes quota rents to license-holders. Look again at <link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-fig-18">Figure 20-11</link>. An import quota that limits imports to <em>Q<sub>DT</sub></em> &#8722; <em>Q<sub>ST</sub></em> will raise the domestic price of phones by the same amount as the tariff we considered previously. That is, it will raise the domestic price from <em>P<sub>W</sub></em> to <em>P<sub>T</sub>.</em> However, area <em>C</em> will now represent quota rents rather than government revenue.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p174" block_type="txt">Who receives import licenses and so collects the quota rents? In the case of U.S. import protection, the answer may surprise you: the most important import licenses&#8212;mainly for clothing, and to a lesser extent for sugar&#8212;are granted to foreign governments.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p175" block_type="txt">Because the quota rents for most U.S. import quotas go to foreigners, the cost to the nation of such quotas is larger than that of a comparable tariff (a tariff that leads to the same level of imports). In <link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-fig-18">Figure 20-11</link> the net loss to the United States from such an import quota would be equal to areas <em>B</em> &#43; <em>C</em> &#43; <em>D,</em> the difference between consumer losses and producer gains.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_588" block_type="page_start">588</p>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-bx2-3" block_type="bx-2-h">
<box-metadata><box-title><phrase block_type="title">ECONOMICS</phrase> <phrase block_type="number"><em>in Action</em></phrase><image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-img-25" alt="image" src="images/world_view_icon.jpg"/></box-title></box-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p176" block_type="bx-2-t"><strong>Trade Protection in the United States</strong></p>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-exp2-3" block_type="mn2">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p177" block_type="fg1-t"><image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-img-26" alt="image" src="images/launchpad_logo_cmyk.jpg"/> &#124; interactive activity</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p178" block_type="bx2-first"><phrase block_type="dropcap">T</phrase>he United States today generally follows a policy of free trade, both in comparison with other countries and in comparison with its own history. Most imports are subject to either no tariff or to a low tariff. So what are the major exceptions to this rule?</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p179" block_type="bx2-txt">Most of the remaining protection involves agricultural products. Topping the list is ethanol, which in the United States is mainly produced from corn and used as an ingredient in motor fuel. Most imported ethanol is subject to a fairly high tariff, but some countries are allowed to sell a limited amount of ethanol in the United States, at high prices, without paying the tariff. Dairy products also receive substantial import protection, again through a combination of tariffs and quotas. </p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p180" block_type="bx2-txt">Until a few years ago, clothing and textiles were also strongly protected from import competition, thanks to an elaborate system of import quotas. However, this system was phased out in 2005 as part of a trade agreement reached a decade earlier. Some clothing imports are still subject to relatively high tariffs, but protection in the clothing industry is a shadow of what it used to be.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p181" block_type="bx2-txt">The most important thing to know about current U.S. trade protection is how limited it really is, and how little cost it imposes on the economy. Every two years the U.S. International Trade Commission, a government agency, produces estimates of the impact of &#8220;significant trade restrictions&#8221; on U.S. welfare. As <link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-fig-19">Figure 20-12</link> shows, over the past two decades both average tariff levels and the cost of trade restrictions as a share of national income, which weren&#8217;t all that big to begin with, have fallen sharply.</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-fig-19" block_type="figure" numbered="true" number="20-12" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="right" width="medium" border="true"/>
<caption><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-fig-19"><phrase block_type="fig-label"><phrase block_type="fig"><strong>FIGURE</strong></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_num"><strong>20-12</strong></phrase></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_title">Tariff Rates and Estimated Welfare Losses, 1993&#8211;2013</phrase></link></caption>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-img-27" alt="image" src="images/KrugESS4e_fig_20_12.jpg"/>
<asset_source><em>Data from:</em> U.S. International Trade Commission (2013), Federal Reserve Bank of St. Louis; and World Development Indicators.</asset_source>
</figure>
</box>
<box title="Quick Review" numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-bx5-3" block_type="sr-1-h">
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-list-11" type="unordered" block_type="redbullet">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p182" block_type="sr1-bl">Most economists advocate <strong>free trade,</strong> although many governments engage in <strong>trade protection</strong> of import-competing industries. The two most common protectionist policies are tariffs and import quotas. In rare instances, governments subsidize exporting industries.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p183" block_type="sr1-bl">A <strong>tariff</strong> is a tax on imports. It raises the domestic price above the world price, leading to a fall in trade and domestic consumption and a rise in domestic production. Domestic producers and the government gain, but domestic consumer losses more than offset this gain, leading to deadweight loss.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p184" block_type="sr1-bl">An <strong>import quota</strong> is a legal quantity limit on imports. Its effect is like that of a tariff, except that revenues&#8212;the quota rents&#8212;accrue to the license holder, not to the domestic government.</p></li>
</list>
</box>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-bx6-3" block_type="sr2-h">
<box-metadata><box-title><phrase block_type="title">Check Your Understanding</phrase> <phrase block_type="number">20-3</phrase></box-title></box-metadata>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-cyuquestion-5" block_type="q_cyu" number="1">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p185" block_type="sr2-nl-first"><phrase block_type="qnum">1.</phrase> Suppose the world price of butter is &#36;0.50 per pound and the domestic price in autarky is &#36;1.00 per pound. Use a diagram similar to <link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-fig-17">Figure 20-10</link> to show the following.</p>
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-list-12" type="ordered" block_type="loweralpha">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p186" block_type="sr2-nl-lvl2">If there is free trade, domestic butter producers want the government to impose a tariff of no less than &#36;0.50 per pound. Compare the outcome with a tariff of &#36;0.25 per pound.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p187" block_type="sr2-nl-lvl2">What happens if a tariff greater than &#36;0.50 per pound is imposed?</p></li>
</list>
</question>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-cyuquestion-6" block_type="q_cyu" number="2">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p188" block_type="sr2-nl-last"><phrase block_type="qnum">2.</phrase> Suppose the government imposes an import quota rather than a tariff on butter. What quota limit would generate the same quantity of imports as a tariff of &#36;0.50 per pound?</p>
</question>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p189" block_type="sr2-nl-fn">Solutions appear at back of book.</p>
</box>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-sec1-4" block_type="h1" title="" chapter="20" numbered="true" level="1" print_page="588">
<section-metadata><section-title>Capital Flows and the Balance of Payments</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p190" block_type="txt-ni">In 2013 people living in the United States sold about &#36;4.2 trillion worth of stuff to people living in other countries and bought about &#36;4.2 trillion worth of stuff in return. What kind of stuff? All kinds. Residents of the United States (including firms operating in the United States) sold airplanes, bonds, wheat, and many other items to residents of other countries. Residents of the United States bought cars, stocks, oil, and many other items from residents of other countries.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_589" block_type="page_start">589</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p191" block_type="txt">How can we keep track of these transactions? In <link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch13.xml">Chapter 13</link> we learned that economists keep track of the domestic economy using the national income and product accounts. Economists keep track of international transactions using a different but related set of numbers, the <em>balance of payments accounts.</em></p>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-sec2-10" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="20" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="589">
<section-metadata><section-title>Balance of Payments Accounts</section-title></section-metadata>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-exp3-17" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p208" block_type="mn-gl-def">A country&#8217;s <strong>balance of payments accounts</strong> are a summary of the country&#8217;s transactions with other countries.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p192" block_type="txt-ni"><strong>Balance of payments accounts</strong> are a summary of a country&#8217;s transactions with other countries for a given year.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p193" block_type="txt">To understand the basic idea behind the balance of payments accounts, let&#8217;s consider a small-scale example: not a country, but a family farm. Let&#8217;s say that we know the following about how last year went financially for the Costas, who own a small artichoke farm in California:</p>
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-list-13" type="unordered" block_type="bullet">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p194" block_type="bl-first">They made &#36;100,000 by selling artichokes.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p195" block_type="bl-mid">They spent &#36;70,000 on running the farm, including purchases of new farm machinery, and another &#36;40,000 buying food, paying utility bills, replacing their worn-out car, and so on.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p196" block_type="bl-mid">They received &#36;500 in interest on their bank account but paid &#36;10,000 in interest on their mortgage.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p197" block_type="bl-last">They took out a new &#36;25,000 loan to help pay for farm improvements but didn&#8217;t use all the money immediately. So they put the extra in the bank.</p></li>
</list>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p198" block_type="txt">How could we summarize the Costas&#8217; transactions for the year? One way would be with a table like <link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-tab-3">Table 20-3</link>, which shows sources of cash coming in and uses of cash going out, characterized under a few broad headings. The first row of the table shows sales and purchases of goods and services: sales of artichokes; purchases of groceries, heating oil, that new car, and so on. The second row shows interest payments: the interest the Costas received from their bank account and the interest they paid on their mortgage. The third row shows loans and deposits: cash coming in from a loan and cash deposited in the bank.</p>
<table id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-tab-3" block_type="table" numbered="false" caption-placement="Top" data-href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-tab-3" data-target="_pop">
<table_caption><strong><phrase block_type="tbl">TABLE</phrase> <phrase block_type="tbl_num">20-3</phrase></strong> <phrase block_type="tbl_title">The Costas&#8217; Financial Year</phrase></table_caption>
<tbody>
<tr class="tbl-hdr-bg">
<td class="tbl-rborder"></td>
<td class="tbl-rborder"><strong>Sources of cash</strong></td>
<td class="tbl-rborder"><strong>Uses of cash</strong></td>
<td><strong>Net</strong></td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tbl-rborder tbl-bborder tbl-ljust"><strong>Purchases or sales of goods and services</strong></td>
<td class="tbl-rborder tbl-bborder tbl-ljust">Artichoke sales: &#36;100,000</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder tbl-bborder tbl-ljust">Farm operation and living expenses: &#36;110,000</td>
<td class="tbl-bborder">&#8722;&#36;10,000</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tbl-rborder tbl-bborder tbl-ljust"><strong>Interest payments</strong></td>
<td class="tbl-rborder tbl-bborder tbl-ljust">Interest received on bank account: &#36;500</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder tbl-bborder tbl-ljust">Interest paid on mortgage: &#36;10,000</td>
<td class="tbl-bborder">&#8722;&#36;9,500</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tbl-rborder tbl-bborder tbl-ljust"><strong>Loans and deposits</strong></td>
<td class="tbl-rborder tbl-bborder tbl-ljust">Funds received from new loan: &#36;25,000</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder tbl-bborder tbl-ljust">Funds deposited in bank: &#36;5,500</td>
<td class="tbl-bborder">&#43;&#36;19,500</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-hdr-bg">
<td class="tbl-rborder tbl-ljust"><strong>Total</strong></td>
<td class="tbl-rborder tbl-ljust"><strong>&#36;125,500</strong></td>
<td class="tbl-rborder tbl-ljust"><strong>&#36;125,500</strong></td>
<td><strong>&#36;0</strong></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p199" block_type="txt">In each row we show the net inflow of cash from that type of transaction. So the net in the first row is &#8722;&#36;10,000, because the Costas spent &#36;10,000 more than they earned. The net in the second row is &#8722;&#36;9,500, the difference between the interest the Costas received on their bank account and the interest they paid on the mortgage. The net in the third row is &#36;19,500: the Costas brought in &#36;25,000 with their new loan but put only &#36;5,500 of that sum in the bank.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p200" block_type="txt">The last row shows the sum of cash coming in from all sources and the sum of all cash used. These sums are equal, by definition: every dollar has a source, and every dollar received gets used somewhere. (What if the Costas hid money under the mattress? Then that would be counted as another &#8220;use&#8221; of cash.)</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p201" block_type="txt">A country&#8217;s balance of payments accounts is a table which summarizes the country&#8217;s transactions with the rest of the world for a given year in a manner very similar to the way we just summarized the Costas&#8217; financial year.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p202" block_type="txt"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-tab-4">Table 20-4</link> shows a simplified version of the U.S. balance of payments accounts for 2013. Where the Costa family&#8217;s accounts show sources and uses of cash, a country&#8217;s balance of payments accounts show payments from foreigners&#8212;sources of cash for the United States as a whole&#8212;and payments to foreigners&#8212;uses of cash for the United States as a whole.</p>
<table id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-tab-4" block_type="table" numbered="false" caption-placement="Top" data-href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-tab-4" data-target="_pop">
<table_caption><strong><phrase block_type="tbl">TABLE</phrase> <phrase block_type="tbl_num">20-4</phrase></strong> <phrase block_type="tbl_title">The U.S. Balance of Payments in 2013 (billions of dollars)</phrase></table_caption>
<tbody>
<tr class="tbl-hdr-bg">
<td colspan="2" class="tbl-rborder tbl-bborder"></td>
<td class="tbl-rborder tbl-bborder"><strong>Payments from<br/> foreigners</strong></td>
<td class="tbl-rborder tbl-bborder"><strong>Payments to<br/> foreigners</strong></td>
<td class="tbl-bborder"><strong>Net</strong></td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tbl-rborder tbl-bborder"><strong>1</strong></td>
<td class="tbl-rborder tbl-bborder tbl-ljust"><strong>Sales and purchases of goods and services</strong></td>
<td class="tbl-rborder tbl-bborder">&#36;2,280</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder tbl-bborder">&#36;2,756</td>
<td class="tbl-bborder">&#8722;&#36;476</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tbl-rborder tbl-bborder"><strong>2</strong></td>
<td class="tbl-rborder tbl-just tbl-bborder"><strong>Factor income</strong></td>
<td class="tbl-rborder tbl-bborder">780</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder tbl-bborder">580</td>
<td class="tbl-bborder">199</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tbl-rborder tbl-bborder"><strong>3</strong></td>
<td class="tbl-rborder tbl-bborder tbl-ljust"><strong>Transfers</strong></td>
<td class="tbl-rborder tbl-bborder">118</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder tbl-bborder">242</td>
<td class="tbl-bborder">&#8722;124</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-hdr-bg">
<td class="tbl-rborder tbl-bborder"></td>
<td class="tbl-rborder tbl-bborder tbl-ljust"><strong>Current account<br/> (1 &#43; 2 &#43; 3)</strong></td>
<td class="tbl-rborder tbl-bborder"></td>
<td class="tbl-rborder tbl-bborder"></td>
<td class="tbl-bborder"><strong>&#8722;400</strong></td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tbl-rborder tbl-bborder"><strong>4</strong></td>
<td class="tbl-rborder tbl-bborder tbl-ljust"><strong>Asset sales and purchases<br/> (financial account)</strong></td>
<td class="tbl-rborder tbl-bborder">1,018</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder tbl-bborder">&#8722;645</td>
<td class="tbl-bborder">373</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-hdr-bg">
<td class="tbl-rborder tbl-bborder"></td>
<td class="tbl-rborder tbl-bborder tbl-ljust"><strong>Financial account (4)</strong></td>
<td class="tbl-rborder tbl-bborder"></td>
<td class="tbl-rborder tbl-bborder"></td>
<td class="tbl-bborder"><strong>373</strong></td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tbl-rborder"></td>
<td class="tbl-rborder tbl-ljust"><strong>Statistical discrepancy</strong></td>
<td class="tbl-rborder">&#8212;</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder">&#8212;</td>
<td><strong>&#8722;27</strong></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p203a" block_type="tbn-sc"><em>Data from:</em> Bureau of Labor Statistics.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_590" block_type="page_start">590</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p203" block_type="txt">Row 1 of <link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-tab-4">Table 20-4</link> shows payments that arise from U.S. sales to foreigners and U.S. purchases from foreigners of goods and services in 2013. For example, the number in the second column of row 1, &#36;2,280 billion, incorporates items such as the value of U.S. wheat exports and the fees foreigners pay to U.S. consulting companies in 2013. The number in the third column of row 1, &#36;2,756 billion, incorporates items such as the value of U.S. oil imports and the fees U.S. companies pay to Indian call centers&#8212;the people who often answer your 1-800 calls&#8212;in 2013.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p204" block_type="txt">Row 2 shows U.S. <em>factor income</em> in 2013&#8212;the income that foreigners paid to American residents for the use of American-owned factors of production, as well as income paid by Americans to foreigners for the use of foreign-owned factors of production. Factor income mostly consists of investment income, such as interest paid by Americans on loans from overseas, profits of American-owned corporations that operate overseas, and the like. For example, the profits earned by Disneyland Paris, which is owned by the U.S.-based Walt Disney Company, are included in the &#36;780 billion figure in the second column of row 2. The profits earned by the U.S. operations of Japanese auto companies are included in the &#36;580 billion figure shown in the third column of row 2. Factor income also includes some labor income. For example, the wages of an American engineer who works temporarily on a construction site in Dubai are counted in the &#36;780 billion figure in the second column.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p205" block_type="txt">Row 3 shows <em>international transfers</em> for the U.S. in 2013&#8212;funds sent by American residents to residents of other countries and vice versa. The figure in the second column of row 3, &#36;118 billion, includes payments sent home by skilled American workers who work abroad. The third column accounts for the major portion of international transfers. The figure there, &#36;242 billion, is composed mainly of remittances that immigrants who reside in the United States, such as the millions of Mexican-born workers employed in the United States, send to their families in their country of origin. In addition there is also a lot of money sent home by U.S. skilled workers abroad.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p206" block_type="txt">Row 4 of the table contains payments accruing from sales and purchases of assets between American residents and foreigners in 2013. For example, in 2013 Shanghui, a Chinese food company, purchased Smithfield Foods, America&#8217;s top pork packager, for &#36;4.7 billion. As a payment to the American owners of Smithfield Foods for the purchase of their assets, that &#36;4.7 billion is included in the figure &#36;1,018 billion, found in the second column of row 4. Also in 2013, some major Wall Street firms were buying European debt, both private and public. As a payment by American residents to foreigners for the purchase of foreign assets, these purchases are included in the &#8722;&#36;645 billion figure located in the third column of row 4.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p207" block_type="txt">In laying out <link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-tab-4">Table 20-4</link>, we have separated rows 1, 2, and 3 into one group, to distinguish them from row 4. This reflects a fundamental difference in how these two groups of transactions affect the future. When a U.S. resident sells a good such as wheat to a foreigner, that&#8217;s the end of the transaction. But a financial asset, such as a bond, is different. Remember, a bond is a promise to pay interest and principal in the future. So when a U.S. resident sells a bond to a foreigner, that sale creates a liability: the U.S. resident will have to pay interest and repay principal in the future. The balance of payments accounts distinguish between transactions that don&#8217;t create liabilities and those that do.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_591" block_type="page_start">591</p>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-exp3-18" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p209" block_type="mn-gl-def">A country&#8217;s <strong>balance of payments on current account,</strong> or <strong>current account,</strong> is its balance of payments on goods and services plus net international transfer payments and factor income.</p>
</box>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-exp3-19" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p210" block_type="mn-gl-def">A country&#8217;s <strong>balance of payments on goods and services</strong> is the difference between its exports and its imports during a given period. </p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p211" block_type="txt">Transactions that don&#8217;t create liabilities are considered part of the <strong>balance of payments on current account,</strong> often referred to simply as the <strong>current account:</strong> the balance of payments on goods and services plus net international transfer payments and factor income. This corresponds to rows 1, 2, and 3 in <link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-tab-4">Table 20-4</link>. In practice, row 1 of <link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-tab-4">Table 20-4</link>, amounting to &#8722;&#36;476 billion in 2013, corresponds to the most important part of the current account: the <strong>balance of payments on goods and services,</strong> the difference between the value of exports and the value of imports during a given period.</p>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-exp3-20" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p212" block_type="mn-gl-def">The <strong>merchandise trade balance,</strong> or <strong>trade balance,</strong> is the difference between a country&#8217;s exports and imports of goods.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p213" block_type="txt">If you read news reports on the economy, you may well see references to another measure, the <strong>merchandise trade balance,</strong> sometimes referred to as the <strong>trade balance</strong> for short. It is the difference between a country&#8217;s exports and imports of goods alone&#8212;not including services. Economists sometimes focus on the merchandise trade balance, even though it&#8217;s an incomplete measure, because data on international trade in services aren&#8217;t as accurate as data on trade in physical goods, and they are also slower to arrive.</p>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-exp3-21" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p214" block_type="mn-gl-def">A country&#8217;s <strong>balance of payments on financial account,</strong> or simply its <strong>financial account,</strong> is the difference between its sales of assets to foreigners and its purchases of assets from foreigners for a given period.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p215" block_type="txt">Transactions that involve the sale or purchase of assets, and therefore do create future liabilities, are considered part of the <strong>balance of payments on financial account,</strong> or the <strong>financial account</strong> for short, for a given period. This corresponds to row 4 in <link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-tab-4">Table 20-4</link>, which was &#36;373 billion in 2013. (Until a few years ago, economists often referred to the financial account as the <em>capital account.</em> We&#8217;ll use the modern term, but you may run across the older term.)</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p216" block_type="txt">So how does it all add up? The shaded rows of <link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-tab-4">Table 20-4</link> show the bottom lines: the overall U.S. current account and financial account for 2013. As you can see, in 2013 the United States ran a current account deficit: the amount it paid to foreigners for goods, services, factors, and transfers was more than the amount it received. Simultaneously, it ran a financial account surplus: the value of the assets it sold to foreigners was more than the value of the assets it bought from foreigners.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p217" block_type="txt">In the 2013 official data, the U.S. current account deficit and financial account surplus didn&#8217;t exactly offset each other: the financial account surplus in 2013 was &#36;27 billion smaller than the current account deficit. But that&#8217;s just a statistical error, reflecting the imperfection of official data. (The discrepancy may have reflected foreign purchases of U.S. assets that official data somehow missed.) In fact, it&#8217;s a basic rule of balance of payments accounting that the current account and the financial account must sum to zero:</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p218" block_type="eq"><strong>(20-1)</strong> Current account (<em>CA</em>) &#43; Financial account (<em>FA</em>) = 0</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p219" block_type="txt-ni">or</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p220" block_type="eq"><em>CA</em> = &#8722;<em>FA</em></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p221" block_type="txt-ni">Why must Equation 20-1 be true? We already saw the fundamental explanation in <link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-tab-3">Table 20-3</link>, which showed the accounts of the Costa family: in total, the sources of cash must equal the uses of cash. The same applies to balance of payments accounts. <link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-fig-20">Figure 20-13</link>, a variant on the circular-flow diagram we have found useful in discussing domestic macroeconomics, may help you visualize how this adding up works. Instead of showing the flow of money <em>within</em> a national economy, <link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-fig-20">Figure 20-13</link> shows the flow of money <em>between</em> national economies.</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-fig-20" block_type="figure" numbered="true" number="20-13" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<caption><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-fig-20"><phrase block_type="fig-label"><phrase block_type="fig"><strong>FIGURE</strong></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_num"><strong>20-13</strong></phrase></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_title">The Balance of Payments</phrase></link></caption>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-img-28" alt="image" src="images/KrugESS4e_fig_20_13.jpg"/>
<caption>The yellow arrows represent payments that are counted in the current account. The green arrows represent payments that are counted in the financial account. Because the total flow into the United States must equal the total flow out of the United States, the sum of the current account plus the financial account is zero.</caption>
</figure>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p222" block_type="txt">Money flows into the United States from the rest of the world as payment for U.S. exports of goods and services, as payment for the use of U.S.-owned factors of production, and as transfer payments. These flows (indicated by the lower green arrow) are the positive components of the U.S. current account. Money also flows into the United States from foreigners who purchase U.S. assets (as shown by the lower green arrow)&#8212;the positive component of the U.S. financial account.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p223" block_type="txt">At the same time, money flows from the United States to the rest of the world as payment for U.S. imports of goods and services, as payment for the use of foreign-owned factors of production, and as transfer payments. These flows, indicated by the upper yellow arrow, are the negative components of the U.S. current account. Money also flows from the United States to purchase foreign assets, as shown by the upper green arrow&#8212;the negative component of the U.S. financial account. As in all circular-flow diagrams, the flow into a box and the flow out of a box are equal. This means that the sum of the yellow and green arrows going into the United States (the top two arrows) is equal to the sum of the yellow and green arrows going out of the United States (the bottom two arrows). That is,</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_592" block_type="page_start">592</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p224" block_type="eq"><strong>(20-2)</strong> Positive entries on current account (lower yellow arrow) &#43; Positive entries on financial account (lower green arrow) = Negative entries on current account (upper yellow arrow) &#43; Negative entries on financial account (upper green arrow)</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p225" block_type="txt-ni">Equation 20-2 can be rearranged as follows:</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p226" block_type="eq"><strong>(20-3)</strong> Positive entries on current account &#8722; Negative entries on current account &#43; Positive entries on financial account &#8722; Negative entries on financial account = 0</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p227" block_type="txt-ni">Equation 20-3 is equivalent to Equation 20-1: the current account plus the financial account&#8212;both equal to positive entries minus negative entries&#8212;is equal to zero.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p228" block_type="txt">But what determines the current account and the financial account?</p>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-sec2-11" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="20" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="592">
<section-metadata><section-title>Underlying Determinants of International Capital Flows</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p229" block_type="txt-ni">International differences in the demand for funds reflect underlying differences in investment opportunities. In particular, a country with a rapidly growing economy, other things equal, tends to offer more investment opportunities than a country with a slowly growing economy. So a rapidly growing economy typically&#8212;though not always&#8212;has a higher demand for capital and offers higher returns to investors than a slowly growing economy. As a result, capital tends to flow from slowly growing to rapidly growing economies.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p230" block_type="txt">The classic example, described in the upcoming Economics in Action, is the flow of capital from Britain to the United States, among other countries, between 1870 and 1914. During that era, the U.S. economy was growing rapidly as the population increased and spread westward and as the nation industrialized, creating a demand for investment spending on railroads, factories, and so on. Meanwhile, Britain had a much more slowly growing population, was already industrialized, and already had a railroad network covering the country. This left Britain with savings to spare, much of which were lent out to the United States and other New World economies.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_593" block_type="page_start">593</p>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-bx4-2" block_type="bx4-h">
<box-metadata><box-title><image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-img-29" alt="image" src="images/World_icon_no_type.jpg"/> <phrase block_type="gc1">GLOBAL</phrase> <phrase block_type="gc2">COMPARISON</phrase></box-title></box-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p231" block_type="bx4-t"><strong>Big Surpluses</strong></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p232" block_type="bx4-txt-ni"><phrase block_type="dropcap">T</phrase>he United States generally runs a large deficit in its current account. In fact, America leads the world in its current account deficit; other countries run bigger deficits as a share of GDP, but they have much smaller economies, so the U.S. deficit is much bigger in absolute terms.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p233" block_type="bx4-txt">For the world as a whole, however, deficits on the part of some countries must be matched with surpluses on the part of other countries. So who are the surplus nations offsetting U.S. deficits, and what if anything do they have in common?</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p234" block_type="bx4-txt">The figure shows the average current account surplus of the six countries that ran the largest surpluses over the period from 2000 to 2013. China tops the list with a surplus that was largely due to its policy of keeping its currency weak relative to other currencies.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p235" block_type="bx4-txt">Japan and Germany run current account surpluses for more or less the same reasons: both are rich nations with high savings rates, giving them a lot of money to invest. Since some of that money goes abroad, the result is that they run deficits on the financial account and surpluses on current account.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p236" block_type="bx4-txt">The other three countries are all major oil exporters. (You may not think of Russia or Norway as &#8220;petro-economies,&#8221; but Russia derives about two-thirds of its export revenue from oil, and Norway owns huge oil fields in the North Sea.) These countries are all deliberately building up assets abroad to help them sustain their spending when the oil runs out.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p237" block_type="bx4-txt">All in all, the surplus countries are a diverse group. If your picture of the world is simply one of American deficits versus Chinese surpluses, you&#8217;re missing a large part of the story.</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-fig-21" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="right" width="medium" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-img-30" alt="image" src="images/KrugESS4e_20UN06.jpg"/>
<asset_source><em>Data from:</em> IMF World Economic Outlook, 2014.</asset_source>
</figure>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p239" block_type="txt">International differences in the supply of funds reflect differences in savings across countries. These may be the result of differences in private savings rates, which vary widely among countries. For example, in 2014 gross private savings were 27&#37; of Germany&#8217;s GDP but only 17&#37; of U.S. GDP. They may also reflect differences in savings by governments. In particular, government budget deficits, which reduce overall national savings, can lead to capital inflows.</p>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-sec2-12" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="20" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="593">
<section-metadata><section-title>Two-Way Capital Flows</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p240" block_type="txt-ni">International investment opportunities and differences in savings rates are important determinants of the direction of <em>net</em> capital flows&#8212;the excess of inflows into a country over outflows, or vice versa. The direction of net flows, other things equal, is determined by differences in interest rates between countries. As we saw in <link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-tab-4">Table 20-4</link>, however, <em>gross</em> flows take place in both directions: for example, the United States both sells assets to foreigners and buys assets from foreigners. Why does capital move in both directions?</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p241" block_type="txt">The answer to this question is that in the real world, as opposed to the simple model we&#8217;ve just learned, there are other motives for international capital flows besides seeking a higher rate of interest.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p242" block_type="txt">Individual investors often seek to diversify against risk by buying stocks in a number of countries. Stocks in Europe may do well when stocks in the United States do badly, or vice versa, so investors in Europe try to reduce their risk by buying some U.S. stocks, as investors in the United States try to reduce their risk by buying some European stocks. The result is capital flows in both directions.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_594" block_type="page_start">594</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-fig-22" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="right" width="medium" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-img-31" alt="image" src="images/KrugESS4e_20UN07.jpg"/>
<asset_source>ImagineChina via AP Images</asset_source>
<caption>Many American companies have opened plants in China to access the growing Chinese market and take advantage of low labor costs.</caption>
</figure>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p243" block_type="txt">Meanwhile, corporations often engage in international investment as part of their business strategy&#8212;for example, auto companies may find that they can compete better in a national market if they assemble some of their cars locally. Such business investments can also lead to two-way capital flows, as, say, European car makers build plants in the United States even as U.S. computer companies open facilities in Europe. </p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p244" block_type="txt">Finally, some countries, including the United States, are international banking centers: people from all over the world put money in U.S. financial institutions, which then invest many of those funds overseas.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p245" block_type="txt">The result of these two-way flows is that modern economies are typically both debtors (countries that owe money to the rest of the world) and creditors (countries to which the rest of the world owes money). Due to years of both capital inflows and outflows, at the end of 2015, the United States had accumulated foreign assets worth &#36;23.2 trillion, and foreigners had accumulated assets in the United States worth &#36;30.6 trillion.</p>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-bx2-4" block_type="bx-2-h">
<box-metadata><box-title><phrase block_type="title">ECONOMICS</phrase> <phrase block_type="number"><em>in Action</em></phrase><image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-img-32" alt="image" src="images/world_view_icon.jpg"/></box-title></box-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p247" block_type="bx-2-t"><strong>The Golden Age of Capital Flows</strong></p>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-exp2-4" block_type="mn2">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p246" block_type="fg1-t"><image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-img-33" alt="image" src="images/launchpad_logo_cmyk.jpg"/> &#124; interactive activity</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p248" block_type="bx2-first"><phrase block_type="dropcap">T</phrase>echnology, it&#8217;s often said, shrinks the world. Jet planes have put most of the world&#8217;s cities within a few hours of one another; modern telecommunications transmit information instantly around the globe. So you might think that international capital flows must now be larger than ever.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p249" block_type="bx2-txt">But if capital flows are measured as a share of world savings and investment, that belief turns out not to be true. The golden age of capital flows actually preceded World War I&#8212;from 1870 to 1914.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p250" block_type="bx2-txt">These capital flows went mainly from European countries, especially Britain, to what were then known as <em>zones of recent settlement,</em> countries that were attracting large numbers of European immigrants. Among the big recipients of capital inflows were Australia, Argentina, Canada, and the United States.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p251" block_type="bx2-txt">The large capital flows reflected differences in investment opportunities. Britain, a mature industrial economy with limited natural resources and a slowly growing population, offered relatively limited opportunities for new investment. The zones of recent settlement, with rapidly growing populations and abundant natural resources, offered investors a higher return and attracted capital inflows. Estimates suggest that over this period Britain sent about 40&#37; of its savings abroad, largely to finance railroads and other large projects. No country has matched that record in modern times.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p252" block_type="bx2-txt">Why can&#8217;t we match the capital flows of our great-great-grandfathers? Economists aren&#8217;t completely sure, but they have pointed to two causes: migration restrictions and political risks.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p253" block_type="bx2-txt">During the golden age of capital flows, capital movements were complementary to population movements: the big recipients of capital from Europe were also places to which large numbers of Europeans were moving. These large-scale population movements were possible before World War I because there were few legal restrictions on immigration. Today, by contrast, migration is limited by extensive legal barriers.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p254" block_type="bx2-txt">The other factor that has changed is political risk. Modern governments often limit foreign investment because they fear it will diminish their national autonomy. And due to political or security concerns, governments sometimes seize foreign property, a risk that deters investors from sending more than a relatively modest share of their wealth abroad. In the nineteenth century such actions were rare, partly because some major destinations of investment were still European colonies, partly because in those days governments had a habit of sending troops and gunboats to enforce the claims of their investors.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_595" block_type="page_start">595</p>
<box title="Quick Review" numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-bx5-4" block_type="sr-1-h">
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-list-14" type="unordered" block_type="redbullet">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p255" block_type="sr1-bl">The <strong>balance of payments accounts,</strong> which track a country&#8217;s international transactions, are composed of the <strong>balance of payments on current account,</strong> or the <strong>current account,</strong> plus the <strong>balance of payments on financial account,</strong> or the <strong>financial account.</strong> The most important component of the current account is the <strong>balance of payments on goods and services,</strong> which itself includes the <strong>merchandise trade balance,</strong> or the <strong>trade balance.</strong></p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p256" block_type="sr1-bl">Because the sources of payments must equal the uses of payments, the current account plus the financial account sum to zero.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p257" block_type="sr1-bl">Capital flows reflect international differences in savings behavior and in investment opportunities.</p></li>
</list>
</box>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-bx6-4" block_type="sr2-h">
<box-metadata><box-title><phrase block_type="title">Check Your Understanding</phrase> <phrase block_type="number">20-4</phrase></box-title></box-metadata>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-cyuquestion-7" block_type="q_cyu" number="1">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p258" block_type="sr2-nl-first"><phrase block_type="qnum">1.</phrase> Which of the balance of payments accounts do the following events affect?</p>
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-list-15" type="ordered" block_type="loweralpha">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p259" block_type="sr2-nl-lvl2">Boeing, a U.S.-based company, sells a newly built airplane to China.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p260" block_type="sr2-nl-lvl2">Chinese investors buy stock in Boeing from Americans.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p261" block_type="sr2-nl-lvl2">A Chinese company buys a used airplane from American Airlines and ships it to China.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p262" block_type="sr2-nl-lvl2">A Chinese investor who owns property in the United States buys a corporate jet, which he will keep in the United States so he can travel around America.</p></li>
</list>
</question>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-cyuquestion-8" block_type="q_cyu" number="2">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p263" block_type="sr2-nl-last"><phrase block_type="qnum">2.</phrase> What effect do you think the collapse of the U.S. housing bubble and the ensuing recession had on international capital flows into the United States?</p>
</question>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p264" block_type="sr2-nl-fn">Solutions appear at back of book.</p>
</box>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-sec1-5" block_type="h1" title="" chapter="20" numbered="true" level="1" print_page="595">
<section-metadata><section-title>The Role of the Exchange Rate</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p265" block_type="txt-ni">We&#8217;ve just seen how differences in the supply of loanable funds from savings and the demand for loanable funds for investment spending lead to international capital flows. We&#8217;ve also learned that a country&#8217;s balance of payments on current account plus its balance of payments on financial account add to zero: a country that receives net capital inflows must run a matching current account deficit, and a country that generates net capital outflows must run a matching current account surplus.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p266" block_type="txt">The behavior of the financial account&#8212;reflecting inflows or outflows of capital&#8212;is best described by equilibrium in the international loanable funds market. At the same time, the balance of payments on goods and services, the main component of the current account, is determined by decisions in the international markets for goods and services. So given that the financial account reflects the movement of capital and the current account reflects the movement of goods and services, what ensures that the balance of payments really does balance? That is, what ensures that the two accounts actually offset each other?</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p267" block_type="txt">Not surprisingly, a price is what makes these two accounts balance. Specifically, that price is the <em>exchange rate,</em> which is determined in the <em>foreign exchange market.</em></p>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-sec2-13" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="20" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="595">
<section-metadata><section-title>Understanding Exchange Rates</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p268" block_type="txt-ni">In general, goods, services, and assets produced in a country must be paid for in that country&#8217;s currency. American products must be paid for in dollars; European products must be paid for in euros; Japanese products must be paid for in yen. Occasionally, sellers will accept payment in foreign currency, but they will then exchange that currency for domestic money.</p>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-exp3-22" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p269" block_type="mn-gl-def">Currencies are traded in the <strong>foreign exchange market.</strong></p>
</box>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-exp3-23" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p270" block_type="mn-gl-def">The prices at which currencies trade are known as <strong>exchange rates.</strong></p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p271" block_type="txt">International transactions, then, require a market&#8212;the <strong>foreign exchange market&#8212;</strong>in which currencies can be exchanged for each other. This market determines <strong>exchange rates,</strong> the prices at which currencies trade. (The foreign exchange market is, in fact, not located in any one geographic spot. Rather, it is a global electronic market that traders around the world use to buy and sell currencies.)</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p272" block_type="txt"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-tab-5">Table 20-5</link> shows exchange rates among the world&#8217;s three most important currencies as of 2 <phrase block_type="smallcaps">P.M.</phrase>, EDT, on Nov. 21, 2014. Each entry shows the price of the &#8220;row&#8221; currency in terms of the &#8220;column&#8221; currency. For example, at that time US&#36;1 exchanged for &#8364;0.8072, so it took &#8364;0.8072 to buy US&#36;1. Similarly, it took US&#36;1.2388 to buy &#8364;1. These two numbers reflect the same rate of exchange between the euro and the U.S. dollar: 1/1.2388 = 0.8072.</p>
<table id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-tab-5" block_type="table" numbered="false" caption-placement="Top" data-href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-tab-5" data-target="_pop">
<table_caption><strong><phrase block_type="tbl">TABLE</phrase> <phrase block_type="tbl_num">20-5</phrase></strong> <phrase block_type="tbl_title">Exchange Rates, November 21, 2014, 2 <phrase block_type="smallcaps">P.M.</phrase></phrase></table_caption>
<tbody>
<tr class="tbl-hdr-bg">
<td></td>
<td class="tbl-rborder"><strong>U.S. dollars</strong></td>
<td class="tbl-rborder"><strong>Yen</strong></td>
<td><strong>Euros</strong></td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tbl-rborder">One U.S. dollar exchanged for</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder">1</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder">117.76</td>
<td>0.8072</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-dark">
<td class="tbl-rborder">One yen exchanged for</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder">0.0085</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder">1</td>
<td>0.0069</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tbl-rborder">One euro exchanged for</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder">1.2388</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder">145.88</td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_596" block_type="page_start">596</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p273" block_type="txt">There are two ways to write any given exchange rate. In this case, there were &#8364;0.8072 to US&#36;1 and US&#36;1.2388 to &#8364;1. Which is the correct way to write it? The answer is that there is no fixed rule. In most countries, people tend to express the exchange rate as the price of a dollar in domestic currency. However, this rule isn&#8217;t universal, and the U.S. dollar&#8211;euro rate is commonly quoted both ways. The important thing is to be sure you know which one you are using! See the Pitfalls on this page.</p>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-exp3-24" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p274" block_type="mn-gl-def">When a currency becomes more valuable in terms of other currencies, it <strong>appreciates.</strong></p>
</box>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-exp3-25" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p275" block_type="mn-gl-def">When a currency becomes less valuable in terms of other currencies, it <strong>depreciates.</strong></p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p276" block_type="txt">When discussing movements in exchange rates, economists use specialized terms to avoid confusion. When a currency becomes more valuable in terms of other currencies, economists say that the currency <strong>appreciates.</strong> When a currency becomes less valuable in terms of other currencies, it <strong>depreciates.</strong> Suppose, for example, that the value of &#8364;1 went from &#36;1 to &#36;1.25, which means that the value of US&#36;1 went from &#8364;1 to &#8364;0.80 (because 1/1.25 = 0.80). In this case, we would say that the euro appreciated and the U.S. dollar depreciated.</p>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-bx1-1" block_type="bx-1-h">
<box-metadata><box-title><strong>PITFALLS</strong> <image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-img-34" alt="image" src="images/world_view_icon.jpg"/></box-title></box-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p277" block_type="bx1-t"><strong>WHICH WAY IS UP?</strong></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p278" block_type="bx1-txt-ni">What does it mean when someone says &#8220;the U.S. exchange rate is up&#8221;?</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p279" block_type="bx1-txt">It isn&#8217;t clear. Sometimes the exchange rate is measured as the price of a dollar in terms of foreign currency, sometimes as the price of foreign currency in terms of dollars. So the statement could mean either that the dollar appreciated or that it depreciated!</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p280" block_type="bx1-txt">And be careful when using published statistics. Most countries other than the United States state their exchange rates in terms of the price of a dollar in their domestic currency&#8212;for example, Mexican officials will say that the exchange rate is 10, meaning 10 pesos per dollar. But Britain, for historical reasons, usually states its exchange rate the other way. On November 21, 2014, US&#36;1 was worth &#163;0.6362, and &#163;1 was worth US&#36;1.5718. More often than not, this number is reported as an exchange rate of 1.5718.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p281" block_type="bx1-txt">Americans generally follow other countries&#8217; lead: we usually say that the exchange rate against Mexico is 10 pesos per dollar but that the exchange rate against Britain is 1.57 dollars per pound. But this rule isn&#8217;t reliable; exchange rates against the euro are often stated both ways.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p282" block_type="bx1-txt">So always check before using exchange rate data: which way is the exchange rate being measured?</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p283" block_type="txt">Movements in exchange rates, other things equal, affect the relative prices of goods, services, and assets in different countries. Suppose, for example, that the price of an American hotel room is US&#36;100 and the price of a French hotel room is &#8364;100. If the exchange rate is &#8364;1 = US&#36;1, these hotel rooms have the same price. If the exchange rate is &#8364;1.25 = US&#36;1, the French hotel room is 20&#37; cheaper than the American hotel room. If the exchange rate is &#8364;0.80 = US&#36;1, the French hotel room is 25&#37; more expensive than the American hotel room.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p284" block_type="txt">But what determines exchange rates? Supply and demand in the foreign exchange market.</p>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-sec2-14" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="20" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="596">
<section-metadata><section-title>The Equilibrium Exchange Rate</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p285" block_type="txt-ni">Imagine, for the sake of simplicity, that there are only two currencies in the world: U.S. dollars and euros. Europeans wanting to purchase American goods, services, and assets come to the foreign exchange market, wanting to exchange euros for U.S. dollars. That is, Europeans demand U.S. dollars from the foreign exchange market and, correspondingly, supply euros to that market. Americans wanting to buy European goods, services, and assets come to the foreign exchange market to exchange U.S. dollars for euros. That is, Americans supply U.S. dollars to the foreign exchange market and, correspondingly, demand euros from that market. (International transfers and payments of factor income also enter into the foreign exchange market, but to make things simple we&#8217;ll ignore these.)</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p286" block_type="txt"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-fig-23">Figure 20-14</link> shows how the foreign exchange market works. The quantity of dollars demanded and supplied at any given euro&#8211;U.S. dollar exchange rate is shown on the horizontal axis, and the euro&#8211;U.S. dollar exchange rate is shown on the vertical axis. The exchange rate plays the same role as the price of a good or service in an ordinary supply and demand diagram.</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-fig-23" block_type="figure" numbered="true" number="20-14" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<caption><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-fig-23"><phrase block_type="fig-label"><phrase block_type="fig"><strong>FIGURE</strong></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_num"><strong>20-14</strong></phrase></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_title">The Foreign Exchange Market</phrase></link></caption>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-img-35" alt="image" src="images/KrugESS4e_fig_20_14.jpg"/>
<caption>The foreign exchange market matches up the demand for a currency from foreigners who want to buy domestic goods, services, and assets with the supply of a currency from domestic residents who want to buy foreign goods, services, and assets. Here the equilibrium in the market for dollars is at point <em>E</em>, corresponding to an equilibrium exchange rate of &#8364;0.80 per US&#36;1.</caption>
</figure>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p287" block_type="txt">The figure shows two curves, the demand curve for U.S. dollars and the supply curve for U.S. dollars. The key to understanding the slopes of these curves is that the level of the exchange rate affects exports and imports. When a country&#8217;s currency appreciates (becomes more valuable), exports fall and imports rise. When a country&#8217;s currency depreciates (becomes less valuable), exports rise and imports fall.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p288" block_type="txt">To understand why the demand curve for U.S. dollars slopes downward, recall that the exchange rate, other things equal, determines the prices of American goods, services, and assets relative to those of European goods, services, and assets.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_597" block_type="page_start">597</p>
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-list-16" type="unordered" block_type="bullet">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p289" block_type="bl-first">If the U.S. dollar rises against the euro (the dollar appreciates), American products will become more expensive to Europeans relative to European products. So Europeans will buy less from the United States and will acquire fewer dollars in the foreign exchange market: the quantity of U.S. dollars demanded falls as the number of euros needed to buy a U.S. dollar rises.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p290" block_type="bl-last">If the U.S. dollar falls against the euro (the dollar depreciates), American products will become relatively cheaper for Europeans. Europeans will respond by buying more from the United States and acquiring more dollars in the foreign exchange market: the quantity of U.S. dollars demanded rises as the number of euros needed to buy a U.S. dollar falls.</p></li>
</list>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p291" block_type="txt">A similar argument explains why the supply curve of U.S. dollars in <link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-fig-23">Figure 20-14</link> slopes upward: the more euros required to buy a U.S. dollar, the more dollars Americans will supply. Again, the reason is the effect of the exchange rate on relative prices. If the U.S. dollar rises against the euro, European products look cheaper to Americans&#8212;who will demand more of them. This will require Americans to convert more dollars into euros.</p>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-exp3-26" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p292" block_type="mn-gl-def">The <strong>equilibrium exchange rate</strong> is the exchange rate at which the quantity of a currency demanded in the foreign exchange market is equal to the quantity supplied.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p293" block_type="txt">The <strong>equilibrium exchange rate</strong> is the exchange rate at which the quantity of U.S. dollars demanded in the foreign exchange market is equal to the quantity of U.S. dollars supplied. In <link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-fig-23">Figure 20-14</link>, the equilibrium is at point <em>E,</em> and the equilibrium exchange rate is 0.80. That is, at an exchange rate of &#8364;0.80 per US&#36;1, the quantity of U.S. dollars supplied to the foreign exchange market is equal to the quantity of U.S. dollars demanded.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p294" block_type="txt">To understand the significance of the equilibrium exchange rate, it&#8217;s helpful to consider a numerical example of what equilibrium in the foreign exchange market looks like. A hypothetical example is shown in <link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-tab-6">Table 20-6</link>. The first row shows European purchases of U.S. dollars, either to buy U.S. goods and services or to buy U.S. assets. The second row shows U.S. sales of U.S. dollars, either to buy European goods and services or to buy European assets. At the equilibrium exchange rate, the total quantity of U.S. dollars Europeans want to buy is equal to the total quantity of U.S. dollars Americans want to sell.</p>
<table id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-tab-6" block_type="table" numbered="false" caption-placement="Top" data-href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-tab-6" data-target="_pop">
<table_caption><strong><phrase block_type="tbl">TABLE</phrase> <phrase block_type="tbl_num">20-6</phrase></strong> <phrase block_type="tbl_title">A Hypothetical Equilibrium in the Foreign Exchange Market</phrase></table_caption>
<tbody>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tbl-rborder tbl-ljust"><strong>European purchases of U.S. dollars (trillions of U.S. dollars)</strong></td>
<td class="tbl-rborder tbl-ljust">To buy U.S. goods and services: 1.0</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder tbl-ljust">To buy U.S. assets: 1.0</td>
<td class="tbl-ljust"><strong>Total purchases of U.S. dollars: 2.0</strong></td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-dark">
<td class="tbl-rborder tbl-ljust"><strong>U.S. sales of U.S. dollars (trillions of U.S. dollars)</strong></td>
<td class="tbl-rborder tbl-ljust">To buy European goods and services: 1.5</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder tbl-ljust">To buy European assets: 0.5</td>
<td class="tbl-ljust"><strong>Total sales of U.S. dollars: 2.0</strong></td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tbl-tborder tbl-rborder"></td>
<td class="tbl-tborder tbl-rborder tbl-ljust"><strong>U.S. balance of payments on current account: &#8722;0.5</strong></td>
<td class="tbl-tborder tbl-rborder tbl-ljust"><strong>U.S. balance of payments on financial account: &#43;0.5</strong></td>
<td class="tbl-tborder"></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_598" block_type="page_start">598</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p295" block_type="txt">Remember that the balance of payments accounts divide international transactions into two types:</p>
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-list-17" type="ordered" block_type="numbered">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p296" block_type="nl-first">Purchases and sales of goods and services are counted in the current account. (Again, we&#8217;re leaving out transfers and factor income to keep things simple.) </p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p297" block_type="nl-last">Purchases and sales of assets are counted in the financial account. At the equilibrium exchange rate, then, we have the situation shown in <link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-tab-6">Table 20-6</link>: the sum of the balance of payments on current account plus the balance of payments on financial account is zero.</p></li>
</list>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p298" block_type="txt">Now let&#8217;s briefly consider how a shift in the demand for U.S. dollars affects equilibrium in the foreign exchange market. Suppose that for some reason capital flows from Europe to the United States increase&#8212;say, due to a change in the preferences of European investors. The effects are shown in <link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-fig-24">Figure 20-15</link>. The demand for U.S. dollars in the foreign exchange market increases as European investors convert euros into dollars to fund their new investments in the United States. This is shown by the shift of the demand curve from <em>D</em><sub>1</sub> to <em>D</em><sub>2</sub>. As a result, the U.S. dollar appreciates against the euro: the number of euros per U.S. dollar at the equilibrium exchange rate rises from <em>XR</em><sub>1</sub> to <em>XR</em><sub>2</sub>.</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-fig-24" block_type="figure" numbered="true" number="20-15" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<caption><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-fig-24"><phrase block_type="fig-label"><phrase block_type="fig"><strong>FIGURE</strong></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_num"><strong>20-15</strong></phrase></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_title">An Increase in the Demand for U.S. Dollars</phrase></link></caption>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-img-36" alt="image" src="images/KrugESS4e_fig_20_15.jpg"/>
<caption>An increase in the demand for U.S. dollars might result from a change in the preferences of European investors. The demand curve for U.S. dollars shifts from <em>D</em><sub>1</sub> to <em>D</em><sub>2</sub>. So the equilibrium number of euros per U.S. dollar rises&#8212;the dollar appreciates against the euro. As a result, the balance of payments on current account falls as the balance of payments on financial account rises.</caption>
</figure>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p299" block_type="txt">What are the consequences of this increased capital inflow for the balance of payments? The total quantity of U.S. dollars supplied to the foreign exchange market still must equal the total quantity of U.S. dollars demanded. So the increased capital inflow to the United States&#8212;an increase in the balance of payments on financial account&#8212;must be matched by a decline in the balance of payments on current account. What causes the balance of payments on current account to decline? The appreciation of the U.S. dollar. A rise in the number of euros per U.S. dollar leads Americans to buy more European goods and services and Europeans to buy fewer American goods and services.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_599" block_type="page_start">599</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p300" block_type="txt"><link href="#0000">Table 20-7</link> shows a hypothetical example of how this might work. Europeans are buying more U.S. assets, increasing the balance of payments on financial account from 0.5 to 1.0. This is offset by a reduction in European purchases of U.S. goods and services and a rise in U.S. purchases of European goods and services, both the result of the dollar&#8217;s appreciation. <em>So any change in the U.S. balance of payments on financial account generates an equal and opposite reaction in the balance of payments on current account.</em> Movements in the exchange rate ensure that changes in the financial account and in the current account offset each other.</p>
<table id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-tab-7" block_type="table" numbered="false" caption-placement="Top" data-href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-tab-7" data-target="_pop">
<table_caption><strong><phrase block_type="tbl">TABLE</phrase> <phrase block_type="tbl_num">20-7</phrase></strong> <phrase block_type="tbl_title">A Hypothetical Example of Effects of Increased Capital Inflows</phrase></table_caption>
<tbody>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tbl-rborder tbl-ljust"><strong>European purchases of U.S. dollars (trillions of U.S. dollars)</strong></td>
<td class="tbl-rborder tbl-ljust">To buy U.S. goods and services: 0.75 (down 0.25)</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder tbl-ljust">To buy U.S. assets: 1.5 (up 0.5)</td>
<td class="tbl-ljust"><strong>Total purchases of U.S. dollars: 2.25</strong></td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-dark">
<td class="tbl-rborder tbl-ljust"><strong>U.S. sales of U.S. dollars (trillions of U.S. dollars)</strong></td>
<td class="tbl-rborder tbl-ljust">To buy European goods and services: 1.75 (up 0.25)</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder tbl-ljust">To buy European assets: 0.5 (no change)</td>
<td class="tbl-ljust"><strong>Total sales of U.S. dollars: 2.25</strong></td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tbl-tborder tbl-rborder"></td>
<td class="tbl-tborder tbl-rborder tbl-ljust"><strong>U.S. balance of payments on current account: &#8722;1.0 (down 0.5)</strong></td>
<td class="tbl-tborder tbl-rborder tbl-ljust"><strong>U.S. balance of payments on financial account: &#43;1.0 (up 0.5)</strong></td>
<td class="tbl-tborder"></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p301" block_type="txt">Let&#8217;s briefly run this process in reverse. Suppose there is a reduction in capital flows from Europe to the United States&#8212;again due to a change in the preferences of European investors. The demand for U.S. dollars in the foreign exchange market falls, and the dollar depreciates: the number of euros per U.S. dollar at the equilibrium exchange rate falls. This leads Americans to buy fewer European products and Europeans to buy more American products. Ultimately, this generates an increase in the U.S. balance of payments on current account. So a fall in capital flows into the United States leads to a weaker dollar, which in turn generates an increase in U.S. net exports.</p>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-sec2-15" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="20" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="599">
<section-metadata><section-title>Inflation and Real Exchange Rates</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p302" block_type="txt-ni">In 1993 one U.S. dollar exchanged, on average, for 3.1 Mexican pesos. By 2013, the peso had fallen against the dollar by more than 75&#37;, with an average exchange rate in 2013 of 12.8 pesos per dollar. Did Mexican products also become much cheaper relative to U.S. products over that 20-year period? Did the price of Mexican products expressed in terms of U.S. dollars also fall by 75&#37;? The answer is no, because Mexico had much higher inflation than the United States over that period. In fact, the relative price of U.S. and Mexican products changed little between 1993 and 2013, although the exchange rate changed a lot.</p>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-exp3-27" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p303" block_type="mn-gl-def"><strong>Real exchange rates</strong> are exchange rates adjusted for international differences in aggregate price levels.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p304" block_type="txt">To take account of the effects of differences in inflation rates, economists calculate <strong>real exchange rates,</strong> exchange rates adjusted for international differences in aggregate price levels. Suppose that the exchange rate we are looking at is the number of Mexican pesos per U.S. dollar. Let <em>P<sub>US</sub></em> and <em>P<sub>Mex</sub></em> be indexes of the aggregate price levels in the United States and Mexico, respectively. Then the real exchange rate between the Mexican peso and the U.S. dollar is defined as:</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-fig-25" block_type="equation" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-img-37" alt="image" src="images/KrugESS4e_eqn_599_01.jpg"/>
</figure>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p305" block_type="txt-ni">To distinguish it from the real exchange rate, the exchange rate unadjusted for aggregate price levels is sometimes called the <em>nominal</em> exchange rate.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p306" block_type="txt">To understand the significance of the difference between the real and nominal exchange rates, let&#8217;s consider the following example. Suppose that the Mexican peso depreciates against the U.S. dollar, with the exchange rate going from 10 pesos per U.S. dollar to 15 pesos per U.S. dollar, a 50&#37; change. But suppose that at the same time the price of everything in Mexico, measured in pesos, increases by 50&#37;, so that the Mexican price index rises from 100 to 150. At the same time, suppose that there is no change in U.S. prices, so that the U.S. price index remains at 100. Then the initial real exchange rate is:</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-fig-26" block_type="equation" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-img-38" alt="image" src="images/KrugESS4e_eqn_599_02.jpg"/>
</figure>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_600" block_type="page_start">600</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p307" block_type="txt-ni">After the peso depreciates and the Mexican price level increases, the real exchange rate is:</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-fig-27" block_type="equation" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-img-39" alt="image" src="images/KrugESS4e_eqn_600_01.jpg"/>
</figure>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p308" block_type="txt-ni">In this example, the peso has depreciated substantially in terms of the U.S. dollar, but the <em>real</em> exchange rate between the peso and the U.S. dollar hasn&#8217;t changed at all. And because the real peso&#8211;U.S. dollar exchange rate hasn&#8217;t changed, the nominal depreciation of the peso against the U.S. dollar will have no effect either on the quantity of goods and services exported by Mexico to the United States or on the quantity of goods and services imported by Mexico from the United States.</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-fig-28" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="right" width="medium" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-img-40" alt="image" src="images/KrugESS4e_20UN08.jpg"/>
<caption>It&#8217;s the real exchange rate, not the nominal exchange rate, that counts in decisions about buying and selling abroad.</caption>
<asset_source>Keith Dannemiller/Alamy</asset_source>
</figure>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p309" block_type="txt">To see why, consider again the example of a hotel room. Suppose that this room initially costs 1,000 pesos per night, which is &#36;100 at an exchange rate of 10 pesos per dollar. After both Mexican prices and the number of pesos per dollar rise by 50&#37;, the hotel room costs 1,500 pesos per night&#8212;but 1,500 pesos divided by 15 pesos per dollar is &#36;100, so the Mexican hotel room still costs &#36;100. As a result, a U.S. tourist considering a trip to Mexico will have no reason to change plans. </p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p310" block_type="txt">The same is true for all goods and services that enter into trade: <em>the current account responds only to changes in the real exchange rate, not the nominal exchange rate.</em> A country&#8217;s products become cheaper to foreigners only when that country&#8217;s currency depreciates in real terms, and those products become more expensive to foreigners only when the currency appreciates in real terms. As a consequence, economists who analyze movements in exports and imports of goods and services focus on the real exchange rate, not the nominal exchange rate.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p311" block_type="txt"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-fig-29">Figure 20-16</link> illustrates just how important it can be to distinguish between nominal and real exchange rates. The line labeled &#8220;Nominal exchange rate&#8221; shows the number of pesos it took to buy a U.S. dollar from 1993 to 2013. As you can see, the peso depreciated massively over that period. But the line labeled &#8220;Real exchange rate&#8221; shows the real exchange rate: it was calculated using Equation 20-4, with price indexes for both Mexico and the United States set so that 1993 = 100. In real terms, the peso depreciated between 1994 and 1995, but not by nearly as much as the nominal depreciation. By 2013, the real peso&#8211;U.S. dollar exchange rate was just about back where it started.</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-fig-29" block_type="figure" numbered="true" number="20-16" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<caption><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-fig-29"><phrase block_type="fig-label"><phrase block_type="fig"><strong>FIGURE</strong></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_num"><strong>20-16</strong></phrase></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_title">Real versus Nominal Exchange Rates, 1993&#8211;2013</phrase></link></caption>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-img-41" alt="image" src="images/KrugESS4e_fig_20_16.jpg"/>
<caption>Between November 1993 and December 2013, the price of a dollar in Mexican pesos increased dramatically. But because Mexico had higher inflation than the United States, the real exchange rate, which measures the relative price of Mexican goods and services, ended up roughly where it started.</caption>
<asset_source><em>Data from:</em> Federal Reserve Bank of St. Louis.</asset_source>
</figure>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_601" block_type="page_start">601</p>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-sec2-16" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="20" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="601">
<section-metadata><section-title>Purchasing Power Parity</section-title></section-metadata>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-exp3-28" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p312" block_type="mn-gl-def">The <strong>purchasing power parity</strong> between two countries&#8217; currencies is the nominal exchange rate at which a given basket of goods and services would cost the same amount in each country.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p313" block_type="txt-ni">A useful tool for analyzing exchange rates, closely connected to the concept of the real exchange rate, is known as <em>purchasing power parity.</em> The <strong>purchasing power parity</strong> between two countries&#8217; currencies is the nominal exchange rate at which a given basket of goods and services would cost the same amount in each country. Suppose, for example, that a basket of goods and services that costs &#36;100 in the United States costs 1,000 pesos in Mexico. Then the purchasing power parity is 10 pesos per U.S. dollar: at that exchange rate, 1,000 pesos = &#36;100, so the market basket costs the same amount in both countries.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p314" block_type="txt">Calculations of purchasing power parities are usually made by estimating the cost of buying broad market baskets containing many goods and services&#8212;everything from automobiles and groceries to housing and telephone calls. But as the following For Inquiring Minds explains, once a year the magazine <em>The Economist</em> publishes a list of purchasing power parities based on the cost of buying a market basket that contains only one item&#8212;a McDonald&#8217;s Big Mac.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p315" block_type="txt">Nominal exchange rates almost always differ from purchasing power parities. Some of these differences are systematic: in general, aggregate price levels are lower in poor countries than in rich countries because services tend to be cheaper in poor countries. But even among countries at roughly the same level of economic development, nominal exchange rates vary quite a lot from purchasing power parity. <link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-fig-30">Figure 20-17</link> shows the nominal exchange rate between the Canadian dollar and the U.S. dollar, measured as the number of Canadian dollars per U.S. dollar, from 1990 to 2013, together with an estimate of the purchasing power parity exchange rate between the United States and Canada over the same period.</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-fig-30" block_type="figure" numbered="true" number="20-17" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<caption><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-fig-30"><phrase block_type="fig-label"><phrase block_type="fig"><strong>FIGURE</strong></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_num"><strong>20-17</strong></phrase></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_title">Purchasing Power Parity versus the Nominal Exchange Rate, 1990&#8211;2013</phrase></link></caption>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-img-42" alt="image" src="images/KrugESS4e_fig_20_17.jpg"/>
<caption>The purchasing power parity between the United States and Canada&#8212;the exchange rate at which a basket of goods and services would have cost the same amount in both countries&#8212;changed very little over the period shown, staying near C&#36;1.20 per US&#36;1. But the nominal exchange rate fluctuated widely.</caption>
<asset_source><em>Data from:</em> OECD.</asset_source>
</figure>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_602" block_type="page_start">602</p>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-bx3-2" block_type="bx3-t">
<box-metadata><box-title><strong>FOR INQUIRING MINDS</strong> &#124; Burgernomics <image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-img-43" alt="image" src="images/world_view_icon.jpg"/></box-title></box-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p316" block_type="bx3-txt-ni">For a number of years the British magazine <em>The Economist</em> has produced an annual comparison of the cost in different countries of one particular consumption item that is found around the world&#8212;a McDonald&#8217;s Big Mac. The magazine finds the price of a Big Mac in local currency, then computes two numbers: the price of a Big Mac in U.S. dollars using the prevailing exchange rate and the exchange rate at which the price of a Big Mac would equal the U.S. price.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p317" block_type="bx3-txt">If purchasing power parity held for Big Macs, the dollar price of a Big Mac would be the same everywhere. If purchasing power parity is a good theory for the long run, the exchange rate at which a Big Mac&#8217;s price matches the U.S. price should offer some guidance about where the exchange rate will eventually end up.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p318" block_type="bx3-txt"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-tab-8">Table 20-8</link> shows the <em>Economist</em> estimates for selected countries as of July 2014, ranked in increasing order of the dollar price of a Big Mac. The countries with the cheapest Big Macs, and therefore by this measure with the most undervalued currencies, are India and China, both developing countries. But not all developing countries have low-priced Big Macs: the price of a Big Mac in Brazil, converted into dollars, is considerably higher than in the United States. This reflects a sharp appreciation of the <em>real,</em> Brazil&#8217;s currency, in recent years as the country has become a favorite of international investors.</p>
<table id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-tab-8" block_type="table" numbered="false" caption-placement="Top" data-href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-tab-8" data-target="_pop">
<table_caption><strong><phrase block_type="tbl">TABLE</phrase> <phrase block_type="tbl_num">20-8</phrase></strong> <phrase block_type="tbl_title">Purchasing Power Parity and the Price of a Big Mac</phrase></table_caption>
<tbody>
<tr class="tbl-hdr-bg">
<td class="tbl-rborder"></td>
<td colspan="2" class="tbl-bborder tbl-rborder"><strong>Big Mac price</strong></td>
<td colspan="2" class="tbl-bborder"><strong>Local currency per dollar</strong></td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-hdr-bg">
<td class="tbl-ljust"><strong>Country</strong></td>
<td class="tbl-lborder"><strong>In local<br/> currency</strong></td>
<td class="tbl-lborder"><strong>In U.S. dollars</strong></td>
<td class="tbl-lborder"><strong>Implied PPP</strong></td>
<td class="tbl-lborder"><strong>Actual<br/> exchange rate</strong></td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tbl-ljust">India</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">Rupee 105</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">1.75</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">21.90</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">60.09</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-dark">
<td class="tbl-ljust">China</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">Yuan 16.9</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">2.73</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">3.52</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">6.20</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tbl-ljust">Mexico</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">Peso 42</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">3.25</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">8.76</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">12.93</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-dark">
<td class="tbl-ljust">Britain</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">&#163; 2.89</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">4.93</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">0.60</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">0.59</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tbl-ljust">United States</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">&#36;4.80</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">4.80</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">1.00</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">1.00</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-dark">
<td class="tbl-ljust">Japan</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">&#165; 370</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">3.64</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">77.16</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">101.53</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tbl-ljust">Euro area</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">&#8364; 3.68</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">4.95</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">0.77</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">0.74</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-dark">
<td class="tbl-ljust">Brazil</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">Real 13</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">5.86</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">2.71</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">2.22</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tbl-ljust">Switzerland</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">SFr 6.16</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">6.83</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">1.28</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">0.90</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p319" block_type="bx3-txt">And topping the list, with a Big Mac some 75&#37; more expensive than in the United States, is Switzerland, which took extraordinary action in 2011 in an effort to depreciate its currency.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p320" block_type="txt">The purchasing power parity didn&#8217;t change much over the whole period because the United States and Canada had about the same rate of inflation. But at the beginning of the period the nominal exchange rate was below purchasing power parity, so a given market basket was more expensive in Canada than in the United States. By 2002 the nominal exchange rate was far above the purchasing power parity, so a market basket was much cheaper in Canada than in the United States.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p321" block_type="txt">Over the long run, however, purchasing power parities are pretty good at predicting actual changes in nominal exchange rates. In particular, nominal exchange rates between countries at similar levels of economic development tend to fluctuate around levels that lead to similar costs for a given market basket. In fact, by July 2005 the nominal exchange rate between the United States and Canada was C&#36;1.22 per US&#36;1&#8212;just about the purchasing power parity. And by 2013 the cost of living was once again higher in Canada than in the United States.</p>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-bx2-5" block_type="bx-2-h">
<box-metadata><box-title><phrase block_type="title">ECONOMICS</phrase> <phrase block_type="number"><em>in Action</em></phrase><image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-img-44" alt="image" src="images/world_view_icon.jpg"/></box-title></box-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p323" block_type="bx-2-t"><strong>Low-Cost America</strong></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p324" block_type="bx2-first"><phrase block_type="dropcap">D</phrase>oes the exchange rate matter for business decisions? And how. Consider what European auto manufacturers were doing in 2008. One report from the University of Iowa summarized the situation as follows:</p>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-exp2-5" block_type="mn2">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p322" block_type="fg1-t"><image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-img-45" alt="image" src="images/launchpad_logo_cmyk.jpg"/> &#124; interactive activity</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p325" block_type="ext">While luxury German carmakers BMW and Mercedes have maintained plants in the American South since the 1990s, BMW aims to expand U.S. manufacturing in South Carolina by 50&#37; during the next 5 years. Volvo of Sweden is in negotiations to build a plant in New Mexico. Analysts at Italian carmaker Fiat determined that it needs to build a North American factory to profit from the upcoming relaunch of its Alfa Romeo model. Tennessee recently closed a deal with Volkswagen to build a &#36;1 billion factory by offering &#36;577 million in incentives.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_603" block_type="page_start">603</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p326" block_type="bx2-txt">Why were European automakers flocking to America? To some extent because they were being offered special incentives, as the case of Volkswagen in Tennessee illustrates. But the big factor was the exchange rate. In the early 2000s one euro was, on average, worth less than a dollar; by the summer of 2008 the exchange rate was around &#8364;1 = &#36;1.50. This change in the exchange rate made it substantially cheaper for European car manufacturers to produce in the United States than at home&#8212;especially if the cars were intended for the U.S. market.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p327" block_type="bx2-txt">Automobile manufacturing wasn&#8217;t the only U.S. industry benefiting from the weak dollar; across the board, U.S. exports surged after 2006 while import growth fell off. <link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-fig-31">Figure 20-18</link> shows one measure of U.S. trade performance, real net exports of goods and services: exports minus imports, both measured in 2009 dollars. As you can see, this balance, after a long slide, turned sharply upward in 2006. There was a modest reversal in 2009&#8211;2010, as an economy recovering from the 2007&#8211;2009 recession pulled in more imports, but a major narrowing of the trade gap remained in place.</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-fig-31" block_type="figure" numbered="true" number="20-18" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="right" width="medium" border="true"/>
<caption><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-fig-31"><phrase block_type="fig-label"><phrase block_type="fig"><strong>FIGURE</strong></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_num"><strong>20-18</strong></phrase></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_title">U.S. Net Exports, 2000&#8211;2014</phrase></link></caption>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-img-46" alt="image" src="images/KrugESS4e_fig_20_18.jpg"/>
<asset_source><em>Data from:</em> Federal Reserve Bank of St. Louis.</asset_source>
</figure>
</box>
<box title="Quick Review" numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-bx5-5" block_type="sr-1-h">
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-list-18" type="unordered" block_type="redbullet">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p328" block_type="sr1-bl">Currencies are traded in the <strong>foreign exchange market,</strong> which determines <strong>exchange rates.</strong></p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p329" block_type="sr1-bl">Exchange rates can be measured in two ways. To avoid confusion, economists say that a currency <strong>appreciates</strong> or <strong>depreciates.</strong> The <strong>equilibrium exchange rate</strong> matches the supply and demand for currencies on the foreign exchange market.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p330" block_type="sr1-bl">To take account of differences in national price levels, economists calculate <strong>real exchange rates.</strong> The current account responds only to changes in the real exchange rate, not the nominal exchange rate.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p331" block_type="sr1-bl"><strong>Purchasing power parity</strong> is the nominal exchange rate that equalizes the price of a market basket in the two countries. While the nominal exchange rate almost always differs from purchasing power parity, purchasing power parity is a good predictor of actual changes in the nominal exchange rate.</p></li>
</list>
</box>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-bx6-5" block_type="sr2-h">
<box-metadata><box-title><phrase block_type="title">Check Your Understanding</phrase> <phrase block_type="number">20-5</phrase></box-title></box-metadata>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-cyuquestion-9" block_type="q_cyu" number="1">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p332" block_type="sr2-nl-first"><phrase block_type="qnum">1.</phrase> Mexico discovers huge reserves of oil and starts exporting oil to the United States. Describe how this would affect the following.</p>
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-list-19" type="ordered" block_type="loweralpha">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p333" block_type="sr2-nl-lvl2">The nominal peso&#8211;U.S. dollar exchange rate</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p334" block_type="sr2-nl-lvl2">Mexican exports of other goods and services</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p335" block_type="sr2-nl-lvl2">Mexican imports of goods and services</p></li>
</list>
</question>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-cyuquestion-10" block_type="q_cyu" number="2">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p336" block_type="sr2-nl-mid"><phrase block_type="qnum">2.</phrase> A basket of goods and services that costs &#36;100 in the United States costs 800 pesos in Mexico, and the current nominal exchange rate is 10 pesos per U.S. dollar. Over the next five years, the cost of that market basket rises to &#36;120 in the United States and to 1,200 pesos in Mexico, although the nominal exchange rate remains at 10 pesos per U.S. dollar. Calculate the following.</p>
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-list-20" type="ordered" block_type="loweralpha">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p337" block_type="sr2-nl-lvl2">The real exchange rate now and five years from now, if today&#8217;s price index in both countries is 100</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p338" block_type="sr2-nl-lvl2">Purchasing power parity today and five years from now</p></li>
</list>
</question>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p339" block_type="sr2-nl-fn">Solutions appear at back of book.</p>
</box>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-sec1-6" block_type="solved_problem" title="" chapter="20" numbered="true" level="1" print_page="604">
<section-metadata><section-title>Solved Problem</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_604" block_type="page_start">604</p>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-bx7-1" block_type="sum-h">
<box-metadata><box-title><phrase block_type="gc1">SOLVED PROBLEM</phrase> <phrase block_type="gc2">Trade Is Sweet</phrase></box-title></box-metadata>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-exp2-6" block_type="mn2">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p340" block_type="fg1-t"><image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-img-47" alt="image" src="images/launchpad_logo_cmyk.jpg"/> for interactive tutorials with step-by-stepguidance on how to solve problems</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p341" block_type="wio-txt-ni">The United States has a long-standing policy of trade protection in the sugar industry. As part of the sugar program, the United States Department of Agriculture limits imports to less than 15&#37; of domestic consumption. The policy is controversial, with producers of sodas, candy bars, and other sweetened snacks pitted against sugar growers as well as some public health advocates. </p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p342" block_type="wio-txt">Using the following hypothetical U.S. domestic demand and supply schedule for sugar, determine how many tons of sugar the United States produces in autarky and the equilibrium price per ton.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p343" block_type="wio-txt">If the world price of sugar is &#36;500 per ton, will the United States import or export sugar? How much will they import if there were no import restrictions?</p>
<table id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-untab-9" block_type="un_table" data-href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-untab-9" data-target="_pop">
<layout align="center" width="large"/>
<tbody>
<tr class="tbl-hdr-bg">
<td class="tbl-rborder"><strong>Price of sugar<br/> (&#36; per metric ton)</strong></td>
<td class="tbl-rborder"><strong>Quantity of sugar demanded<br/> (millions of tons)</strong></td>
<td><strong>Quantity of sugar supplied<br/> (millions of tons)</strong></td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tbl-rborder">&#36;650</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder">4</td>
<td>12</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-dark">
<td class="tbl-rborder">600</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder">6</td>
<td>10</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tbl-rborder">550</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder">8</td>
<td>8</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-dark">
<td class="tbl-rborder">500</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder">10</td>
<td>6</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tbl-rborder">450</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder">12</td>
<td>4</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-dark">
<td class="tbl-rborder">400</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder">14</td>
<td>2</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tbl-rborder">350</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder">16</td>
<td>0</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p344" block_type="sp-stp-txt"><phrase block_type="step"><phrase block_type="step-green">STEP</phrase> &#124; <phrase block_type="step-green">1</phrase></phrase> <phrase block_type="step-title"><strong>In autarky, how many tons of sugar does the United States produce, and at what price are they bought and sold?</strong>
<phrase block_type="step-subtext">Review page 579.</phrase></phrase></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p345" block_type="wio-txt-ni">In autarky, the United States produces 8 million tons of sugar, and sugar is sold at &#36;550 per metric ton. This is the quantity and price at which &#8220;Quantity of sugar demanded&#8221; equals &#8220;Quantity of sugar supplied&#8221; in the table. At this price and production level, the market is in equilibrium.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p346" block_type="sp-stp-txt"><phrase block_type="step"><phrase block_type="step-green">STEP</phrase> &#124; <phrase block_type="step-green">2</phrase></phrase> <phrase block_type="step-title"><strong>If the world price of sugar is &#36;500 per ton, will the United States import or export sugar?</strong>
<phrase block_type="step-subtext">Review pages 579&#8211;581.</phrase></phrase></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p347" block_type="wio-txt-ni">As shown in <link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-fig-12">Figure 20-6</link>, if the world price is less than the autarky price, then a country will import. In this case, the world price is &#36;500 per ton, and as determined in step 1, the autarky price is &#36;550 per ton, so the United States will import sugar.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p348" block_type="sp-stp-txt"><phrase block_type="step"><phrase block_type="step-green">STEP</phrase> &#124; <phrase block_type="step-green">3</phrase></phrase> <phrase block_type="step-title"><strong>Determine how much will be imported or exported.</strong>
<phrase block_type="step-subtext">Review pages 579&#8211;581.</phrase></phrase></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p349" block_type="wio-txt-ni">Domestic demand at a world price of &#36;500 per ton is 10 million tons, and domestic supply at a world price of &#36;500 per ton is 6 million tons. Since there is a shortage of 4 million tons, the United States will import 4 million tons of sugar if there are no import restrictions.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p350" block_type="wio-txt">But in reality, because of the sugar program the United States could not import the required amount of sugar, resulting in higher prices.</p>
</box>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-sec1-7" block_type="cr-que-t" title="" chapter="20" numbered="true" level="1" print_page="604">
<section-metadata><section-title>SUMMARY</section-title></section-metadata>
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-list-21" type="ordered" block_type="numbered">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p351" block_type="sum-nl">International trade is of growing importance to the United States and of even greater importance to most other countries. International trade, like trade among individuals, arises from comparative advantage: the opportunity cost of producing an additional unit of a good is lower in some countries than in others. Goods and services purchased from abroad are <strong>imports;</strong> those sold abroad are <strong>exports.</strong> Foreign trade, like other economic linkages between countries, has been growing rapidly, a phenomenon called <strong>globalization. Hyperglobalization,</strong> the phenomenon of extremely high levels of international trade, has occurred as advances in communication and transportation technology have allowed supply chains of production to span the globe.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p352" block_type="sum-nl">The <strong>Ricardian model of international trade</strong> assumes that opportunity costs are constant. It shows that there are gains from trade: two countries are better off with trade than in <strong>autarky.</strong></p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p353" block_type="sum-nl">In practice, comparative advantage reflects differences between countries in climate, factor endowments, and technology. The <strong>Heckscher&#8211;Ohlin model</strong> shows how differences in factor endowments determine comparative advantage: goods differ in <strong>factor intensity,</strong> and countries tend to export goods that are intensive in the factors they have in abundance.</p>
 <p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_605" block_type="page_start">605</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p354" block_type="sum-nl">The <strong>domestic demand curve</strong> and the <strong>domestic supply curve</strong> determine the price of a good in autarky. When international trade occurs, the domestic price is driven to equality with the <strong>world price,</strong> the price at which the good is bought and sold abroad.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p355" block_type="sum-nl">If the world price is below the autarky price, a good is imported. This leads to an increase in consumer surplus, a fall in producer surplus, and a gain in total surplus. If the world price is above the autarky price, a good is exported. This leads to an increase in producer surplus, a fall in consumer surplus, and a gain in total surplus.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p356" block_type="sum-nl">International trade leads to expansion in <strong>exporting industries</strong> and contraction in <strong>import-competing industries.</strong> This raises the domestic demand for abundant factors of production, reduces the demand for scarce factors, and so affects factor prices, such as wages.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p357" block_type="sum-nl">Most economists advocate <strong>free trade,</strong> but in practice many governments engage in <strong>trade protection.</strong> The two most common forms of <strong>protection</strong> are tariffs and quotas. In rare occasions, export industries are subsidized. </p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p358" block_type="sum-nl">A <strong>tariff</strong> is a tax levied on imports. It raises the domestic price above the world price, hurting consumers, benefiting domestic producers, and generating government revenue. As a result, total surplus falls. An <strong>import quota</strong> is a legal limit on the quantity of a good that can be imported. It has the same effects as a tariff, except that the revenue goes not to the government but to those who receive import licenses.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p359" block_type="sum-nl">A country&#8217;s <strong>balance of payments accounts</strong> summarize its transactions with the rest of the world. The <strong>balance of payments on current account,</strong> or <strong>current account,</strong> includes the <strong>balance of payments on goods and services</strong> together with balances on factor income and transfers. The <strong>merchandise trade balance,</strong> or <strong>trade balance,</strong> is a frequently cited component of the balance of payments on goods and services. The <strong>balance of payments on financial account,</strong> or <strong>financial account,</strong> measures capital flows. By definition, the balance of payments on current account plus the balance of payments on financial account is zero.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p360" block_type="sum-nl">Capital flows respond to international differences in interest rates and other rates of return; they can be usefully analyzed using an international version of the loanable funds model, which shows how a country where the interest rate would be low in the absence of capital flows sends funds to a country where the interest rate would be high in the absence of capital flows. The underlying determinants of capital flows are international differences in savings and opportunities for investment spending.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p361" block_type="sum-nl">Currencies are traded in the <strong>foreign exchange market;</strong> the prices at which they are traded are <strong>exchange rates.</strong> When a currency rises against another currency, it <strong>appreciates;</strong> when it falls, it <strong>depreciates.</strong> The <strong>equilibrium exchange rate</strong> matches the quantity of that currency supplied to the foreign exchange market to the quantity demanded.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p362" block_type="sum-nl">To correct for international differences in inflation rates, economists calculate <strong>real exchange rates,</strong> which multiply the exchange rate between two countries&#8217; currencies by the ratio of the countries&#8217; price levels. The current account responds only to changes in the real exchange rate, not the nominal exchange rate. <strong>Purchasing power parity</strong> is the exchange rate that makes the cost of a basket of goods and services equal in two countries. While purchasing power parity and the nominal exchange rate almost always differ, purchasing power parity is a good predictor of actual changes in the nominal exchange rate.</p></li>
</list>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-sec1-8" block_type="cr-kt-t" title="" chapter="20" numbered="true" level="1" print_page="605">
<section-metadata><section-title>KEY TERMS</section-title></section-metadata>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-exp2-7" block_type="mn2">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p363" block_type="fg1-t"><image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-img-48" alt="image" src="images/launchpad_logo_cmyk.jpg"/> &#124; interactive activity</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p364" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p20">Imports, p. 570</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p365" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p20">Exports, p. 570</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p366" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p24">Globalization, p. 570</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p367" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p24">Hyperglobalization, p. 570</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p368" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p34">Ricardian model of international trade, p. 571</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p369" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p38">Autarky, p. 572</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p370" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p74">Factor intensity, p. 576</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p371" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p76">Heckscher&#8211;Ohlin model, p. 577</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p372" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p105">Domestic demand curve, p. 579</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p373" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p107">Domestic supply curve, p. 579</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p374" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p110">World price, p. 580</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p375" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p129">Exporting industries, p. 583</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p376" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p129">Import-competing industries, p. 583</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p377" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p152">Free trade, p. 585</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p378" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p154">Trade protection (protection), p. 585</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p379" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p157">Tariff, p. 585</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p380" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p171">Import quota, p. 587</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p381" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p211">Balance of payments accounts, p. 589</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p382" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p211">Balance of payments on current account (current account), p. 591</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p383" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p211">Balance of payments on goods and services, p. 591</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p384" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p213">Merchandise trade balance (trade balance), p. 591</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p385" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p215">Balance of payments on financial account (financial account), p. 591</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p386" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p271">Foreign exchange market, p. 595</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p387" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p271">Exchange rates, p. 595</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p388" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p276">Appreciates, p. 596</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p389" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p276">Depreciates, p. 596</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p390" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p293">Equilibrium exchange rate, p. 597</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p391" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p304">Real exchange rate, p. 599</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p392" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p313">Purchasing power parity, p. 601</link></p>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-sec1-9" block_type="cr-que-t" title="" chapter="20" numbered="true" level="1" print_page="606">
<section-metadata><section-title>PROBLEMS</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_606" block_type="page_start">606</p>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-question-1" block_type="q_prob" number="1">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p393" block_type="cr-que-nl-mid"><phrase block_type="qnum">1.</phrase> Both Canada and the United States produce lumber and footballs with constant opportunity costs. The United States can produce either 10 tons of lumber and no footballs, or 1,000 footballs and no lumber, or any combination in between. Canada can produce either 8 tons of lumber and no footballs, or 400 footballs and no lumber, or any combination in between.</p>
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-list-22" type="ordered" block_type="loweralpha">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p394" block_type="cr-que-ans-first">Draw the U.S. and Canadian production possibility frontiers in two separate diagrams, with footballs on the horizontal axis and lumber on the vertical axis.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p395" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">In autarky, if the United States wants to consume 500 footballs, how much lumber can it consume at most? Label this point <em>A</em> in your diagram. Similarly, if Canada wants to consume 1 ton of lumber, how many footballs can it consume in autarky? Label this point <em>C</em> in your diagram.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p396" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">Which country has the absolute advantage in lumber production?</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p397" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">Which country has the comparative advantage in lumber production?</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p398" block_type="cr-que-txt">Suppose each country specializes in the good in which it has the comparative advantage, and there is trade.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p399" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">How many footballs does the United States produce? How much lumber does Canada produce?</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p400" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">Is it possible for the United States to consume 500 footballs and 7 tons of lumber? Label this point <em>B</em> in your diagram. Is it possible for Canada at the same time to consume 500 footballs and 1 ton of lumber? Label this point <em>D</em> in your diagram.</p></li>
</list>
</question>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-question-2" block_type="q_prob" number="2">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p401" block_type="cr-que-nl-mid"><phrase block_type="qnum">2.</phrase> For each of the following trade relationships, explain the likely source of the comparative advantage of each of the exporting countries.</p>
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-list-23" type="ordered" block_type="loweralpha">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p402" block_type="cr-que-ans-first">The United States exports software to Venezuela, and Venezuela exports oil to the United States.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p403" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">The United States exports airplanes to China, and China exports clothing to the United States.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p404" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">The United States exports wheat to Colombia, and Colombia exports coffee to the United States.</p></li>
</list>
</question>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-question-3" block_type="q_prob" number="3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p405" block_type="cr-que-nl-mid"><phrase block_type="qnum">3.</phrase> The U.S. Census Bureau keeps statistics on U.S. imports and exports on its website. The following steps will take you to the foreign trade statistics. Use them to answer the questions below.</p>
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-list-24" type="ordered" block_type="lowerroman">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p406" block_type="cr-que-ans2-first">Go to the U.S. Census Bureau&#8217;s website at <link href="http://www.census.gov">www.census.gov</link></p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p407" block_type="cr-que-ans2-mid">Under the heading &#8220;Topics&#8221; select &#8220;International Trade&#8221; and then select &#8220;Import Export Data&#8221;</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p408" block_type="cr-que-ans2-mid">In the left menu bar, select &#8220;Country/Product Trade&#8221;</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p409" block_type="cr-que-ans2-mid">Under the heading &#8220;North American Industry Classification System (NAICS)-Based,&#8221; select &#8220;NAICS web application&#8221;</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p410" block_type="cr-que-ans2-mid">In the drop-down menu &#8220;3-digit and 6-digit NAICS by country,&#8221; select the product category you are interested in, and hit &#8220;Go&#8221;</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p411" block_type="cr-que-ans2-mid">In the drop-down menu &#8220;Select 6-digit NAICS,&#8221; select the good or service you are interested in, and hit &#8220;Go&#8221;</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p412" block_type="cr-que-ans2-mid">In the drop-down menus that allow you to select a month and year, select &#8220;December&#8221; and &#8220;2013,&#8221; and hit &#8220;Go&#8221;</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p413" block_type="cr-que-ans2-mid">The right side of the table now shows the import and export statistics for the entire year 2013. For the questions below on U.S. imports, use the column for &#8220;Consumption Imports, Customs Value Basis.&#8221;</p></li>
</list>
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-list-25" type="ordered" block_type="loweralpha">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p414" block_type="cr-que-ans-first">Look up data for U.S. imports of hats and caps: in step (vi), select &#8220;(315) Apparel &#38; Accessories&#8221; and in step (vii), select &#8220;(315220) Men&#8217;s and Boys&#8217; Cut and Sew Apparel.&#8221; From which country do we import the most apparel? Which of the three sources of comparative advantage (climate, factor endowments, and technology) accounts for that country&#8217;s comparative advantage in apparel production?</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p415" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">Look up data for U.S. imports of grapes: in step (vi), select &#8220;(111) Agricultural Products&#8221; and in step (vii), select &#8220;(111332) Grapes.&#8221; From which country do we import the most grapes? Which of the three sources of comparative advantage (climate, factor endowments, and technology) accounts for that country&#8217;s comparative advantage in grape production?</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p416" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">Look up data for U.S. imports of food product machinery: in step (vi), select &#8220;(333) Machinery, Except Electrical&#8221; and in step (vii), select &#8220;333241 Food Product Machinery.&#8221; From which country do we import the most food product machinery? Which of the three sources of comparative advantage (climate, factor endowments, and technology) accounts for that country&#8217;s comparative advantage in food product machinery?</p></li>
</list>
</question>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-question-4" block_type="q_prob" number="4">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p417" block_type="cr-que-nl-mid"><phrase block_type="qnum">4.</phrase> Since 2000, the value of U.S. imports of men&#8217;s and boy&#8217;s apparel from China has more than tripled. What prediction does the Heckscher&#8211;Ohlin model make about the wages received by labor in China?</p>
</question>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-question-5" block_type="q_prob" number="5">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p418" block_type="cr-que-nl-mid"><phrase block_type="qnum">5.</phrase> Shoes are labor-intensive and satellites are capital-intensive to produce. The United States has abundant capital. China has abundant labor. According to the Heckscher&#8211;Ohlin model, which good will China export? Which good will the United States export? In the United States, what will happen to the price of labor (the wage) and to the price of capital?</p>
</question>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-question-6" block_type="q_prob" number="6">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p419" block_type="cr-que-nl-mid"><phrase block_type="qnum">6.</phrase> Before the North American Free Trade Agreement (NAFTA) gradually eliminated import tariffs on goods, the autarky price of tomatoes in Mexico was below the world price and in the United States was above the world price. Similarly, the autarky price of poultry in Mexico was above the world price and in the United States was below the world price. Draw diagrams with domestic supply and demand curves for each country and each of the two goods. As a result of NAFTA, the United States now imports tomatoes from Mexico and the United States now exports poultry to Mexico. How would you expect the following groups to be affected?</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_607" block_type="page_start">607</p>
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-list-26" type="ordered" block_type="loweralpha">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p420" block_type="cr-que-ans-first">Mexican and U.S. consumers of tomatoes. Illustrate the effect on consumer surplus in your diagram.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p421" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">Mexican and U.S. producers of tomatoes. Illustrate the effect on producer surplus in your diagram.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p422" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">Mexican and U.S. tomato workers.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p423" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">Mexican and U.S. consumers of poultry. Illustrate the effect on consumer surplus in your diagram.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p424" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">Mexican and U.S. producers of poultry. Illustrate the effect on producer surplus in your diagram.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p425" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">Mexican and U.S. poultry workers.</p></li>
</list>
</question>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-question-7" block_type="q_prob" number="7">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p426" block_type="cr-que-nl-mid"><phrase block_type="qnum">7.</phrase> The accompanying table indicates the U.S. domestic demand schedule and domestic supply schedule for commercial jet airplanes. Suppose that the world price of a commercial jet airplane is &#36;100 million.</p>
<table id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-untab-10" block_type="un_table" data-href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-untab-10" data-target="_pop">
<layout align="center" width="large"/>
<tbody>
<tr class="tbl-hdr-bg">
<td class="tbl-rborder"><strong>Price of jet<br/>(millions)</strong></td>
<td class="tbl-rborder"><strong>Quantity of jets<br/>demanded</strong> </td>
<td><strong>Quantity of jets<br/>supplied</strong></td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tbl-rborder">&#36;120</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder">100</td>
<td>1,000</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-dark">
<td class="tbl-rborder">110</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder">150</td>
<td>900</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tbl-rborder">100</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder">200</td>
<td>800</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-dark">
<td class="tbl-rborder">90</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder">250</td>
<td>700</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tbl-rborder">80</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder">300</td>
<td>600</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-dark">
<td class="tbl-rborder">70</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder">350</td>
<td>500</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tbl-rborder">60</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder">400</td>
<td>400</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-dark">
<td class="tbl-rborder">50</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder">450</td>
<td>300</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tbl-rborder">40</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder">500</td>
<td>200</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-list-27" type="ordered" block_type="loweralpha">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p427" block_type="cr-que-ans-first">In autarky, how many commercial jet airplanes does the United States produce, and at what price are they bought and sold?</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p428" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">With trade, what will the price for commercial jet airplanes be? Will the United States import or export airplanes? How many?</p></li>
</list>
</question>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-question-8" block_type="q_prob" number="8">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p429" block_type="cr-que-nl-mid"><phrase block_type="qnum">8.</phrase> The accompanying table shows the U.S. domestic demand schedule and domestic supply schedule for oranges. Suppose that the world price of oranges is &#36;0.30 per orange.</p>
<table id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-untab-11" block_type="un_table" data-href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-untab-11" data-target="_pop">
<layout align="center" width="large"/>
<tbody>
<tr class="tbl-hdr-bg">
<td class="tbl-rborder"><strong>Price of orange</strong></td>
<td class="tbl-rborder"><strong>Quantity of<br/> oranges demanded<br/> (thousands)</strong></td>
<td><strong>Quantity of<br/> oranges supplied<br/>(thousands)</strong></td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tbl-rborder">&#36;1.00</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder"> 2</td>
<td>11</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-dark">
<td class="tbl-rborder">0.90</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder"> 4</td>
<td>10</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tbl-rborder">0.80</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder"> 6</td>
<td>9</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-dark">
<td class="tbl-rborder">0.70</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder"> 8</td>
<td>8</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tbl-rborder">0.60</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder">10</td>
<td>7</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-dark">
<td class="tbl-rborder">0.50</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder">12</td>
<td>6</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tbl-rborder">0.40</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder">14</td>
<td>5</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-dark">
<td class="tbl-rborder">0.30</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder">16</td>
<td>4</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tbl-rborder">0.20</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder">18</td>
<td>3</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-list-28" type="ordered" block_type="loweralpha">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p430" block_type="cr-que-ans-first">Draw the U.S. domestic supply curve and domestic demand curve.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p431" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">With free trade, how many oranges will the United States import or export?</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p432" block_type="cr-que-txt">Suppose that the U.S. government imposes a tariff on oranges of &#36;0.20 per orange.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p433" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">How many oranges will the United States import or export after introduction of the tariff?</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p434" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">In your diagram, shade the gain or loss to the economy as a whole from the introduction of this tariff.</p></li>
</list>
</question>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-question-9" block_type="q_prob" number="9">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p435" block_type="cr-que-nl-mid"><phrase block_type="qnum">9.</phrase> How would the following transactions be categorized in the U.S. balance of payments accounts? Would they be entered in the current account (as a payment to or from a foreigner) or the financial account (as a sale of assets to or purchase of assets from a foreigner)? How will the balance of payments on the current and financial accounts change?</p>
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-list-29" type="ordered" block_type="loweralpha">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p436" block_type="cr-que-ans-first">A French importer buys a case of California wine for &#36;500.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p437" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">An American who works for a French company deposits her paycheck, drawn on a Paris bank, into her San Francisco bank.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p438" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">An American buys a bond from a Japanese company for &#36;10,000.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p439" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">An American charity sends &#36;100,000 to Africa to help local residents buy food after a harvest shortfall.</p></li>
</list>
</question>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-question-10" block_type="q_prob" number="10">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p440" block_type="cr-que-nl-mid"><phrase block_type="qnum">10.</phrase> The accompanying diagram shows foreign-owned assets in the United States and U.S.-owned assets abroad, both as a percentage of foreign GDP. As you can see from the diagram, both increased around fivefold from 1980 to 2013.</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-fig-32" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="right" width="medium" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-img-49" alt="image" src="images/KrugESS4e_20UN09.jpg"/>
<asset_source><em>Data from:</em> IMF; Bureau of Economic Analysis.</asset_source>
</figure>
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-list-30" type="ordered" block_type="loweralpha">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p441" block_type="cr-que-ans-first">As U.S.-owned assets abroad increased as a percentage of foreign GDP, does this mean that the United States, over the period, experienced net capital outflows?</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p442" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">Does this diagram indicate that world economies were more tightly linked in 2013 than they were in 1980?</p></li>
</list>
</question>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_608" block_type="page_start">608</p>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-question-11" block_type="q_prob" number="11">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p443" block_type="cr-que-nl-mid"><phrase block_type="qnum">11.</phrase> In the economy of Scottopia in 2014, exports equaled &#36;400 billion of goods and &#36;300 billion of services, imports equaled &#36;500 billion of goods and &#36;350 billion of services, and the rest of the world purchased &#36;250 billion of Scottopia&#8217;s assets. What was the merchandise trade balance for Scottopia? What was the balance of payments on current account in Scottopia? What was the balance of payments on financial account? What was the value of Scottopia&#8217;s purchases of assets from the rest of the world?</p>
</question>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-question-12" block_type="q_prob" number="12">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p444" block_type="cr-que-nl-mid"><phrase block_type="qnum">12.</phrase> In the economy of Popania in 2014, total Popanian purchases of assets in the rest of the world equaled &#36;300 billion, purchases of Popanian assets by the rest of the world equaled &#36;400 billion, and Popania exported goods and services equal to &#36;350 billion. What was Popania&#8217;s balance of payments on financial account in 2014? What was its balance of payments on current account? What was the value of its imports?</p>
</question>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-question-13" block_type="q_prob" number="13">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p445" block_type="cr-que-nl-mid"><phrase block_type="qnum">13.</phrase> Based on the exchange rates for the first trading days of 2013 and 2014 shown in the accompanying table, did the U.S. dollar appreciate or depreciate during 2014? Did the movement in the value of the U.S. dollar make American goods and services more or less attractive to foreigners?</p>
<table id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-untab-12" block_type="un_table" data-href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-untab-12" data-target="_pop">
<layout align="center" width="large"/>
<tbody>
<tr class="tbl-hdr-bg">
<td class="tbl-rborder"><strong>October 1, 2013</strong></td>
<td><strong>October 1, 2014</strong></td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tbl-rborder tbl-ljust">US&#36;1.62 to buy 1 British pound sterling</td>
<td class="tbl-ljust">US&#36;1.62 to buy 1 British pound sterling</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-dark">
<td class="tbl-rborder tbl-ljust">29.51 Taiwan dollars to buy US&#36;1</td>
<td class="tbl-ljust">30.43 Taiwan dollars to buy US&#36;1</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tbl-rborder tbl-ljust">US&#36;0.97 to buy 1 Canadian dollar</td>
<td class="tbl-ljust">US&#36;0.89 to buy 1 Canadian dollar</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-dark">
<td class="tbl-rborder tbl-ljust">98.04 Japanese yen to buy US&#36;1</td>
<td class="tbl-ljust">109.31 Japanese yen to buy US&#36;1</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tbl-rborder tbl-ljust">US&#36;1.35 to buy 1 euro</td>
<td class="tbl-ljust">US&#36;1.26 to buy 1 euro</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-dark">
<td class="tbl-rborder tbl-ljust">0.91 Swiss franc to buy US&#36;1</td>
<td class="tbl-ljust">0.96 Swiss franc to buy US&#36;1</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</question>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-question-14" block_type="q_prob" number="14">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p446" block_type="cr-que-nl-mid"><phrase block_type="qnum">14.</phrase> Go to <link href="http://fx.sauder.ubc.ca">http://fx.sauder.ubc.ca</link>. Using the table labeled &#8220;The Most Recent Cross-Rates of Major Currencies,&#8221; determine whether the British pound (GBP), the Canadian dollar (CAD), the Japanese yen (JPY), the euro (EUR), and the Swiss franc (CHF) have appreciated or depreciated against the U.S. dollar (USD) since October 1, 2014. The exchange rates on October 1, 2014, are listed in the table in Problem 13.</p>
</question>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-question-15" block_type="q_prob" number="15">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p447" block_type="cr-que-nl-mid"><phrase block_type="qnum">15.</phrase> In each of the following scenarios, suppose that the two nations are the only trading nations in the world. Given inflation and the change in the nominal exchange rate, which nation&#8217;s goods become more attractive?</p>
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-list-31" type="ordered" block_type="loweralpha">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p448" block_type="cr-que-ans-first">Inflation is 10&#37; in the United States and 5&#37; in Japan; the U.S. dollar&#8211;Japanese yen exchange rate remains the same.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p449" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">Inflation is 3&#37; in the United States and 8&#37; in Mexico; the price of the U.S. dollar falls from 12.50 to 10.25 Mexican pesos.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p450" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">Inflation is 5&#37; in the United States and 3&#37; in the euro area; the price of the euro falls from &#36;1.30 to &#36;1.20.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p451" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">Inflation is 8&#37; in the United States and 4&#37; in Canada; the price of the Canadian dollar rises from US&#36;0.60 to US&#36;0.75.</p></li>
</list>
</question>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-sec2-17" block_type="sum-h" title="" chapter="20" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="608">
<section-metadata><section-title>WORK IT OUT</section-title></section-metadata>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-exp2-8" block_type="mn2">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p452" block_type="fg1-t"><image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-img-50" alt="image" src="images/launchpad_logo_cmyk.jpg"/> &#124; interactive activity</p>
</box>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-question-16" block_type="q_prob" number="16">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p453" block_type="cr-wio-nl-first"><phrase block_type="qnum">16.</phrase> Assume Saudi Arabia and the United States face the production possibilities for oil and cars shown in the accompanying table.</p>
<table id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-untab-13" block_type="un_table" data-href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-untab-13" data-target="_pop">
<layout align="center" width="large"/>
<tbody>
<tr class="tbl-hdr-bg">
<td colspan="2" class="tbl-bborder"><strong>Saudi Arabia</strong></td>
<td></td>
<td colspan="2"><strong>United States</strong></td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-hdr-bg">
<td><strong>Quantity of oil<br/> (millions of barrels)</strong></td>
<td class="tbl-rborder"><strong>Quantity of<br/> cars (millions)</strong></td>
<td><strong>Quantity of oil<br/> (millions of barrels)</strong></td>
<td><strong>Quantity of cars (millions)</strong></td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tbl-rborder">0</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder">4</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder">0</td>
<td>10.0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-dark">
<td class="tbl-rborder">200</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder">3</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder">100</td>
<td>7.5</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tbl-rborder">400</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder">2</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder">200</td>
<td>5.0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-dark">
<td class="tbl-rborder">600</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder">1</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder">300</td>
<td>2.5</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tbl-rborder">800</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder">0</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder">400</td>
<td>0</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-list-32" type="ordered" block_type="loweralpha">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p454" block_type="cr-wio-ans-first">What is the opportunity cost of producing a car in Saudi Arabia? In the United States? What is the opportunity cost of producing a barrel of oil in Saudi Arabia? In the United States?</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p455" block_type="cr-wio-ans-mid">Which country has the comparative advantage in producing oil? In producing cars?</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p456" block_type="cr-wio-ans-mid">Suppose that in autarky, Saudi Arabia produces 200 million barrels of oil and 3 million cars; similarly, that the United States produces 300 million barrels of oil and 2.5 million cars. Without trade, can Saudi Arabia produce more oil <em>and</em> more cars? Without trade, can the United States produce more oil <em>and</em> more cars?</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p457" block_type="cr-wio-ans-mid">Suppose now that each country specializes in the good in which it has the comparative advantage, and the two countries trade. Also assume that for each country the value of imports must equal the value of exports.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_609" block_type="page_start">609</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p458" block_type="cr-wio-ans-mid">What is the total quantity of oil produced? What is the total quantity of cars produced?</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p459" block_type="cr-wio-ans-mid">Is it possible for Saudi Arabia to consume 400 million barrels of oil and 5 million cars and for the United States to consume 400 million barrels of oil and 5 million cars?</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p460" block_type="cr-wio-ans-last">Suppose that, in fact, Saudi Arabia consumes 300 million barrels of oil and 4 million cars and the United States consumes 500 million barrels of oil and 6 million cars. How many barrels of oil does the United States import? How many cars does the United States export? Suppose a car costs &#36;10,000 on the world market. How much, then, does a barrel of oil cost on the world market?</p></li>
</list>
</question>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-question-17" block_type="q_prob" number="17">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p461" block_type="cr-wio-nl-first"><phrase block_type="qnum">17.</phrase> Suppose the United States and Japan are the only two trading countries in the world. What will happen to the value of the U.S. dollar if the following occur, other things equal?</p>
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-list-33" type="ordered" block_type="loweralpha">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p462" block_type="cr-wio-ans-first">Japan relaxes some of its import restrictions.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p463" block_type="cr-wio-ans-mid">The United States imposes some import tariffs on Japanese goods.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p464" block_type="cr-wio-ans-mid">Interest rates in the United States rise dramatically.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p465" block_type="cr-wio-ans-last">A report indicates that Japanese cars last much longer than previously thought, especially compared with American cars.</p></li>
</list>
</question>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-sec1-7a" block_type="business_case" title="" chapter="20" numbered="true" level="1" print_page="610">
<section-metadata><section-title>Business Case</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_610" block_type="page_start">610</p>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-bx5-6" block_type="bcbx5-h">
<box-metadata><box-title><image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-img-51" alt="image" src="images/world_view_icon.jpg"/> <phrase block_type="bc1">BUSINESS</phrase> <phrase block_type="bc2">CASE</phrase><strong>Li &#38; Fung: From Guangzhou to You</strong></box-title></box-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p467" block_type="bx5-txt-ni"><phrase block_type="dropcap">I</phrase>t&#8217;s a very good bet that as you read this, you&#8217;re wearing something manufactured in Asia. And if you are, it&#8217;s also a good bet that the Hong Kong company Li &#38; Fung was involved in getting your garment designed, produced, and shipped to your local store. From Levi&#8217;s to The Limited to Walmart, Li &#38; Fung is a critical conduit from factories around the world to the shopping mall nearest you.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p468" block_type="bx5-txt">The company was founded in 1906 in Guangzhou, China. According to Victor Fung, the company&#8217;s chairman, his grandfather&#8217;s &#8220;value added&#8221; was that he spoke English, allowing him to serve as an interpreter in business deals between Chinese and foreigners. When Mao&#8217;s Communist Party seized control in mainland China, the company moved to Hong Kong. There, as Hong Kong&#8217;s market economy took off during the 1960s and 1970s, Li &#38; Fung grew as an export broker, bringing together Hong Kong manufacturers and foreign buyers.</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-fig-33" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="right" width="medium" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-img-52" alt="image" src="images/KrugESS4e_20UN10.jpg"/>
<asset_source>Jerome Favre/Bloomberg via Getty Images</asset_source>
</figure>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p469" block_type="bx5-txt">The real transformation of the company came, however, as Asian economies grew and changed. Hong Kong&#8217;s rapid growth led to rising wages, making Li &#38; Fung increasingly uncompetitive in garments, its main business. So the company reinvented itself: rather than being a simple broker, it became a &#8220;supply chain manager.&#8221; Not only would it allocate production of a good to a manufacturer, it would also break production down, allocate production of the inputs, and then allocate final assembly of the good among its 12,000&#43; suppliers around the globe. Sometimes production would be done in sophisticated economies like those of Hong Kong or even Japan, where wages are high but so is quality and productivity; sometimes it would be done in less advanced locations like mainland China or Thailand, where labor is less productive but cheaper.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p470" block_type="bx5-txt">For example, suppose you own a U.S. retail chain and want to sell garment-washed blue jeans. Rather than simply arrange for production Li &#38; Fung will work with you on their design, providing you with the latest production and style information, like what materials and colors are hot. After the design has been finalized, Li &#38; Fung will arrange for the creation of a prototype, find the most cost-effective way to manufacture it, and then place an order on your behalf. Through Li &#38; Fung, the yarn might be made in Korea and dyed in Taiwan, and the jeans sewn in Thailand or mainland China. And because production is taking place in so many locations, Li &#38; Fung provides transport logistics as well as quality control.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p471" block_type="bx5-txt">Li &#38; Fung has been enormously successful. In 2015 the company had a market value of approximately &#36;5 billion and business turnover of over &#36;17 billion, with offices and distribution centers in more than 40 countries. Year after year, it has regularly doubled or tripled its profits.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p472" block_type="bx5-nl-h"><strong>QUESTIONS FOR THOUGHT</strong></p>
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-list-34" type="ordered" block_type="numbered">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p473" block_type="bx5-nl">Why do you think it was profitable for Li &#38; Fung to go beyond brokering exports to becoming a supply chain manager, breaking down the production process and sourcing the inputs from various suppliers across many countries?</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p474" block_type="bx5-nl">What principle do you think underlies Li &#38; Fung&#8217;s decisions on how to allocate production of a good&#8217;s inputs and its final assembly among various countries?</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p475" block_type="bx5-nl">Why do you think a retailer prefers to have Li &#38; Fung arrange international production of its jeans rather than purchase them directly from a jeans manufacturer in mainland China?</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch20-p476" block_type="bx5-nl">What is the source of Li &#38; Fung&#8217;s success? Is it based on human capital, on ownership of a natural resource, or on ownership of capital?</p></li>
</list>
</box>
</section>
</chapter>
</manuscript>
