<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<manuscript xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" manuscript-id="16" name="" title="KRU_Chapter_16_DJHrev" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="../xsd/digfir_manuscript.xsd">
<chapter number="16" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-chapter-16" title="CHAPTER 16: Aggregate Demand and Aggregate Supply" start-numbering-at="16" numbered="true">
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-sec1-1a" block_type="intro" title="Chapter Introduction" numbered="true" level="1" print_page="439">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p1" block_type="chapter_title">Aggregate Demand and Aggregate Supply</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p2" block_type="chapter_number"><phrase block_type="chap">CHAPTER</phrase> <phrase block_type="chapnum">16</phrase></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_439" block_type="page_start">439</p>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-bx3-1" block_type="bx3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p3" block_type="co-t"> <strong>WHAT KIND OF SHOCK?</strong></p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-fig-1" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-img-1" alt="image" src="images/KrugESS4e_CO16.jpg"/>
<caption> The Federal Open Market Committee, which decides whether to pump cash into the economy to fight unemployment or pull cash out of the economy to fight inflation, got its priorities wrong in 2008.</caption>
<asset_source>United States government work</asset_source>
</figure>
</box>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-exp1-1" block_type="mn1">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p4" block_type="obj-h"><strong>What You Will Learn in This Chapter</strong></p>
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-list-1" type="unordered" block_type="greensquare">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p5" block_type="obj-bl">How the <strong>aggregate demand curve</strong> illustrates the relationship between the aggregate price level and the quantity of aggregate output demanded in the economy</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p6" block_type="obj-bl">How the <strong>aggregate supply curve</strong> illustrates the relationship between the aggregate price level and the quantity of aggregate output supplied in the economy</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p7" block_type="obj-bl">Why the aggregate supply curve is different in the short run compared to the long run</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p8" block_type="obj-bl">How the <strong><em>AD&#8211;AS</em> model</strong> is used to analyze economic fluctuations</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p9" block_type="obj-bl">How monetary policy and fiscal policy can stabilize the economy</p></li>
</list>
</box>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-exp2-1" block_type="mn2">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p10" block_type="fg1-t"><image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-img-2" alt="image" src="images/learningcurve_logo_cmyk.jpg"/> &#124; interactive activity</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p11" block_type="co-txt-ni"><phrase block_type="dropcap">T</phrase>HE FEDERAL OPEN MARKET Committee, or FOMC, is the branch of the Federal Reserve System that sets U.S. monetary policy and arguably has much more power over the economy than anyone else&#8212;including the president. It held one of its regular meetings on September 16, 2008. That was, it turned out, a very important day. Simmering problems in the financial industry had just boiled over with the failure of the investment bank Lehman Brothers, and the U.S. economy, already in recession, was about to go into free fall. Not surprisingly, the officials around the table were worried.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p12" block_type="co-txt">But many committee members, it turns out, were worried about the wrong thing. When the committee released transcripts of its 2008 meetings&#8212;which it didn&#8217;t do until 2014&#8212;we learned that during the summer of 2008 most of the people around the table were much more worried about inflation than they were about the financial crisis or the prospect of a sharp rise in unemployment from a crisis-caused recession&#8212;an attitude that persisted into September. In the June and August 2008 meetings the word <em>inflation</em> came up more than ten times as often as the word <em>unemployment.</em> Even in that fateful September meeting, inflation mentions outnumbered unemployment mentions five to one. </p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p13" block_type="co-txt">Later events showed that this was a case of misplaced priorities, with important consequences. Why? Because the appropriate policy responses to soaring unemployment, on one side, and soaring inflation, on the other, are more or less opposite. If unemployment is the main problem, the Fed should be cutting interest rates in an attempt to boost spending; if inflation is the main problem, the Fed should be raising rates to cool things off.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p14" block_type="co-txt">By focusing on inflation, which turned out not to be a problem at all during the fall and summer of 2008, as opposed to unemployment, which was about to skyrocket, the committee was looking for trouble in all the wrong places. </p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p15" block_type="co-txt">How could the committee have had its priorities so wrong? Well, we know now that the big shock hitting the economy in 2008 was the financial crisis, which in turn led to plunging spending by businesses and consumers. For much of that year, however, the eyes of the Federal Reserve and, to be fair, many other observers were instead focused on a different shock: the soaring price of oil, which had jumped from &#36;60 a barrel in the summer of 2007 to a peak of &#36;145 a barrel in July 2008. And many members of the committee worried more about the effects of oil prices than they did about the gathering financial storm.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p16" block_type="co-txt">As we&#8217;ve just suggested, financial crises and soaring oil prices can both create devastating economic problems&#8212;but the problems they create are very different, and so is the appropriate policy response. A financial crisis hurts the economy by reducing spending&#8212;it&#8217;s a <em>demand shock,</em> which raises unemployment while cutting inflation and possibly even leading to <em>deflation,</em> as it did during the worst slump in history, the economy&#8217;s plunge from 1929 to 1933. And the appropriate policy in response to such a shock involves propping up spending, among other things by cutting interest rates.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p17" block_type="co-txt">A surge in the price of oil, however, does much of its damage by raising costs and discouraging production; it&#8217;s a <em>supply shock.</em> Like negative demand shocks, adverse supply shocks cause the economy to shrink and unemployment to rise. But they also cause inflation&#8212;specifically, they cause the unpleasant combination of high inflation and high unemployment known as <em>stagflation,</em> which afflicted the U.S. economy during much of the 1970s (largely thanks to two spikes in the price of oil, in 1973 and again in 1979). And responding to stagflation is tricky: you might want to cut interest rates to defend employment, but on the other hand you might want to raise interest rates to fight inflation.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_440" block_type="page_start">440</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p18" block_type="co-txt">In the end, what the FOMC did in response to these conflicting stories about what ailed the economy was . . . nothing. It kept interest rates unchanged all through the summer and left them unchanged in September of 2008. Within a few weeks it became clear that demand, not supply, was the serious concern, at which point the Fed began a frantic effort to pull the economy out of its accelerating tailspin. But the perplexity of the Fed in 2008 tells us that such decisions aren&#8217;t always easy to understand.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p19" block_type="co-txt">We should mention, that the Fed&#8217;s policy response to the financial crisis was, in the end, a partial success at best. With the Fed&#8217;s help the economy did stabilize over the course of 2009, but the subsequent recovery was painfully slow. Even if the Fed had realized the true danger sooner, the economy probably would have still suffered a lot of damage. But its confusion in 2008 certainly didn&#8217;t help.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p20" block_type="co-txt">In this chapter, we&#8217;ll develop a model that shows us how to distinguish between different types of short-run economic fluctuations.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p21" block_type="co-txt">To develop this model, we&#8217;ll proceed in three steps. First, we&#8217;ll develop the concept of <em>aggregate demand.</em> Then we&#8217;ll turn to the parallel concept of <em>aggregate supply.</em> Finally, we&#8217;ll put them together in the <em>AD&#8211;AS model.</em></p>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-sec1-001" block_type="h1" title="" chapter="ch16" numbered="true" level="1" print_page="440">
<section-metadata><section-title>Aggregate Demand</section-title></section-metadata>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-exp3-1" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p22" block_type="mn-gl-def">The <strong>aggregate demand curve</strong> shows the relationship between the aggregate price level and the quantity of aggregate output demanded by households, businesses, the government, and the rest of the world.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p23" block_type="txt-ni">The Great Depression, the great majority of economists agree, was the result of a massive negative demand shock. What does that mean? In <link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch03.xml">Chapter 3</link> we explained that when economists talk about a fall in the demand for a particular good or service, they&#8217;re referring to a leftward shift of the demand curve. Similarly, when economists talk about a negative demand shock to the economy as a whole, they&#8217;re referring to a leftward shift of the <strong>aggregate demand curve,</strong> a curve that shows the relationship between the aggregate price level and the quantity of aggregate output demanded by households, firms, the government, and the rest of the world.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p24" block_type="txt"><link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16.xml#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-fig-2">Figure 16-1</link> shows what the aggregate demand curve may have looked like in 1933, at the end of the 1929&#8211;1933 recession. The horizontal axis shows the total quantity of domestic goods and services demanded, measured in 2009 dollars. We use real GDP to measure aggregate output and will often use the two terms interchangeably. The vertical axis shows the aggregate price level, measured by the GDP deflator. With these variables on the axes, we can draw a curve, <em>AD,</em> showing how much aggregate output would have been demanded at any given aggregate price level. Since <em>AD</em> is meant to illustrate aggregate demand in 1933, one point on the curve corresponds to actual data for 1933, when the aggregate price level was 7.3 and the total quantity of domestic final goods and services purchased was &#36;778 billion in 2009 dollars.</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-fig-2" block_type="figure" numbered="true" number="16-1" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="medium" border="true"/>
<caption><link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16.xml#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-fig-2"><phrase block_type="fig-label"><phrase block_type="fig"><strong>FIGURE</strong></phrase></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_num"><strong>16-1</strong></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_title">The Aggregate Demand Curve</phrase></link></caption>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-img-3" alt="image" src="images/KrugESS4e_fig_16_01.jpg"/>
<caption>The aggregate demand curve shows the relationship between the aggregate price level and the quantity of aggregate output demanded. The curve is downward sloping due to the wealth effect of a change in the aggregate price level and the interest rate effect of a change in the aggregate price level. Corresponding to the actual 1933 data, here the total quantity of goods and services demanded at an aggregate price level of 7.3 is &#36;778 billion in 2009 dollars. According to our hypothetical curve, however, if the aggregate price level had been only 4.2, the quantity of aggregate output demanded would have risen to &#36;1,000 billion.</caption>
</figure>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_441" block_type="page_start">441</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p25" block_type="txt">As drawn in <link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16.xml#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-fig-2">Figure 16-1</link>, the aggregate demand curve is downward sloping, indicating a negative relationship between the aggregate price level and the quantity of aggregate output demanded. A higher aggregate price level, other things equal, reduces the quantity of aggregate output demanded; a lower aggregate price level, other things equal, increases the quantity of aggregate output demanded. According to <link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16.xml#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-fig-2">Figure 16-1</link>, if the price level in 1933 had been 4.2 instead of 7.3, the total quantity of domestic final goods and services demanded would have been &#36;1,000 billion in 2009 dollars instead of &#36;778 billion.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p26" block_type="txt">The first key question about the aggregate demand curve is: why should the curve be downward sloping?</p>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-sec2-001" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="ch16" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="441">
<section-metadata><section-title>Why Is the Aggregate Demand Curve Downward Sloping?</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p27" block_type="txt-ni">In <link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16.xml#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-fig-2">Figure 16-1</link>, the curve <em>AD</em> is downward sloping. To understand why, you&#8217;ll need to learn the basic equation of national income accounting:</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p28" block_type="eq"><strong>(16-1)</strong> GDP = <em>C</em> &#43; <em>I</em> &#43; <em>G</em> &#43; <em>X</em> &#8722; <em>IM</em></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p29" block_type="txt-ni">where <em>C</em> is consumer spending, <em>I</em> is investment spending, <em>G</em> is government purchases of goods and services, <em>X</em> is exports to other countries, and <em>IM</em> is imports. If we measure these variables in constant dollars&#8212;that is, in prices of a base year&#8212;then <em>C</em> &#43; <em>I</em> &#43; <em>G</em> &#43; <em>X</em> &#8722; <em>IM</em> is the quantity of domestically produced final goods and services demanded during a given period. <em>G</em> is decided by the government, but the other variables are private-sector decisions. To understand why the aggregate demand curve slopes downward, we need to understand why a rise in the aggregate price level reduces <em>C, I,</em> and <em>X</em> &#8722; <em>IM.</em></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p30" block_type="txt">You might think that the downward slope of the aggregate demand curve is a natural consequence of the <em>law of demand</em> we defined back in <link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch03.xml">Chapter 3</link>. That is, since the demand curve for any one good is downward sloping, isn&#8217;t it natural that the demand curve for aggregate output is also downward sloping? This turns out, however, to be a misleading parallel. The demand curve for any individual good shows how the quantity demanded depends on the price of that good, <em>holding the prices of other goods and services constant.</em> The main reason the quantity of a good demanded falls when the price of that good rises&#8212;that is, the quantity of a good demanded falls as we move up the demand curve&#8212;is that people switch their consumption to other goods and services.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p31" block_type="txt">But when we consider movements up or down the aggregate demand curve, we&#8217;re considering <em>a simultaneous change in the prices of all final goods and services.</em> Furthermore, changes in the composition of goods and services in consumer spending aren&#8217;t relevant to the aggregate demand curve: if consumers decide to buy fewer clothes but more cars, this doesn&#8217;t necessarily change the total quantity of final goods and services they demand.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p32" block_type="txt">Why, then, does a rise in the aggregate price level lead to a fall in the quantity of all domestically produced final goods and services demanded? There are two main reasons: the <em>wealth effect</em> and the <em>interest rate effect</em> of a change in the aggregate price level.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p33" block_type="txt-3"><phrase block_type="h3"><strong>The Wealth Effect</strong></phrase> An increase in the aggregate price level, other things equal, reduces the purchasing power of many assets. Consider, for example, someone who has &#36;5,000 in a bank account. If the aggregate price level were to rise by 25&#37;, what used to cost &#36;5,000 would now cost &#36;6,250, and would no longer be affordable. And what used to cost &#36;4,000 would now cost &#36;5,000, so that the &#36;5,000 in the bank account would now buy only as much as &#36;4,000 would have bought previously. With the loss in purchasing power, the owner of that bank account would probably scale back his or her consumption plans. Millions of other people would respond the same way, leading to a fall in spending on final goods and services, because a rise in the aggregate price level reduces the purchasing power of everyone&#8217;s bank account.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_442" block_type="page_start">442</p>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-exp3-2" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p34" block_type="mn-gl-def">The <strong>wealth effect of a change in the aggregate price level</strong> is the effect on consumer spending caused by the effect of a change in the aggregate price level on the purchasing power of consumers&#8217; assets.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p35" block_type="txt">Correspondingly, a fall in the aggregate price level increases the purchasing power of consumers&#8217; assets and leads to more consumer demand. The <strong>wealth effect of a change in the aggregate price level</strong> is the effect on consumer spending caused by the effect of a change in the aggregate price level on the purchasing power of consumers&#8217; assets. Because of the wealth effect, consumer spending, <em>C,</em> falls when the aggregate price level rises, leading to a downward-sloping aggregate demand curve.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p36" block_type="txt-3"><phrase block_type="h3"><strong>The Interest Rate Effect</strong></phrase> Economists use the term <em>money</em> in its narrowest sense to refer to cash and bank deposits on which people can write checks. People and firms hold money because it reduces the cost and inconvenience of making transactions. An increase in the aggregate price level, other things equal, reduces the purchasing power of a given amount of money holdings. To purchase the same basket of goods and services as before, people and firms now need to hold more money. So, in response to an increase in the aggregate price level, the public tries to increase its money holdings, either by borrowing more or by selling assets such as bonds. This reduces the funds available for lending to other borrowers and drives interest rates up.</p>
<box title="PITFALLS" numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-bx1-1" block_type="bx-1-h">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p37" block_type="bx1-t"><strong>CHANGES IN WEALTH: A MOVEMENT ALONG VERSUS A SHIFT OF THE AGGREGATE DEMAND CURVE</strong></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p38" block_type="bx1-txt-ni">Earlier we explained that one reason the <em>AD</em> curve is downward sloping is the wealth effect of a change in the aggregate price level: a higher aggregate price level reduces the purchasing power of households&#8217; assets and leads to a fall in consumer spending, <em>C.</em> But we&#8217;ve just explained that changes in wealth lead to a shift of the <em>AD</em> curve. Aren&#8217;t those two explanations contradictory? Which one is it&#8212;does a change in wealth move the economy along the <em>AD</em> curve or does it shift the <em>AD</em> curve? The answer is both: it depends on the <em>source</em> of the change in wealth.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p39" block_type="bx1-txt">A movement along the <em>AD</em> curve occurs when a change in the aggregate price level changes the purchasing power of consumers&#8217; existing wealth (the real value of their assets). This is the <em>wealth effect of a change in the aggregate price level&#8212;</em>a change in the aggregate price level is the source of the change in wealth. For example, a fall in the aggregate price level increases the purchasing power of consumers&#8217; assets and leads to a movement down the <em>AD</em> curve.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p40" block_type="bx1-txt">In contrast, a change in wealth <em>independent of a change in the aggregate price level</em> shifts the <em>AD</em> curve. So, a rise in the stock market or in real estate values leads to an increase in the real value of consumers&#8217; assets at any given aggregate price level. In this case, the source of the change in wealth is a change in the values of assets without any change in the aggregate price level&#8212;that is, a change in asset values holding the prices of all final goods and services constant.</p>
</box>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-exp3-3" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p41" block_type="mn-gl-def">The <strong>interest rate effect of a change in the aggregate price level</strong> is the effect on consumer spending and investment spending caused by the effect of a change in the aggregate price level on the purchasing power of consumers&#8217; and firms&#8217; money holdings.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p42" block_type="txt">A rise in the interest rate reduces investment spending because it makes the cost of borrowing higher. It also reduces consumer spending because households save more of their disposable income. So a rise in the aggregate price level depresses investment spending, <em>I,</em> and consumer spending, <em>C,</em> through its effect on the purchasing power of money holdings, an effect known as the <strong>interest rate effect of a change in the aggregate price level.</strong> This also leads to a downward-sloping aggregate demand curve.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p43" block_type="txt">We&#8217;ll have a lot more to say about money and interest rates in <link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch19.xml">Chapter 19</link> on monetary policy. For now, the important point is that the aggregate demand curve is downward sloping due to both the wealth effect and the interest rate effect of a change in the aggregate price level.</p>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-sec2-002" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="ch16" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="442">
<section-metadata><section-title>Shifts of the Aggregate Demand Curve</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p44" block_type="txt-ni">In <link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch03.xml">Chapter 3</link>, where we introduced the analysis of supply and demand in the market for an individual good, we stressed the importance of the distinction between <em>movements along</em> the demand curve and <em>shifts of</em> the demand curve. The same distinction applies to the aggregate demand curve. <link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16.xml#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-fig-2">Figure 16-1</link> shows a <em>movement along</em> the aggregate demand curve, a change in the aggregate quantity of goods and services demanded as the aggregate price level changes.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p45" block_type="txt">But there can also be <em>shifts of</em> the aggregate demand curve, changes in the quantity of goods and services demanded at any given price level, as shown in <link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16.xml#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-fig-3">Figure 16-2</link>. When we talk about an increase in aggregate demand, we mean a shift of the aggregate demand curve to the right, as shown in panel (a) by the shift from <em>AD</em><sub>1</sub> to <em>AD</em><sub>2</sub>. A rightward shift occurs when the quantity of aggregate output demanded increases at any given aggregate price level. A decrease in aggregate demand means that the <em>AD</em> curve shifts to the left, as in panel (b). A leftward shift implies that the quantity of aggregate output demanded falls at any given aggregate price level.</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-fig-3" block_type="figure" numbered="true" number="16-2" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="medium" border="true"/>
<caption><link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16.xml#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-fig-3"><phrase block_type="fig-label"><phrase block_type="fig"><strong>FIGURE</strong></phrase></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_num"><strong>16-2</strong></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_title">Shifts of the Aggregate Demand Curve</phrase></link></caption>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-img-4" alt="image" src="images/KrugESS4e_fig_16_02ab.jpg"/>
<caption>Panel (a) shows the effect of events that increase the quantity of aggregate output demanded at any given aggregate price level, such as improvements in business and consumer expectations or increased government spending. Such changes shift the aggregate demand curve to the right, from <em>AD</em><sub>1</sub> to <em>AD</em><sub>2</sub>. Panel (b) shows the effect of events that decrease the quantity of aggregate output demanded at any given aggregate price level, such as a fall in wealth caused by a stock market decline. This shifts the aggregate demand curve leftward from <em>AD</em><sub>1</sub> to <em>AD</em><sub>2</sub>.</caption>
</figure>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_443" block_type="page_start">443</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p46" block_type="txt">A number of factors can shift the aggregate demand curve. Among the most important are changes in expectations, changes in wealth, and the size of the existing stock of physical capital. In addition, both fiscal and monetary policy can shift the aggregate demand curve. We&#8217;ll now examine each of the factors that shift the aggregate demand curve. For an overview of them, see <link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16.xml#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-tab-1">Table 16-1</link>.</p>
<table id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-tab-1" block_type="table" numbered="false" caption-placement="Top" data-href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-tab-1" data-target="_pop">
<table_caption><strong><phrase block_type="tbl">TABLE</phrase> <phrase block_type="tbl_num">16-1</phrase></strong> <phrase block_type="tbl_title">Factors That Shift Aggregate Demand</phrase></table_caption>
<tbody>
<tr class="tbl-hdr-bg">
<td class="tbl-ljust"><strong>When this<br/>happens, . . .</strong></td>
<td><strong>. . . aggregate<br/>demand increases:</strong></td>
<td class="tbl-ljust"><strong>But when this<br/>happens, . . .</strong></td>
<td><strong>. . . aggregate<br/>demand decreases:</strong></td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-hdr-bg">
<td colspan="4" class="tbl-ljust"><strong>Changes in expectations:</strong></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="2" class="tbl-td-light">
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-img-11" alt="image" src="images/KrugESS4e_T_16_01a.jpg"/></td>
<td colspan="2" class="tbl-td-dark">
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-img-12" alt="image" src="images/KrugESS4e_T_16_01f.jpg"/></td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-hdr-bg">
<td colspan="4" class="tbl-ljust"><strong>Changes in wealth:</strong></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="2" class="tbl-td-light">
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-img-11" alt="image" src="images/KrugESS4e_T_16_01b.jpg"/></td>
<td colspan="2" class="tbl-td-dark">
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-img-12" alt="image" src="images/KrugESS4e_T_16_01g.jpg"/></td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-hdr-bg">
<td colspan="4" class="tbl-ljust"><strong>Size of the existing stock of physical capital:</strong></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="2" class="tbl-td-light">
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-img-13" alt="image" src="images/KrugESS4e_T_16_01c.jpg"/></td>
<td colspan="2" class="tbl-td-dark">
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-img-14" alt="image" src="images/KrugESS4e_T_16_01h.jpg"/></td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-hdr-bg">
<td colspan="4" class="tbl-ljust"><strong>Fiscal policy:</strong></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="2" class="tbl-td-light">
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-img-15" alt="image" src="images/KrugESS4e_T_16_01d.jpg"/></td>
<td colspan="2" class="tbl-td-dark">
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-img-16" alt="image" src="images/KrugESS4e_T_16_01i.jpg"/></td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-hdr-bg">
<td colspan="4" class="tbl-ljust"><strong>Monetary policy:</strong></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="2" class="tbl-td-light">
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-img-11" alt="image" src="images/KrugESS4e_T_16_01e.jpg"/></td>
<td colspan="2" class="tbl-td-dark">
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-img-12" alt="image" src="images/KrugESS4e_T_16_01j.jpg"/></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p47" block_type="txt-3"><phrase block_type="h3"><strong>Changes in Expectations</strong></phrase> Both consumer spending and planned investment spending depend in part on people&#8217;s expectations about the future. Consumers base their spending not only on the income they have now but also on the income they expect to have in the future. Firms base their planned investment spending not only on current conditions but also on the sales they expect to make in the future. As a result, changes in expectations can push consumer spending and planned investment spending up or down. If consumers and firms become more optimistic, aggregate spending rises; if they become more pessimistic, aggregate spending falls.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p48" block_type="txt">In fact, short-run economic forecasters pay careful attention to surveys of consumer and business sentiment. In particular, forecasters watch the Consumer Confidence Index, a monthly measure calculated by the Conference Board, and the Michigan Consumer Sentiment Index, a similar measure calculated by the University of Michigan.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p49" block_type="txt-3"><phrase block_type="h3"><strong>Changes in Wealth</strong></phrase> Consumer spending depends in part on the value of household assets. When the real value of these assets rises, the purchasing power they embody also rises, leading to an increase in aggregate spending. For example, in the 1990s there was a significant rise in the stock market that increased aggregate demand. And when the real value of household assets falls&#8212;for example, because of a stock market crash&#8212;the purchasing power they embody is reduced and aggregate demand also falls. The stock market crash of 1929 was a significant factor leading to the Great Depression. Similarly, a sharp decline in real estate values was a major factor depressing consumer spending during the 2007&#8211;2009 recession.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_444" block_type="page_start">444</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p50" block_type="txt-3"><phrase block_type="h3"><strong>Size of the Existing Stock of Physical Capital</strong></phrase> Firms engage in planned investment spending to add to their stock of physical capital. Their incentive to spend depends in part on how much physical capital they already have: the more they have, the less they will feel a need to add more, other things equal. The same applies to other types of investment spending&#8212;for example, if a large number of houses have been built in recent years, this will depress the demand for new houses and as a result also tend to reduce residential investment spending. In fact, that&#8217;s part of the reason for the deep slump in residential investment spending that began in 2006. The housing boom of the previous few years had created an oversupply of houses: by spring 2009, the inventory of unsold houses on the market was equal to more than 14 months of sales, and prices of new homes had fallen more than 25&#37; from their peak. This gave the construction industry little incentive to build even more homes.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_445" block_type="page_start">445</p>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-sec2-003" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="ch16" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="445">
<section-metadata><section-title>Government Policies and Aggregate Demand</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p51" block_type="txt-ni">One of the key insights of macroeconomics is that the government can have a powerful influence on aggregate demand and that, in some circumstances, this influence can be used to improve economic performance.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p52" block_type="txt">The two main ways the government can influence the aggregate demand curve are through fiscal policy and monetary policy. We&#8217;ll briefly discuss their influence on aggregate demand, leaving a full-length discussion for upcoming chapters.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p53" block_type="txt-3"><phrase block_type="h3"><strong>Fiscal Policy</strong></phrase> As we learned, fiscal policy is the use of either government spending&#8212;government purchases of final goods and services and government transfers&#8212;or tax policy to stabilize the economy. In practice, governments often respond to recessions by increasing spending, cutting taxes, or both. They often respond to inflation by reducing spending or increasing taxes.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p54" block_type="txt">The effect of government purchases of final goods and services, <em>G,</em> on the aggregate demand curve is <em>direct</em> because government purchases are themselves a component of aggregate demand. So an increase in government purchases shifts the aggregate demand curve to the right and a decrease shifts it to the left. History&#8217;s most dramatic example of how increased government purchases affect aggregate demand was the effect of wartime government spending during World War II.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p55" block_type="txt">Because of the war, U.S. federal purchases surged 400&#37;. This increase in purchases is usually credited with ending the Great Depression. In the 1990s Japan used large public works projects&#8212;such as government-financed construction of roads, bridges, and dams&#8212;in an effort to increase aggregate demand in the face of a slumping economy. Similarly, in 2009, in the wake of the Great Recession, the United States began spending more than &#36;100 billion on infrastructure projects such as improving highways, bridges, public transportation, and more, to stimulate overall spending.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p56" block_type="txt">In contrast, changes in either tax rates or government transfers influence the economy <em>indirectly</em> through their effect on disposable income. A lower tax rate means that consumers get to keep more of what they earn, increasing their disposable income. An increase in government transfers also increases consumers&#8217; disposable income. In either case, this increases consumer spending and shifts the aggregate demand curve to the right. A higher tax rate or a reduction in transfers reduces the amount of disposable income received by consumers. This reduces consumer spending and shifts the aggregate demand curve to the left.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p57" block_type="txt-3"><phrase block_type="h3"><strong>Monetary Policy</strong></phrase> Earlier we talked about the problems faced by the FOMC, the branch of the Federal Reserve that controls monetary policy&#8212;the use of changes in the quantity of money or the interest rate to stabilize the economy. We&#8217;ve just discussed how a rise in the aggregate price level, by reducing the purchasing power of money holdings, causes a rise in the interest rate. That, in turn, reduces both investment spending and consumer spending. </p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p58" block_type="txt">But what happens if the quantity of money in the hands of households and firms changes? In modern economies, the quantity of money in circulation is largely determined by the decisions of a <em>central bank</em> created by the government. As we&#8217;ll learn in <link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18.xml">Chapter 18</link>, the Federal Reserve, the U.S. central bank, is a special institution that is neither exactly part of the government nor exactly a private institution. When the central bank increases the quantity of money in circulation, households and firms have more money, which they are willing to lend out. The effect is to drive the interest rate down at any given aggregate price level, leading to higher investment spending and higher consumer spending. </p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_446" block_type="page_start">446</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p59" block_type="txt">That is, increasing the quantity of money shifts the aggregate demand curve to the right. Reducing the quantity of money has the opposite effect: households and firms have less money holdings than before, leading them to borrow more and lend less. This raises the interest rate, reduces investment spending and consumer spending, and shifts the aggregate demand curve to the left.</p>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-bx2-1" block_type="bx-2-h">
<box-metadata><box-title><phrase block_type="title">ECONOMICS</phrase><phrase block_type="number"><em>in Action</em></phrase></box-title></box-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p60" block_type="bx-2-t"><strong>Moving Along the Aggregrate Demand Curve, 1979&#8211;1980</strong></p>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-exp2-2" block_type="mn2">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p61" block_type="txt"><image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-img-5" alt="image" src="images/launchpad_logo_cmyk.jpg"/> &#124; interactive activity</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p62" block_type="bx2-first"><phrase block_type="dropcap">W</phrase>hen looking at data, it&#8217;s often hard to distinguish between changes in spending that represent <em>movements along</em> the aggregate demand curve and <em>shift</em>s <em>of</em> the aggregate demand curve. One telling exception, however, is what happened right after the oil crisis of 1979, which we mentioned in this chapter&#8217;s opening story. Faced with a sharp increase in the aggregate price level&#8212;the rate of consumer price inflation reached 14.8&#37; in March of 1980&#8212;the Federal Reserve stuck to a policy of increasing the quantity of money slowly. The aggregate price level was rising steeply, but the quantity of money circulating in the economy was growing slowly. The net result was that the purchasing power of the quantity of money in circulation fell.</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-fig-4" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="right" width="medium" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-img-6" alt="image" src="images/KrugESS4e_16UN01.jpg"/>
<caption>The interest rate effect of a rise in the aggregate price level leads to a drop in consumer and investment spending.</caption>
<asset_source>Glow Images/SuperStock</asset_source>
</figure>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p63" block_type="bx2-txt">This led to an increase in the demand for borrowing and a surge in interest rates. The <em>prime rate,</em> which is the interest rate banks charge their best customers, climbed above 20&#37;. High interest rates, in turn, caused both consumer spending and investment spending to fall: in 1980 purchases of durable consumer goods like cars fell by 5.3&#37; and real investment spending fell by 8.9&#37;.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p64" block_type="bx2-txt">In other words, in 1979&#8211;1980 the economy responded just as we&#8217;d expect if it were moving upward along the aggregate demand curve from right to left: due to the wealth effect and the interest rate effect of a change in the aggregate price level, the quantity of aggregate output demanded fell as the aggregate price level rose. This does not explain, of course, why the aggregate price level rose. But as we&#8217;ll see in the upcoming section on the <em>AD&#8211;AS</em> model, the answer to that question lies in the behavior of the <em>short-run aggregate supply curve.</em> </p>
</box>
<box title="Quick Review" numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-bx5-1" block_type="sr-1-h">
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-list-2" type="unordered" block_type="redbullet">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p65" block_type="sr1-bl">The <strong>aggregate demand curve</strong> is downward sloping because of the <strong>wealth effect of a change in the aggregate price level</strong> and the <strong>interest rate effect of a change in the aggregate price level.</strong></p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p66" block_type="sr1-bl">Changes in consumer spending caused by changes in wealth and expectations about the future shift the aggregate demand curve. Changes in investment spending caused by changes in expectations and by the size of the existing stock of physical capital also shift the aggregate demand curve.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p67" block_type="sr1-bl">Fiscal policy affects aggregate demand directly through government purchases and indirectly through changes in taxes or government transfers. Monetary policy affects aggregate demand indirectly through changes in the interest rate.</p></li>
</list>
</box>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-bx6-1" block_type="sr2-h">
<box-metadata><box-title><phrase block_type="title">Check Your Understanding</phrase><phrase block_type="number">16-1</phrase></box-title></box-metadata>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-cyuquestion-1" block_type="q_cyu" number="1">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p68" block_type="sr2-nl-first"><phrase block_type="qnum">1.</phrase> Determine the effect on aggregate demand of each of the following events. Explain whether it represents a movement along the aggregate demand curve (up or down) or a shift of the curve (leftward or rightward).</p>
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-list-1" type="ordered" block_type="loweralpha">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p69" block_type="sr2-nl-lvl2">A rise in the interest rate caused by a change in monetary policy</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p70" block_type="sr2-nl-lvl2">A fall in the real value of money in the economy due to a higher aggregate price level</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p71" block_type="sr2-nl-lvl2">News of a worse-than-expected job market next year</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p72" block_type="sr2-nl-lvl2">A fall in tax rates</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p73" block_type="sr2-nl-lvl2">A rise in the real value of assets in the economy due to a lower aggregate price level</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p74" block_type="sr2-nl-lvl2">A rise in the real value of assets in the economy due to a surge in real estate values</p></li>
</list>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p75" block_type="sr2-nl-fn">Solutions appear at back of book.</p>
</question>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_447" block_type="page_start">447</p>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-sec1-002" block_type="h1" title="" chapter="ch16" numbered="true" level="1" print_page="447">
<section-metadata><section-title>Aggregate Supply</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p76" block_type="txt-ni">Between 1929 and 1933 there was a sharp fall in aggregate demand&#8212;a reduction in the quantity of goods and services demanded at any given price level. One consequence of the economy-wide decline in demand was a fall in the prices of most goods and services. By 1933, the GDP deflator (one of the price indexes we defined in <link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch13.xml">Chapter 13</link>) was 26&#37; below its 1929 level, and other indexes were down by similar amounts. A second consequence was a decline in the output of most goods and services: by 1933, real GDP was 27&#37; below its 1929 level. A third consequence, closely tied to the fall in real GDP, was a surge in the unemployment rate from 3&#37; to 25&#37;.</p>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-exp3-4" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p77" block_type="mn-gl-def">The <strong>aggregate supply curve</strong> shows the relationship between the aggregate price level and the quantity of aggregate output supplied in the economy. </p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p78" block_type="txt">The association between the plunge in real GDP and the plunge in prices wasn&#8217;t an accident. Between 1929 and 1933, the U.S. economy was moving down its <strong>aggregate supply curve,</strong> which shows the relationship between the economy&#8217;s aggregate price level (the overall price level of final goods and services in the economy) and the total quantity of final goods and services, or aggregate output, producers are willing to supply. (As you will recall, we use real GDP to measure aggregate output. So we&#8217;ll often use the two terms interchangeably.) More specifically, between 1929 and 1933 the U.S. economy moved down its <em>short-run aggregate supply curve.</em></p>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-sec2-004" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="ch16" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="447">
<section-metadata><section-title>The Short-Run Aggregate Supply Curve</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p79" block_type="txt-ni">The period from 1929 to 1933 demonstrated that there is a positive relationship in the short run between the aggregate price level and the quantity of aggregate output supplied. That is, a rise in the aggregate price level is associated with a rise in the quantity of aggregate output supplied, other things equal; a fall in the aggregate price level is associated with a fall in the quantity of aggregate output supplied, other things equal.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p80" block_type="txt">To understand why this positive relationship exists, consider the most basic question facing a producer: is producing a unit of output profitable or not? Let&#8217;s define profit per unit:</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p81" block_type="eq"><strong>(16-2)</strong> Profit per unit of output =</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p82" block_type="eq">Price per unit of output &#8722; Production cost per unit of output</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p83" block_type="txt">Thus, the answer to the question depends on whether the price the producer receives for a unit of output is greater or less than the cost of producing that unit of output. At any given point in time, many of the costs producers face are fixed per unit of output and can&#8217;t be changed for an extended period of time. Typically, the largest source of inflexible production cost is the wages paid to workers. <em>Wages</em> here refers to all forms of worker compensation, such as employer-paid health care and retirement benefits in addition to earnings.</p>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-exp3-5" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p84" block_type="mn-gl-def">The <strong>nominal wage</strong> is the dollar amount of the wage paid.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p85" block_type="txt">Wages are typically an inflexible production cost because the dollar amount of any given wage paid, called the <strong>nominal wage,</strong> is often determined by contracts that were signed some time ago. And even when there are no formal contracts, there are often informal agreements between management and workers, making companies reluctant to change wages in response to economic conditions. For example, companies usually will not reduce wages during poor economic times&#8212;unless the downturn has been particularly long and severe&#8212;for fear of generating worker resentment. Correspondingly, they typically won&#8217;t raise wages during better economic times&#8212;until they are at risk of losing workers to competitors&#8212;because they don&#8217;t want to encourage workers to routinely demand higher wages.</p>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-exp3-6" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p86" block_type="mn-gl-def"><strong>Sticky wages</strong> are nominal wages that are slow to fall even in the face of high unemployment and slow to rise even in the face of labor shortages.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p87" block_type="txt">As a result of both formal and informal agreements, then, the economy is characterized by <strong>sticky wages:</strong> nominal wages that are slow to fall even in the face of high unemployment and slow to rise even in the face of labor shortages. It&#8217;s important to note, however, that nominal wages cannot be sticky forever: ultimately, formal contracts and informal agreements will be renegotiated to take into account changed economic circumstances. As the Pitfalls later in the chapter explains, how long it takes for nominal wages to become flexible is an integral component of what distinguishes the short run from the long run.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_448" block_type="page_start">448</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p88" block_type="txt">To understand how the fact that many costs are fixed in nominal terms gives rise to an upward-sloping short-run aggregate supply curve, it&#8217;s helpful to know that prices are set somewhat differently in different kinds of markets. In <em>perfectly competitive markets,</em> producers take prices as given; in <em>imperfectly competitive markets,</em> producers have some ability to choose the prices they charge. In both kinds of markets, there is a short-run positive relationship between prices and output, but for slightly different reasons.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p89" block_type="txt">Let&#8217;s start with the behavior of producers in perfectly competitive markets; remember, they take the price as given. Imagine that, for some reason, the aggregate price level falls, which means that the price received by the typical producer of a final good or service falls. Because many production costs are fixed in the short run, production cost per unit of output doesn&#8217;t fall by the same proportion as the fall in the price of output. So the profit per unit of output declines, leading perfectly competitive producers to reduce the quantity supplied in the short run.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p90" block_type="txt">But suppose that for some reason the aggregate price level rises. As a result, the typical producer receives a higher price for its final good or service. Again, many production costs are fixed in the short run, so production cost per unit of output doesn&#8217;t rise by the same proportion as the rise in the price of a unit. And since the typical perfectly competitive producer takes the price as given, profit per unit of output rises and output increases.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p91" block_type="txt">Now consider an imperfectly competitive producer that is able to set its own price. If there is a rise in the demand for this producer&#8217;s product, it will be able to sell more at any given price. Given stronger demand for its products, it will probably choose to increase its prices as well as its output, as a way of increasing profit per unit of output. In fact, industry analysts often talk about variations in an industry&#8217;s &#8220;pricing power&#8221;: when demand is strong, firms with pricing power are able to raise prices&#8212;and they do.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p92" block_type="txt">Conversely, if there is a fall in demand, firms will normally try to limit the fall in their sales by cutting prices.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_449" block_type="page_start">449</p>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-exp3-7" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p93" block_type="mn-gl-def">The <strong>short-run aggregate supply curve</strong> shows the relationship between the aggregate price level and the quantity of aggregate output supplied that exists in the short run, the time period when many production costs can be taken as fixed.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p94" block_type="txt">Both the responses of firms in perfectly competitive industries and those of firms in imperfectly competitive industries lead to an upward-sloping relationship between aggregate output and the aggregate price level. The positive relationship between the aggregate price level and the quantity of aggregate output producers are willing to supply during the time period when many production costs, particularly nominal wages, can be taken as fixed is illustrated by the <strong>short-run aggregate supply curve.</strong> The positive relationship between the aggregate price level and aggregate output in the short run gives the short-run aggregate supply curve its upward slope.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p95" block_type="txt"><link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16.xml#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-fig-5">Figure 16-3</link> shows a hypothetical short-run aggregate supply curve, <em>SRAS,</em> which matches actual U.S. data for 1929 and 1933. On the horizontal axis is aggregate output (or, equivalently, real GDP)&#8212;the total quantity of final goods and services supplied in the economy&#8212;measured in 2009 dollars. On the vertical axis is the aggregate price level as measured by the GDP deflator, with the value for the year 2009 equal to 100. In 1929, the aggregate price level was 9.9 and real GDP was &#36;1,057 billion. In 1933, the aggregate price level was 7.3 and real GDP was only &#36;778 billion. The movement down the <em>SRAS</em> curve corresponds to the deflation and fall in aggregate output experienced over those years.</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-fig-5" block_type="figure" numbered="true" number="16-3" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="medium" border="true"/>
<caption><link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16.xml#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-fig-5"><phrase block_type="fig-label"><phrase block_type="fig"><strong>FIGURE</strong></phrase></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_num"><strong>16-3</strong></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_title">Short-Run Aggregate Supply Curve</phrase></link></caption>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-img-7" alt="image" src="images/KrugESS4e_fig_16_03.jpg"/>
<caption>The short-run aggregate supply curve shows the relationship between the aggregate price level and the quantity of aggregate output supplied in the short run, the period in which many production costs such as nominal wages are fixed. It is upward sloping because a higher aggregate price level leads to higher profit per unit of output and higher aggregate output given fixed nominal wages. Here we show numbers corresponding to the Great Depression, from 1929 to 1933: when deflation occurred and the aggregate price level fell from 9.9 (in 1929) to 7.3 (in 1933), firms responded by reducing the quantity of aggregate output supplied from &#36;1,057 billion to &#36;778 billion measured in 2009 dollars.</caption>
</figure>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-sec2-005" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="ch16" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="449">
<section-metadata><section-title>Shifts of the Short-Run Aggregate Supply Curve</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p96" block_type="txt-ni"><link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16.xml#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-fig-5">Figure 16-3</link> shows a <em>movement along</em> the short-run aggregate supply curve, as the aggregate price level and aggregate output fell from 1929 to 1933. But there can also be <em>shifts of</em> the short-run aggregate supply curve, as shown in <link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16.xml#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-fig-6">Figure 16-4</link>. Panel (a) shows a <em>decrease in short-run aggregate supply&#8212;</em>a leftward shift of the short-run aggregate supply curve. Aggregate supply decreases when producers reduce the quantity of aggregate output they are willing to supply at any given aggregate price level. Panel (b) shows an <em>increase in short-run aggregate supply&#8212;</em>a rightward shift of the short-run aggregate supply curve. Aggregate supply increases when producers increase the quantity of aggregate output they are willing to supply at any given aggregate price level.</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-fig-6" block_type="figure" numbered="true" number="16-4" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="medium" border="true"/>
<caption><link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16.xml#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-fig-6"><phrase block_type="fig-label"><phrase block_type="fig"><strong>FIGURE</strong></phrase></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_num"><strong>16-4</strong></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_title">Shifts of the Short-Run Aggregate Supply Curve</phrase></link></caption>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-img-8" alt="image" src="images/KrugESS4e_fig_16_04ab.jpg"/>
<caption>Panel (a) shows a decrease in short-run aggregate supply: the short-run aggregate supply curve shifts leftward from <em>SRAS</em><sub>1</sub> to <em>SRAS</em><sub>2</sub>, and the quantity of aggregate output supplied at any given aggregate price level falls. Panel (b) shows an increase in short-run aggregate supply: the short-run aggregate supply curve shifts rightward from <em>SRAS</em><sub>1</sub> to <em>SRAS</em><sub>2</sub>, and the quantity of aggregate output supplied at any given aggregate price level rises.</caption>
</figure>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-bx3-2" block_type="bx3-t">
<box-metadata><box-title><strong>FOR INQUIRING MINDS</strong> &#124; What&#8217;s Truly Flexible, What&#8217;s Truly Sticky</box-title></box-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p97" block_type="bx3-txt-ni">Most macroeconomists agree that the basic picture shown in <link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16.xml#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-fig-5">Figure 16-3</link> is correct: there is, other things equal, a positive short-run relationship between the aggregate price level and aggregate output. But many would argue that the details are a bit more complicated.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p98" block_type="bx3-txt">So far we&#8217;ve stressed a difference in the behavior of the aggregate price level and the behavior of nominal wages. That is, we&#8217;ve said that the aggregate price level is flexible but nominal wages are sticky in the short run. Although this assumption is a good way to explain why the short-run aggregate supply curve is upward sloping, empirical data on wages and prices don&#8217;t wholly support a sharp distinction between flexible prices of final goods and services and sticky nominal wages.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p99" block_type="bx3-txt">On one side, some nominal wages are in fact flexible even in the short run because some workers are not covered by a contract or informal agreement with their employers. Since some nominal wages are sticky but others are flexible, we observe that the <em>average nominal wage&#8212;</em>the nominal wage averaged over all workers in the economy&#8212;falls when there is a steep rise in unemployment. For example, nominal wages fell substantially in the early years of the Great Depression.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p100" block_type="bx3-txt">On the other side, some prices of final goods and services are sticky rather than flexible. For example, some firms, particularly the makers of luxury or name-brand goods, are reluctant to cut prices even when demand falls. Instead they prefer to cut output even if their profit per unit hasn&#8217;t declined.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p101" block_type="bx3-txt">These complications, as we&#8217;ve said, don&#8217;t change the basic picture. When the aggregate price level falls, some producers cut output because the nominal wages they pay are sticky. And some producers don&#8217;t cut their prices in the face of a falling aggregate price level, preferring instead to reduce their output. In both cases, the positive relationship between the aggregate price level and aggregate output is maintained. So, in the end, the short-run aggregate supply curve is still upward sloping.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_450" block_type="page_start">450</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p102" block_type="txt">To understand why the short-run aggregate supply curve can shift, it&#8217;s important to recall that producers make output decisions based on their profit per unit of output. The short-run aggregate supply curve illustrates the relationship between the aggregate price level and aggregate output: because some production costs are fixed in the short run, a change in the aggregate price level leads to a change in producers&#8217; profit per unit of output and, in turn, leads to a change in aggregate output. But other factors besides the aggregate price level can affect profit per unit and, in turn, aggregate output. It is changes in these other factors that will shift the short-run aggregate supply curve.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p103" block_type="txt">To develop some intuition, suppose that something happens that raises production costs&#8212;say, an increase in the price of oil. At any given price of output, a producer now earns a smaller profit per unit of output. As a result, producers reduce the quantity supplied at any given aggregate price level, and the short-run aggregate supply curve shifts to the left. If, in contrast, something happens that lowers production costs&#8212;say, a fall in the nominal wage&#8212;a producer now earns a higher profit per unit of output at any given price of output. This leads producers to increase the quantity of aggregate output supplied at any given aggregate price level, and the short-run aggregate supply curve shifts to the right.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p104" block_type="txt">Now we&#8217;ll discuss some of the important factors that affect producers&#8217; profit per unit and so can lead to shifts of the short-run aggregate supply curve.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p105" block_type="txt-3"><phrase block_type="h3"><strong>Changes in Commodity Prices</strong></phrase> In this chapter&#8217;s opening story, we described how a surge in the price of oil caused problems for the U.S. economy in the 1970s and early in 2008. Oil is a commodity, a standardized input bought and sold in bulk quantities. An increase in the price of a commodity&#8212;oil&#8212;raised production costs across the economy and reduced the quantity of aggregate output supplied at any given aggregate price level, shifting the short-run aggregate supply curve to the left. Conversely, a decline in commodity prices reduces production costs, leading to an increase in the quantity supplied at any given aggregate price level and a rightward shift of the short-run aggregate supply curve.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p106" block_type="txt">Why isn&#8217;t the influence of commodity prices already captured by the short-run aggregate supply curve? Because commodities&#8212;unlike, say, soft drinks&#8212;are not a final good, their prices are not included in the calculation of the aggregate price level. Further, commodities represent a significant cost of production to most suppliers, just like nominal wages do. So changes in commodity prices have large impacts on production costs. And in contrast to noncommodities, the prices of commodities can sometimes change drastically due to industry-specific shocks to supply&#8212;such as wars in the Middle East or rising Chinese demand that leaves less oil for the United States.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_451" block_type="page_start">451</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p107" block_type="txt-3"><phrase block_type="h3"><strong>Changes in Nominal Wages</strong></phrase> At any given point in time, the dollar wages of many workers are fixed because they are set by contracts or informal agreements made in the past. Nominal wages can change, however, once enough time has passed for contracts and informal agreements to be renegotiated. Suppose, for example, that there is an economy-wide rise in the cost of health care insurance premiums paid by employers as part of employees&#8217; wages. From the employers&#8217; perspective, this is equivalent to a rise in nominal wages because it is an increase in employer-paid compensation. So this rise in nominal wages increases production costs and shifts the short-run aggregate supply curve to the left. Conversely, suppose there is an economy-wide fall in the cost of such premiums. This is equivalent to a fall in nominal wages from the point of view of employers; it reduces production costs and shifts the short-run aggregate supply curve to the right.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p108" block_type="txt">An important historical fact is that during the 1970s the surge in the price of oil had the indirect effect of also raising nominal wages. This &#8220;knock-on&#8221; effect occurred because many wage contracts included <em>cost-of-living allowances</em> that automatically raised the nominal wage when consumer prices increased. Through this channel, the surge in the price of oil&#8212;which led to an increase in overall consumer prices&#8212;ultimately caused a rise in nominal wages.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p109" block_type="txt">So the economy, in the end, experienced two leftward shifts of the aggregate supply curve: the first generated by the initial surge in the price of oil, the second generated by the induced increase in nominal wages. The negative effect on the economy of rising oil prices was greatly magnified through the cost-of-living allowances in wage contracts. Today, cost-of-living allowances in wage contracts are rare.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p110" block_type="txt-3"><phrase block_type="h3"><strong>Changes in Productivity</strong></phrase> An increase in productivity means that a worker can produce more units of output with the same quantity of inputs. For example, the introduction of bar-code scanners in retail stores greatly increased the ability of a single worker to stock, inventory, and resupply store shelves. As a result, the cost to a store of &#8220;producing&#8221; a dollar of sales fell and profit rose. And, correspondingly, the quantity supplied increased. (Think of Walmart and the increase in the number of its stores as an increase in aggregate supply.) So a rise in productivity, whatever the source, increases producers&#8217; profits and shifts the short-run aggregate supply curve to the right. </p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p111" block_type="txt">Conversely, a fall in productivity&#8212;say, due to new regulations that require workers to spend more time filling out forms&#8212;reduces the number of units of output a worker can produce with the same quantity of inputs. Consequently, the cost per unit of output rises, profit falls, and quantity supplied falls. This shifts the short-run aggregate supply curve to the left.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p112" block_type="txt">A summary of the factors that shift the short-run aggregate supply curve appears in <link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16.xml#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-tab-2">Table 16-2</link>.</p>
<table id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-tab-2" block_type="table" numbered="false" caption-placement="Top" data-href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-tab-2" data-target="_pop">
<table_caption><strong><phrase block_type="tbl">TABLE</phrase> <phrase block_type="tbl_num">16-2</phrase></strong> <phrase block_type="tbl_title">Factors That Shift Aggregate Supply</phrase></table_caption>
<tbody>
<tr class="tbl-hdr-bg">
<td class="tbl-ljust"><strong>When this<br/>happens, . . .</strong></td>
<td><strong>. . . aggregate<br/>demand increases:</strong></td>
<td class="tbl-ljust"><strong>But when this<br/>happens, . . .</strong></td>
<td><strong>. . . aggregate<br/>demand decreases:</strong></td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-hdr-bg">
<td colspan="4" class="tbl-ljust"><strong>Changes in commodity prices:</strong></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="2" class="tbl-td-light">
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-img-11" alt="image" src="images/KrugESS4e_T_16_02a.jpg"/></td>
<td colspan="2" class="tbl-td-dark">
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-img-12" alt="image" src="images/KrugESS4e_T_16_02d.jpg"/></td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-hdr-bg">
<td colspan="4" class="tbl-ljust"><strong>Changes in nominal wages:</strong></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="2" class="tbl-td-light">
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-img-11" alt="image" src="images/KrugESS4e_T_16_02b.jpg"/></td>
<td colspan="2" class="tbl-td-dark">
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-img-12" alt="image" src="images/KrugESS4e_T_16_02e.jpg"/></td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-hdr-bg">
<td colspan="4" class="tbl-ljust"><strong>Changes in productivity:</strong></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="2" class="tbl-td-light">
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-img-13" alt="image" src="images/KrugESS4e_T_16_02c.jpg"/></td>
<td colspan="2" class="tbl-td-dark">
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-img-14" alt="image" src="images/KrugESS4e_T_16_02f.jpg"/></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-sec2-006" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="ch16" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="451">
<section-metadata><section-title>The Long-Run Aggregate Supply Curve</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p113" block_type="txt-ni">We&#8217;ve just seen that in the short run a fall in the aggregate price level leads to a decline in the quantity of aggregate output supplied because nominal wages are sticky in the short run. But, as we mentioned earlier, contracts and informal agreements are renegotiated in the long run. So in the long run, nominal wages&#8212;like the aggregate price level&#8212;are flexible, not sticky. This fact greatly alters the long-run relationship between the aggregate price level and aggregate supply. In fact, in the long run the aggregate price level has <em>no</em> effect on the quantity of aggregate output supplied.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p114" block_type="txt">To see why, let&#8217;s conduct a thought experiment. Imagine that you could wave a magic wand&#8212;or maybe a magic bar-code scanner&#8212;and cut <em>all prices</em> in the economy in half at the same time. By &#8220;all prices&#8221; we mean the prices of all inputs, including nominal wages, as well as the prices of final goods and services. What would happen to aggregate output, given that the aggregate price level has been halved and all input prices, including nominal wages, have been halved?</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_452" block_type="page_start">452</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p115" block_type="txt">The answer is: nothing. Consider Equation 16-2 again: each producer would receive a lower price for its product, but costs would fall by the same proportion. As a result, every unit of output profitable to produce before the change in prices would still be profitable to produce after the change in prices. So a halving of <em>all</em> prices in the economy has no effect on the economy&#8217;s aggregate output. In other words, changes in the aggregate price level now have no effect on the quantity of aggregate output supplied.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p116" block_type="txt">In reality, of course, no one can change all prices by the same proportion at the same time. But we&#8217;ll now consider the <em>long run, the period of time over which all prices are fully flexible.</em> In the long run, inflation or deflation has the same effect as someone changing all prices by the same proportion. <em>As a result, changes in the aggregate price level do not change the quantity of aggregate output supplied in the long run.</em> That&#8217;s because changes in the aggregate price level will, in the long run, be accompanied by equal proportional changes in <em>all</em> input prices, including nominal wages.</p>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-exp3-8" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p117" block_type="mn-gl-def">The <strong>long-run aggregate supply curve</strong> shows the relationship between the aggregate price level and the quantity of aggregate output supplied that would exist if all prices, including nominal wages, were fully flexible.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p118" block_type="txt">The <strong>long-run aggregate supply curve,</strong> illustrated in <link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16.xml#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-fig-7">Figure 16-5</link> by the curve <em>LRAS,</em> shows the relationship between the aggregate price level and the quantity of aggregate output supplied that would exist if all prices, including nominal wages, were fully flexible. The long-run aggregate supply curve is vertical because changes in the aggregate price level have <em>no</em> effect on aggregate output in the long run. At an aggregate price level of 15.0, the quantity of aggregate output supplied is &#36;800 billion in 2009 dollars. If the aggregate price level falls by 50&#37; to 7.5, the quantity of aggregate output supplied is unchanged in the long run at &#36;800 billion in 2009 dollars.</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-fig-7" block_type="figure" numbered="true" number="16-5" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="medium" border="true"/>
<caption><link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16.xml#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-fig-7"><phrase block_type="fig-label"><phrase block_type="fig"><strong>FIGURE</strong></phrase></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_num"><strong>16-5</strong></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_title">The Long-Run Aggregate Supply Curve</phrase></link></caption>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-img-9" alt="image" src="images/KrugESS4e_fig_16_05.jpg"/>
<caption>The long-run aggregate supply curve shows the quantity of aggregate output supplied when all prices, including nominal wages, are flexible. It is vertical at potential output, <em>Y<sub>P</sub></em>, because in the long run a change in the aggregate price level has no effect on the quantity of aggregate output supplied.</caption>
</figure>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_453" block_type="page_start">453</p>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-exp3-9" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p119" block_type="mn-gl-def"><strong>Potential output</strong> is the level of real GDP the economy would produce if all prices, including nominal wages, were fully flexible.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p120" block_type="txt">It&#8217;s important to understand not only that the <em>LRAS</em> curve is vertical but also that its position along the horizontal axis represents a significant measure. The horizontal intercept in <link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16.xml#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-fig-7">Figure 16-5</link>, where <em>LRAS</em> touches the horizontal axis (&#36;800 billion in 2009 dollars), is the economy&#8217;s <strong>potential output,</strong> <em>Y<sub>P</sub></em><em>:</em> the level of real GDP the economy would produce if all prices, including nominal wages, were fully flexible.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p121" block_type="txt">In reality, the actual level of real GDP is almost always either above or below potential output. We&#8217;ll see why later in this chapter, when we discuss the <em>AD&#8211;AS</em> model. Still, an economy&#8217;s potential output is an important number because it defines the trend around which actual aggregate output fluctuates from year to year.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p122" block_type="txt">In the United States, the Congressional Budget Office, or CBO, estimates annual potential output for the purpose of federal budget analysis. In <link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16.xml#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-fig-8">Figure 16-6</link>, the CBO&#8217;s estimates of U.S. potential output from 1990 to 2014 are represented by the orange line and the actual values of U.S. real GDP over the same period are represented by the blue line. Years shaded purple on the horizontal axis correspond to periods in which actual aggregate output fell short of potential output, years shaded green to periods in which actual aggregate output exceeded potential output.</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-fig-8" block_type="figure" numbered="true" number="16-6" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="medium" border="true"/>
<caption><link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16.xml#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-fig-8"><phrase block_type="fig-label"><phrase block_type="fig"><strong>FIGURE</strong></phrase></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_num"><strong>16-6</strong></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_title">Actual and Potential Output from 1990 to 2014</phrase></link></caption>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-img-10" alt="image" src="images/KrugESS4e_fig_16_06.jpg"/>
<caption>This figure shows the performance of actual and potential output in the United States from 1990 to 2014. The orange line shows estimates of U.S. potential output, produced by the Congressional Budget Office, and the blue line shows actual aggregate output. The purple-shaded years are periods in which actual aggregate output fell below potential output, and the green-shaded years are periods in which actual aggregate output exceeded potential output. As shown, significant shortfalls occurred in the recessions of the early 1990s and after 2000. Actual aggregate output was significantly above potential output in the boom of the late 1990s, and a huge shortfall occurred after the recession of 2007&#8211;2009.</caption>
<asset_source><em>Data from:</em> Congressional Budget Office; Bureau of Economic Analysis.</asset_source>
</figure>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p123" block_type="txt">As you can see, U.S. potential output has risen steadily over time&#8212;implying a series of rightward shifts of the <em>LRAS</em> curve. What has caused these rightward shifts? The answer lies in the factors related to long-run growth that we discussed in <link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch15.xml">Chapter 15</link>, such as increases in physical capital and human capital as well as technological progress. Over the long run, as the size of the labor force and the productivity of labor both rise, the level of real GDP that the economy is capable of producing also rises. Indeed, one way to think about long-run economic growth is that it is the growth in the economy&#8217;s potential output. We generally think of the long-run aggregate supply curve as shifting to the right over time as an economy experiences long-run growth.</p>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-sec2-007" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="ch16" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="453">
<section-metadata><section-title>From the Short Run to the Long Run</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p124" block_type="txt-ni">As you can see in <link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16.xml#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-fig-8">Figure 16-6</link>, the economy normally produces more or less than potential output: actual aggregate output was below potential output in the early 1990s, above potential output in the late 1990s, below potential output for most of the 2000s, and significantly below potential output after the recession of 2007&#8211;2009. So the economy is normally on its short-run aggregate supply curve&#8212;but not on its long-run aggregate supply curve. So why is the long-run curve relevant? Does the economy ever move from the short run to the long run? And if so, how?</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_454" block_type="page_start">454</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p125" block_type="txt">The first step to answering these questions is to understand that the economy is always in one of only two states with respect to the short-run and long-run aggregate supply curves:</p>
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-list-2" type="ordered" block_type="numbered">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p126" block_type="nl-first">It can be on both curves simultaneously by being at a point where the curves cross (as in the few years in <link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16.xml#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-fig-8">Figure 16-6</link> in which actual aggregate output and potential output roughly coincided).</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p127" block_type="nl-last">Or it can be on the short-run aggregate supply curve but not the long-run aggregate supply curve (as in the years in which actual aggregate output and potential output <em>did not</em> coincide).</p></li>
</list>
<box title="PITFALLS" numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-bx1-2" block_type="bx-1-h">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p128" block_type="bx1-t"><strong>ARE WE THERE YET? WHAT THE LONG RUN REALLY MEANS</strong></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p129" block_type="bx1-txt-ni">We&#8217;ve used the term <em>long run</em> in two different contexts. In the previous chapter we focused on <em>long-run economic growth</em> that takes place over decades. In this chapter we introduced the <em>long-run aggregate supply curve,</em> which depicts the economy&#8217;s potential output: the level of aggregate output that the economy would produce if all prices, including nominal wages, were fully flexible. It might seem that we&#8217;re using the same term, <em>long run,</em> for two different concepts. But we aren&#8217;t: these two concepts are really the same thing.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p130" block_type="bx1-txt">Because the economy always tends to return to potential output in the long run, actual aggregate output <em>fluctuates around</em> potential output, rarely getting too far from it. As a result, the economy&#8217;s rate of growth over long periods of time&#8212;say, decades&#8212;is very close to the rate of growth of potential output. And potential output growth is determined by the factors we analyzed in the chapter on long-run economic growth. So that means that the &#8220;long run&#8221; of long-run growth and the &#8220;long run&#8221; of the long-run aggregate supply curve coincide.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p131" block_type="txt">But that is not the end of the story. If the economy is on the short-run but not the long-run aggregate supply curve, the short-run aggregate supply curve will shift over time until the economy is at a point where both curves cross&#8212;a point where actual aggregate output is equal to potential output.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p132" block_type="txt"><link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16.xml#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-fig-9">Figure 16-7</link> illustrates how this process works. In both panels <em>LRAS</em> is the long-run aggregate supply curve, <em>SRAS</em><sub>1</sub> is the initial short-run aggregate supply curve, and the aggregate price level is at <em>P</em><sub>1</sub>. In panel (a) the economy starts at the initial production point, <em>A</em><sub>1</sub>, which corresponds to a quantity of aggregate output supplied, <em>Y</em><sub>1</sub>, that is higher than potential output, <em>Y<sub>P</sub></em>. Producing an aggregate output level (such as <em>Y</em><sub>1</sub>) that is higher than potential output (<em>Y<sub>P</sub></em>) is possible only because nominal wages haven&#8217;t yet fully adjusted upward.</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-fig-9" block_type="figure" numbered="true" number="16-7" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="medium" border="true"/>
<caption><link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16.xml#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-fig-9"><phrase block_type="fig-label"><phrase block_type="fig"><strong>FIGURE</strong></phrase></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_num"><strong>16-7</strong></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_title">From the Short Run to the Long Run</phrase></link></caption>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-img-11" alt="image" src="images/KrugESS4e_fig_16_07ab.jpg"/>
<caption>In panel (a), the initial short-run aggregate supply curve is <em>SRAS</em><sub>1</sub>. At the aggregate price level, <em>P</em><sub>1</sub>, the quantity of aggregate output supplied, <em>Y</em><sub>1</sub>, exceeds potential output, <em>Y</em><sub>P</sub>. Eventually, low unemployment will cause nominal wages to rise, leading to a leftward shift of the short-run aggregate supply curve from <em>SRAS</em><sub>1</sub> to <em>SRAS</em><sub>2</sub>. In panel (b), the reverse happens: at the aggregate price level, <em>P</em><sub>1</sub>, the quantity of aggregate output supplied is less than potential output. High unemployment eventually leads to a fall in nominal wages over time and a rightward shift of the short-run aggregate supply curve.</caption>
</figure>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_455" block_type="page_start">455</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p133" block_type="txt">Until this upward adjustment in nominal wages occurs, producers are earning high profits and producing a high level of output. But a level of aggregate output higher than potential output means a low level of unemployment. Because jobs are abundant and workers are scarce, nominal wages will rise over time, gradually shifting the short-run aggregate supply curve leftward. Eventually it will be in a new position, such as <em>SRAS</em><sub>2</sub>.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p134" block_type="txt">In panel (b), the initial production point, <em>A</em><sub>1</sub>, corresponds to an aggregate output level, <em>Y</em><sub>1</sub>, that is lower than potential output, <em>Y<sub>P</sub></em>. Producing an aggregate output level (such as <em>Y</em><sub>1</sub>) that is lower than potential output (<em>Y<sub>P</sub></em>) is possible only because nominal wages haven&#8217;t yet fully adjusted downward. Until this downward adjustment occurs, producers are earning low (or negative) profits and producing a low level of output. An aggregate output level lower than potential output means high unemployment. Because workers are abundant and jobs are scarce, nominal wages will fall over time, shifting the short-run aggregate supply curve gradually to the right. Eventually it will be in a new position, such as <em>SRAS</em><sub>2</sub>.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p135" block_type="txt">We&#8217;ll see shortly that these shifts of the short-run aggregate supply curve will return the economy to potential output in the long run. </p>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-bx2-2" block_type="bx-2-h">
<box-metadata><box-title><phrase block_type="title">ECONOMICS</phrase><phrase block_type="number"><em>in Action</em></phrase> <image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-img-12" alt="image" src="images/world_view_icon.jpg"/></box-title></box-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p136" block_type="bx-2-t"><strong>Sticky Wages in the Great Recession</strong></p>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-exp2-3" block_type="mn2">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p137" block_type="fg1-t"><image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-img-13" alt="image" src="images/launchpad_logo_cmyk.jpg"/> &#124; interactive activity</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p138" block_type="bx2-first"><phrase block_type="dropcap">W</phrase>e&#8217;ve asserted that the aggregate supply curve is upward-sloping in the short run mainly because of <em>sticky wages&#8212;</em>in particular, because employers are reluctant to cut nominal wages (and workers are unwilling to accept wage cuts) even when labor is in excess supply. But what is the evidence for wage stickiness?</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_456" block_type="page_start">456</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p139" block_type="bx2-txt">The answer is that we can look at what happens to wages at times when we might have expected to see many workers facing wage cuts because similar workers are unemployed and would be willing to work for less. If wages are sticky, what we would expect to find at such times is that many workers&#8217; wages don&#8217;t change at all: there&#8217;s no reason for employers to give them a raise, but because wages are sticky, they don&#8217;t face cuts either.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p140" block_type="bx2-txt">And that is exactly what you find during and after the Great Recession of 2007&#8211;2009. Mary Daly and Bart Hobijn, economists at the Federal Reserve Bank of San Francisco, looked at data on wage changes for a sample of workers. Their findings are shown in <link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16.xml#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-fig-10">Figure 16-8</link>: as unemployment soared after 2007, so did the fraction of U.S. workers receiving the same wage as they did a year ago. </p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-fig-10" block_type="figure" numbered="true" number="16-8" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="right" width="medium" border="true"/>
<caption><link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16.xml#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-fig-10"><phrase block_type="fig-label"><phrase block_type="fig"><strong>FIGURE</strong></phrase></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_num"><strong>16-8</strong></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_title">Sticky Wages in the Great Recession</phrase></link></caption>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-img-14" alt="image" src="images/KrugESS4e_fig_16_08.jpg"/>
</figure>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p141" block_type="bx2-txt">Similar results can be found in European nations facing high unemployment, such as Spain. The Great Recession provided strong confirmation that wages are indeed sticky.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p142" block_type="bx2-txt">When unemployment soared in the face of the economic slump following the 2008 financial crisis, you might have expected to see widespread wage cuts. But employers are reluctant to cut wages. So what we saw instead was a sharp rise in the number of workers whose wages were flat&#8212;neither rising nor falling. </p>
</box>
<box title="Quick Review" numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-bx5-2" block_type="sr-1-h">
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-list-3" type="unordered" block_type="redbullet">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p143" block_type="sr1-bl">The <strong>aggregate supply curve</strong> illustrates the relationship between the aggregate price level and the quantity of aggregate output supplied.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p144" block_type="sr1-bl*">The <strong>short-run aggregate supply curve</strong> is upward sloping: a higher aggregate price level leads to higher aggregate output given that <strong>nominal wages</strong> are <strong>sticky.</strong></p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p145" block_type="sr1-bl*">Changes in commodity prices, nominal wages, and productivity shift the short-run aggregate supply curve.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p146" block_type="sr1-bl*">In the long run, all prices are flexible, and changes in the aggregate price level have no effect on aggregate output. The <strong>long-run aggregate supply curve</strong> is vertical at <strong>potential output.</strong></p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p147" block_type="sr1-bl*">If actual aggregate output exceeds potential output, nominal wages eventually rise and the short-run aggregate supply curve shifts leftward. If potential output exceeds actual aggregate output, nominal wages eventually fall and the short-run aggregate supply curve shifts rightward.</p></li>
</list>
</box>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-bx6-2" block_type="sr2-h">
<box-metadata><box-title><phrase block_type="title">Check Your Understanding</phrase><phrase block_type="number">16-2</phrase></box-title></box-metadata>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-cyuquestion-2" block_type="q_cyu" number="1">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p148" block_type="sr2-nl-first"><phrase block_type="qnum">1.</phrase> Determine the effect on short-run aggregate supply of each of the following events. Explain whether it represents a movement along the <em>SRAS</em> curve or a shift of the <em>SRAS</em> curve.</p>
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-list-3" type="ordered" block_type="loweralpha">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p149" block_type="sr2-nl-lvl2">A rise in the consumer price index (CPI) leads producers to increase output.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p150" block_type="sr2-nl-lvl2">A fall in the price of oil leads producers to increase output.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p151" block_type="sr2-nl-lvl2">A rise in legally mandated retirement benefits paid to workers leads producers to reduce output.</p></li>
</list>
</question>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-cyuquestion-3" block_type="q_cyu" number="1">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p152" block_type="sr2-nl-first"><phrase block_type="qnum">2.</phrase> Suppose the economy is initially at potential output and the quantity of aggregate output supplied increases. What information would you need to determine whether this was due to a movement along the <em>SRAS</em> curve or a shift of the <em>LRAS</em> curve?</p>
</question>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p153" block_type="sr2-nl-fn">Solutions appear at back of book.</p>
</box>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-sec1-003" block_type="h1" title="" chapter="ch16" numbered="true" level="1" print_page="456">
<section-metadata><section-title>The <em>AD&#8211;AS</em> Model</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p154" block_type="txt-ni">From 1929 to 1933, the U.S. economy moved down the short-run aggregate supply curve as the aggregate price level fell. In contrast, from 1979 to 1980 the U.S. economy moved up the aggregate demand curve as the aggregate price level rose. In each case, the cause of the movement along the curve was a shift of the other curve. In 1929&#8211;1933, it was a leftward shift of the aggregate demand curve&#8212;a major fall in consumer spending. In 1979&#8211;1980, it was a leftward shift of the short-run aggregate supply curve&#8212;a dramatic fall in short-run aggregate supply caused by the oil price shock.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_457" block_type="page_start">457</p>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-exp3-10" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p155" block_type="mn-gl-def">In the <strong>AD&#8211;AS model,</strong> the aggregate supply curve and the aggregate demand curve are used together to analyze economic fluctuations.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p156" block_type="txt">So to understand the behavior of the economy, we must put the aggregate supply curve and the aggregate demand curve together. The result is the <strong>AD&#8211;AS model,</strong> the basic model we use to understand economic fluctuations.</p>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-sec2-008" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="ch16" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="457">
<section-metadata><section-title>Short-Run Macroeconomic Equilibrium</section-title></section-metadata>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-exp3-11" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p157" block_type="mn-gl-def">The economy is in <strong>short-run macroeconomic equilibrium</strong> when the quantity of aggregate output supplied is equal to the quantity demanded.</p>
</box>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-exp3-12" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p158" block_type="mn-gl-def">The <strong>short-run equilibrium aggregate price level</strong> is the aggregate price level in the short-run macroeconomic equilibrium.</p>
</box>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-exp3-13" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p159" block_type="mn-gl-def"><strong>Short-run equilibrium aggregate output</strong> is the quantity of aggregate output produced in the short-run macroeconomic equilibrium.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p160" block_type="txt-ni">We&#8217;ll begin our analysis by focusing on the short run. <link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16.xml#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-fig-11">Figure 16-9</link> shows the aggregate demand curve and the short-run aggregate supply curve on the same diagram. The point at which the <em>AD</em> and <em>SRAS</em> curves intersect, <em>E<sub>SR</sub></em>, is the <strong>short-run macroeconomic equilibrium:</strong> the point at which the quantity of aggregate output supplied is equal to the quantity demanded by domestic households, businesses, the government, and the rest of the world. The aggregate price level at <em>E<sub>SR</sub>, P<sub>E</sub>,</em> is the <strong>short-run equilibrium aggregate price level.</strong> The level of aggregate output at <em>E<sub>SR</sub>, Y<sub>E</sub>,</em> is the <strong>short-run equilibrium aggregate output.</strong></p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-fig-11" block_type="figure" numbered="true" number="16-9" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="medium" border="true"/>
<caption><link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16.xml#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-fig-11"><phrase block_type="fig-label"><phrase block_type="fig"><strong>FIGURE</strong></phrase></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_num"><strong>16-9</strong></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_title">The <em>AD&#8211;AS</em> Model</phrase></link></caption>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-img-15" alt="image" src="images/KrugESS4e_fig_16_09.jpg"/>
<caption>The <em>AD&#8211;AS</em> model combines the aggregate demand curve and the short-run aggregate supply curve. Their point of intersection, <em>E<sub>SR</sub></em>, is the point of short-run macroeconomic equilibrium where the quantity of aggregate output demanded is equal to the quantity of aggregate output supplied. <em>P<sub>E</sub></em> is the short-run equilibrium aggregate price level, and <em>Y<sub>E</sub></em> is the short-run equilibrium level of aggregate output.</caption>
</figure>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p161" block_type="txt">In the supply and demand model we saw that a shortage of any individual good causes its market price to rise but a surplus of the good causes its market price to fall. These forces ensure that the market reaches equilibrium. The same logic applies to short-run macroeconomic equilibrium. If the aggregate price level is above its equilibrium level, the quantity of aggregate output supplied exceeds the quantity of aggregate output demanded. This leads to a fall in the aggregate price level and pushes it toward its equilibrium level. </p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p162" block_type="txt">If the aggregate price level is below its equilibrium level, the quantity of aggregate output supplied is less than the quantity of aggregate output demanded. This leads to a rise in the aggregate price level, again pushing it toward its equilibrium level. In the discussion that follows, we&#8217;ll assume that the economy is always in short-run macroeconomic equilibrium.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p163" block_type="txt">We&#8217;ll also make another important simplification based on the observation that in reality there is a long-term upward trend in both aggregate output and the aggregate price level. We&#8217;ll assume that a fall in either variable really means a fall compared to the long-run trend. For example, if the aggregate price level normally rises 4&#37; per year, a year in which the aggregate price level rises only 3&#37; would count, for our purposes, as a 1&#37; decline. In fact, since the Great Depression there have been very few years in which the aggregate price level of any major nation actually declined&#8212;Japan&#8217;s period of deflation since 1995 is one of the few exceptions. There have, however, been many cases in which the aggregate price level fell relative to the long-run trend.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p164" block_type="txt">Short-run equilibrium aggregate output and the short-run equilibrium aggregate price level can change either because of shifts of the <em>AD</em> curve or because of shifts of the <em>SRAS</em> curve. Let&#8217;s look at each case in turn.</p>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-sec2-009" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="ch16" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="458">
<section-metadata><section-title>Shifts of Aggregate Demand: Short-Run Effects</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_458" block_type="page_start">458</p>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-exp3-14" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p165" block_type="mn-gl-def">An event that shifts the aggregate demand curve is a <strong>demand shock.</strong></p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p166" block_type="txt-ni">An event that shifts the aggregate demand curve, such as a change in expectations or wealth, the effect of the size of the existing stock of physical capital, or the use of fiscal or monetary policy, is known as a <strong>demand shock.</strong> The Great Depression was caused by a negative demand shock, the collapse of wealth and of business and consumer confidence that followed the stock market crash of 1929 and the banking crisis of 1930&#8211;1931.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p167" block_type="txt">The Depression was ended by a positive demand shock&#8212;the huge increase in government purchases during World War II. In 2008 the U.S. economy experienced another significant negative demand shock as the housing market turned from boom to bust, leading consumers and firms to scale back their spending.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p168" block_type="txt"><link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16.xml#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-fig-12">Figure 16-10</link> shows the short-run effects of negative and positive demand shocks. A negative demand shock shifts the aggregate demand curve, <em>AD,</em> to the left, from <em>AD</em><sub>1</sub> to <em>AD</em><sub>2</sub>, as shown in panel (a). The economy moves down along the <em>SRAS</em> curve from <em>E</em><sub>1</sub> to <em>E</em><sub>2</sub>, leading to lower short-run equilibrium aggregate output and a lower short-run equilibrium aggregate price level. A positive demand shock shifts the aggregate demand curve, <em>AD,</em> to the right, as shown in panel (b). Here, the economy moves up along the <em>SRAS</em> curve, from <em>E</em><sub>1</sub> to <em>E</em><sub>2</sub>. This leads to higher short-run equilibrium aggregate output and a higher short-run equilibrium aggregate price level. Demand shocks cause aggregate output and the aggregate price level to move in the same direction.</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-fig-12" block_type="figure" numbered="true" number="16-10" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="medium" border="true"/>
<caption><link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16.xml#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-fig-12"><phrase block_type="fig-label"><phrase block_type="fig"><strong>FIGURE</strong></phrase></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_num"><strong>16-10</strong></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_title">Demand Shocks</phrase></link></caption>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-img-16" alt="image" src="images/KrugESS4e_fig_16_10ab.jpg"/>
<caption>A demand shock shifts the aggregate demand curve, moving the aggregate price level and aggregate output in the same direction. In panel (a), a negative demand shock shifts the aggregate demand curve leftward from <em>AD</em><sub>1</sub> to <em>AD</em><sub>2</sub>, reducing the aggregate price level from <em>P</em><sub>1</sub> to <em>P</em><sub>2</sub> and aggregate output from <em>Y</em><sub>1</sub> to <em>Y</em><sub>2</sub>. In panel (b), a positive demand shock shifts the aggregate demand curve rightward, increasing the aggregate price level from <em>P</em><sub>1</sub> to <em>P</em><sub>2</sub> and aggregate output from <em>Y</em><sub>1</sub> to <em>Y</em><sub>2</sub>. </caption>
</figure>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-sec2-010" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="ch16" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="458">
<section-metadata><section-title>Shifts of the SRAS Curve</section-title></section-metadata>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-exp3-15" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p169" block_type="mn-gl-def">An event that shifts the short-run aggregate supply curve is a <strong>supply shock.</strong></p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p170" block_type="txt-ni">An event that shifts the short-run aggregate supply curve, such as a change in commodity prices, nominal wages, or productivity, is known as a <strong>supply shock.</strong> A <em>negative</em> supply shock raises production costs and reduces the quantity producers are willing to supply at any given aggregate price level, leading to a leftward shift of the short-run aggregate supply curve. The U.S. economy experienced severe negative supply shocks following disruptions to world oil supplies in 1973 and 1979.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_459" block_type="page_start">459</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p171" block_type="txt">In contrast, a <em>positive</em> supply shock reduces production costs and increases the quantity supplied at any given aggregate price level, leading to a rightward shift of the short-run aggregate supply curve. The United States experienced a positive supply shock between 1995 and 2000, when the increasing use of the internet and other information technologies caused productivity growth to surge.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p172" block_type="txt">The effects of a negative supply shock are shown in panel (a) of <link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16.xml#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-fig-13">Figure 16-11</link>. The initial equilibrium is at <em>E</em><sub>1</sub>, with aggregate price level <em>P</em><sub>1</sub> and aggregate output <em>Y</em><sub>1</sub>. The disruption in the oil supply causes the short-run aggregate supply curve to shift to the left, from <em>SRAS</em><sub>1</sub> to <em>SRAS</em><sub>2</sub>. As a consequence, aggregate output falls and the aggregate price level rises, an upward movement along the <em>AD</em> curve. At the new equilibrium, <em>E</em><sub>2</sub>, the short-run equilibrium aggregate price level, <em>P</em><sub>2</sub>, is higher, and the short-run equilibrium aggregate output level, <em>Y</em><sub>2</sub>, is lower than before.</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-fig-13" block_type="figure" numbered="true" number="16-11" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="medium" border="true"/>
<caption><link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16.xml#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-fig-13"><phrase block_type="fig-label"><phrase block_type="fig"><strong>FIGURE</strong></phrase></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_num"><strong>16-11</strong></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_title">Supply Shocks</phrase></link></caption>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-img-17" alt="image" src="images/KrugESS4e_fig_16_11ab.jpg"/>
<caption>A supply shock shifts the short-run aggregate supply curve, moving the aggregate price level and aggregate output in opposite directions. Panel (a) shows a negative supply shock, which shifts the short-run aggregate supply curve leftward and causes stagflation&#8212;lower aggregate output and a higher aggregate price level. Here the short-run aggregate supply curve shifts from <em>SRAS</em><sub>1</sub> to <em>SRAS</em><sub>2</sub>, and the economy moves from <em>E</em><sub>1</sub> to <em>E</em><sub>2</sub>. The aggregate price level rises from <em>P</em><sub>1</sub> to <em>P</em><sub>2</sub>, and aggregate output falls from <em>Y</em><sub>1</sub> to <em>Y</em><sub>2</sub>. Panel (b) shows a positive supply shock, which shifts the short-run aggregate supply curve rightward, generating higher aggregate output and a lower aggregate price level. The short-run aggregate supply curve shifts from <em>SRAS</em><sub>1</sub> to <em>SRAS</em><sub>2</sub>, and the economy moves from <em>E</em><sub>1</sub> to <em>E</em><sub>2</sub>. The aggregate price level falls from <em>P</em><sub>1</sub> to <em>P</em><sub>2</sub>, and aggregate output rises from <em>Y</em><sub>1</sub> to <em>Y</em><sub>2</sub>.</caption>
</figure>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-exp3-16" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p173" block_type="mn-gl-def"><strong>Stagflation</strong> is the combination of inflation and falling aggregate output.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p174" block_type="txt">The combination of inflation and falling aggregate output shown in panel (a) has a special name: <strong>stagflation,</strong> for &#8220;stagnation plus inflation.&#8221; When an economy experiences stagflation, it&#8217;s very unpleasant: falling aggregate output leads to rising unemployment, and people feel that their purchasing power is squeezed by rising prices. Stagflation in the 1970s led to a mood of national pessimism. It also poses a dilemma for policy makers.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p175" block_type="txt">A positive supply shock, shown in panel (b), has exactly the opposite effects. A rightward shift of the <em>SRAS</em> curve from <em>SRAS</em><sub>1</sub> to <em>SRAS</em><sub>2 </sub>results in a rise in aggregate output and a fall in the aggregate price level, a downward movement along the <em>AD</em> curve. The favorable supply shocks of the late 1990s led to a combination of full employment and declining inflation. That is, the aggregate price level fell compared with the long-run trend. This combination produced, for a time, a great wave of national optimism.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_460" block_type="page_start">460</p>
<box title="GLOBAL COMPARISION " numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-bx4-1" block_type="bx4-h">
<box-metadata><box-title><image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-img-18" alt="image" src="images/World_icon_no_type.jpg"/> <phrase block_type="gc1">GLOBAL</phrase><phrase block_type="gc2">COMPARISON</phrase></box-title></box-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p176" block_type="bx4-t"><strong>Supply Shocks of the Twenty-first Century</strong></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p177" block_type="bx4-txt-ni"><phrase block_type="dropcap">T</phrase>he price of oil and other raw materials has been highly unstable in recent years, with surging prices in 2007&#8211;2008, plunging prices in 2008&#8211;2009, and another surge starting in the second half of 2010. The reasons for these wild swings are somewhat controversial, but their macroeconomic implications are clear: much of the world has been subjected to a series of supply shocks. There was a negative shock in 2007&#8211;2008, a positive shock in 2008&#8211;2009, and another negative shock in 2010&#8211;2011.</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-fig-14" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="right" width="medium" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-img-19" alt="image" src="images/KrugESS4e_16UN02.jpg"/>
<asset_source><em>Data from:</em> Federal Reserve Bank of St. Louis.</asset_source>
</figure>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p178" block_type="bx4-txt">You can see the effect of these shocks in the accompanying figure, which shows the rate of inflation, as measured by the percentage change in consumer prices over the previous year, in three large economies. Economic policies have been quite different in the United States, Germany (which shares a currency with many other European countries), and China. Yet in all three, inflation rose sharply in 2007&#8211;2008, fell dramatically thereafter, and rose sharply again in 2011.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p179" block_type="txt">The distinctive feature of supply shocks, both negative and positive, is that, unlike demand shocks, they cause the aggregate price level and aggregate output to move in <em>opposite</em> directions.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p180" block_type="txt">There&#8217;s another important contrast between supply shocks and demand shocks. As we&#8217;ve seen, monetary policy and fiscal policy enable the government to shift the <em>AD</em> curve, meaning that governments are in a position to create the kinds of shocks shown in <link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16.xml#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-fig-12">Figure 16-10</link>. It&#8217;s much harder for governments to shift the <em>AS</em> curve. Are there good policy reasons to shift the <em>AD</em> curve? We&#8217;ll turn to that question soon. First, however, let&#8217;s look at the difference between short-run macroeconomic equilibrium and long-run macroeconomic equilibrium.</p>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-sec2-011" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="ch16" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="460">
<section-metadata><section-title>Long-Run Macroeconomic Equilibrium</section-title></section-metadata>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-exp3-17" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p181" block_type="mn-gl-def">The economy is in <strong>long-run macroeconomic equilibrium</strong> when the point of short-run macroeconomic equilibrium is on the long-run aggregate supply curve.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p183" block_type="txt-ni"><link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16.xml#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-fig-15">Figure 16-12</link> combines the aggregate demand curve with both the short-run and long-run aggregate supply curves. The aggregate demand curve, <em>AD,</em> crosses the short-run aggregate supply curve, <em>SRAS,</em> at <em>E<sub>LR</sub></em>. Here we assume that enough time has elapsed that the economy is also on the long-run aggregate supply curve, <em>LRAS.</em> As a result, <em>E<sub>LR</sub></em> is at the intersection of all three curves&#8212;<em>SRAS, LRAS,</em> and <em>AD.</em> So short-run equilibrium aggregate output is equal to potential output, <em>Y<sub>P</sub>.</em> Such a situation, in which the point of short-run macroeconomic equilibrium is on the long-run aggregate supply curve, is known as <strong>long-run macroeconomic equilibrium.</strong></p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-fig-15" block_type="figure" numbered="true" number="16-12" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="medium" border="true"/>
<caption><link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16.xml#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-fig-15"><phrase block_type="fig-label"><phrase block_type="fig"><strong>FIGURE</strong></phrase></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_num"><strong>16-12</strong></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_title">Long-Run Macroeconomic Equilibrium</phrase></link></caption>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-img-20" alt="image" src="images/KrugESS4e_fig_16_12.jpg"/>
<caption>Here the point of short-run macroeconomic equilibrium also lies on the long-run aggregate supply curve, <em>LRAS</em>. As a result, short-run equilibrium aggregate output is equal to potential output, <em>Y<sub>P</sub></em>. The economy is in long-run macroeconomic equilibrium at <em>E<sub>LR</sub></em>.</caption>
</figure>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p184" block_type="txt">To see the significance of long-run macroeconomic equilibrium, let&#8217;s consider what happens if a demand shock moves the economy away from long-run macroeconomic equilibrium. In <link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16.xml#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-fig-16">Figure 16-13</link>, we assume that the initial aggregate demand curve is <em>AD</em><sub>1</sub> and the initial short-run aggregate supply curve is <em>SRAS</em><sub>1</sub>. So the initial macroeconomic equilibrium is at <em>E</em><sub>1</sub>, which lies on the long-run aggregate supply curve, <em>LRAS.</em> The economy, then, starts from a point of short-run and long-run macroeconomic equilibrium, and short-run equilibrium aggregate output equals potential output at <em>Y</em><sub>1</sub>.</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-fig-16" block_type="figure" numbered="true" number="16-3" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="medium" border="true"/>
<caption><link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16.xml#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-fig-16"><phrase block_type="fig-label"><phrase block_type="fig"><strong>FIGURE</strong></phrase></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_num"><strong>16-13</strong></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_title">Short-Run versus Long-Run Effects of a Negative Demand Shock</phrase></link></caption>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-img-21" alt="image" src="images/KrugESS4e_fig_16_14.jpg"/>
<caption>In the long run the economy is self-correcting: demand shocks have only a short-run effect on aggregate output. Starting at <em>E</em><sub>1</sub>, a negative demand shock shifts <em>AD</em><sub>1</sub> leftward to <em>AD</em><sub>2</sub>. In the short run the economy moves to <em>E</em><sub>2</sub> and a recessionary gap arises: the aggregate price level declines from <em>P</em><sub>1</sub> to <em>P</em><sub>2</sub>, aggregate output declines from <em>Y</em><sub>1</sub> to <em>Y</em><sub>2</sub>, and unemployment rises. But in the long run nominal wages fall in response to high unemployment at <em>Y</em><sub>2</sub>, and <em>SRAS</em><sub>1</sub> shifts rightward to <em>SRAS</em><sub>2</sub>. Aggregate output rises from <em>Y</em><sub>2</sub> to <em>Y</em><sub>1</sub>, and the aggregate price level declines again, from <em>P</em><sub>2</sub> to <em>P</em><sub>3</sub>. Long-run macroeconomic equilibrium is eventually restored at <em>E</em><sub>3</sub>.</caption>
</figure>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_461" block_type="page_start">461</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p185" block_type="txt">Now suppose that for some reason&#8212;such as a sudden worsening of business and consumer expectations&#8212;aggregate demand falls and the aggregate demand curve shifts leftward to <em>AD</em><sub>2</sub>. This results in a lower equilibrium aggregate price level at <em>P</em><sub>2</sub> and a lower equilibrium aggregate output level at <em>Y</em><sub>2</sub> as the economy settles in the short run at <em>E</em><sub>2</sub>. The short-run effect of such a fall in aggregate demand is what the U.S. economy experienced in 1929&#8211;1933: a falling aggregate price level and falling aggregate output. </p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_432" block_type="page_start">432</p>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-exp3-18" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p186" block_type="mn-gl-def">There is a <strong>recessionary gap</strong> when aggregate output is below potential output.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p187" block_type="txt">Aggregate output in this new short-run equilibrium, <em>E</em><sub>2</sub>, is below potential output. When this happens, the economy faces a <strong>recessionary gap.</strong> A recessionary gap inflicts a great deal of pain because it corresponds to high unemployment. The large recessionary gap that had opened up in the United States by 1933 caused intense social and political turmoil. And the devastating recessionary gap that opened up in Germany at the same time played an important role in Hitler&#8217;s rise to power.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p188" block_type="txt">But this isn&#8217;t the end of the story. In the face of high unemployment, nominal wages eventually fall, as do any other sticky prices, ultimately leading producers to increase output. As a result, a recessionary gap causes the short-run aggregate supply curve to gradually shift to the right over time. This process continues until <em>SRAS</em><sub>1</sub> reaches its new position at <em>SRAS</em><sub>2</sub>, bringing the economy to equilibrium at <em>E</em><sub>3</sub>, where <em>AD</em><sub>2</sub>, <em>SRAS</em><sub>2</sub>, and <em>LRAS</em> all intersect. At <em>E</em><sub>3</sub>, the economy is back in long-run macroeconomic equilibrium; it is back at potential output <em>Y</em><sub>1</sub> but at a lower aggregate price level, <em>P</em><sub>3</sub>, reflecting a long-run fall in the aggregate price level. In the end, the economy is <em>self-correcting</em> in the long run.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p189" block_type="txt">What if, instead, there was an increase in aggregate demand? The results are shown in <link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16.xml#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-fig-17">Figure 16-14</link>, where we again assume that the initial aggregate demand curve is <em>AD</em><sub>1</sub> and the initial short-run aggregate supply curve is <em>SRAS</em><sub>1</sub>, so that the initial macroeconomic equilibrium, at <em>E</em><sub>1</sub>, lies on the long-run aggregate supply curve, <em>LRAS.</em> Initially, then, the economy is in long-run macro-economic equilibrium.</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-fig-17" block_type="figure" numbered="true" number="16-14" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="medium" border="true"/>
<caption><link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16.xml#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-fig-17"><phrase block_type="fig-label"><phrase block_type="fig"><strong>FIGURE</strong></phrase></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_num"><strong>16-14</strong></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_title">Short-Run versus Long-Run Effects of a Positive Demand Shock</phrase></link></caption>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-img-22" alt="image" src="images/KrugESS4e_fig_16_13.jpg"/>
<caption>Starting at <em>E</em><sub>1</sub>, a positive demand shock shifts <em>AD</em><sub>1</sub> rightward to <em>AD</em><sub>2</sub>, and the economy moves to <em>E</em><sub>2</sub> in the short run. This results in an inflationary gap as aggregate output rises from <em>Y</em><sub>1</sub> to <em>Y</em><sub>2</sub>, the aggregate price level rises from <em>P</em><sub>1</sub> to <em>P</em><sub>2</sub>, and unemployment falls to a low level. In the long run, <em>SRAS</em><sub>1</sub> shifts leftward to <em>SRAS</em><sub>2</sub> as nominal wages rise in response to low unemployment at <em>Y</em><sub>2</sub>. Aggregate output falls back to <em>Y</em><sub>1</sub>, the aggregate price level rises again to <em>P</em><sub>3</sub>, and the economy self-corrects as it returns to long-run macroeconomic equilibrium at <em>E</em><sub>3</sub>.</caption>
</figure>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-exp3-19" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p190" block_type="mn-gl-def">There is an <strong>inflationary gap</strong> when aggregate output is above potential output.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p191" block_type="txt">Now suppose that aggregate demand rises, and the <em>AD</em> curve shifts rightward to <em>AD</em><sub>2</sub>. This results in a higher aggregate price level, at <em>P</em><sub>2</sub>, and a higher aggregate output level, at <em>Y</em><sub>2</sub>, as the economy settles in the short run at <em>E</em><sub>2</sub>. Aggregate output in this new short-run equilibrium is above potential output, and unemployment is low in order to produce this higher level of aggregate output. When this happens, the economy experiences an <strong>inflationary gap.</strong></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_463" block_type="page_start">463</p>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-bx3-3" block_type="bx3-t">
<box-metadata><box-title><strong>FOR INQUIRING MINDS</strong> &#124; Where&#8217;s the Deflation?<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-img-7a2" alt="image" src="images/world_view_icon.jpg"/></box-title></box-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p192" block_type="bx3-txt-ni">The <em>AD&#8211;AS</em> model says that either a negative demand shock or a positive supply shock should lead to a fall in the aggregate price level&#8212;that is, deflation. However, since 1949, an actual fall in the aggregate price level has been a rare occurrence in the United States. Similarly, most other countries have had little or no experience with deflation. Japan, which experienced sustained mild deflation in the late 1990s and the early part of the next decade, is the big (and much discussed) exception. What happened to deflation?</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p193" block_type="bx3-txt">The basic answer is that since World War II economic fluctuations have largely taken place around a long-run inflationary trend. Before the war, it was common for prices to fall during recessions, but since then negative demand shocks have largely been reflected in a <em>decline in the rate of inflation</em> rather than an actual fall in prices. For example, the rate of consumer price inflation fell from more than 3&#37; at the beginning of the 2001 recession to 1.1&#37; a year later, but it never went below zero.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p194" block_type="bx3-txt">All of this changed during the recession of 2007&#8211;2009. The negative demand shock that followed the 2008 financial crisis was so severe that, for most of 2009, consumer prices in the United States indeed fell. But the deflationary period didn&#8217;t last long: beginning in 2010, prices again rose, at a rate of between 1&#37; and 4&#37; per year.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p195" block_type="txt">As in the case of a recessionary gap, this isn&#8217;t the end of the story. In the face of low unemployment, nominal wages will rise, as will other sticky prices. An inflationary gap causes the short-run aggregate supply curve to shift gradually to the left as producers reduce output in the face of rising nominal wages. This process continues until <em>SRAS</em><sub>1</sub> reaches its new position at <em>SRAS</em><sub>2</sub>, bringing the economy to equilibrium at <em>E</em><sub>3</sub>, where <em>AD</em><sub>2</sub>, <em>SRAS</em><sub>2</sub>, and <em>LRAS</em> all intersect. At <em>E</em><sub>3</sub>, the economy is back in long-run macroeconomic equilibrium. It is back at potential output, but at a higher price level, <em>P</em><sub>3</sub>, reflecting a long-run rise in the aggregate price level. Again, the economy is self-correcting in the long run.</p>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-exp3-20" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p196" block_type="mn-gl-def">The <strong>output gap</strong> is the percentage difference between actual aggregate output and potential output.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p197" block_type="txt">To summarize the analysis of how the economy responds to recessionary and inflationary gaps, we can focus on the <strong>output gap,</strong> the percentage difference between actual aggregate output and potential output. The output gap is calculated as follows:</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-fig-18" block_type="equation" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="medium" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-img-23" alt="image" src="images/KrugESS4e_eqn_463_01.jpg"/>
</figure>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p198" block_type="txt-ni">Our analysis says that the output gap always tends toward zero.</p>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-exp3-45" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p199" block_type="mn-gl-def">The economy is <strong>self-correcting</strong> when shocks to aggregate demand affect aggregate output in the short run, but not the long run.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p200" block_type="txt">If there is a recessionary gap, so that the output gap is negative, nominal wages eventually fall, moving the economy back to potential output and bringing the output gap back to zero. If there is an inflationary gap, so that the output gap is positive, nominal wages eventually rise, also moving the economy back to potential output and again bringing the output gap back to zero. So in the long run the economy is <strong>self-correcting:</strong> shocks to aggregate demand affect aggregate output in the short run but not in the long run.</p>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-bx2-3" block_type="bx-2-h">
<box-metadata><box-title><phrase block_type="title">ECONOMICS</phrase><phrase block_type="number"><em>in Action</em></phrase> <image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-img-24" alt="image" src="images/world_view_icon.jpg"/></box-title></box-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p201" block_type="bx-2-t"><strong>Supply Shocks versus Demand Shocks in Practice</strong></p>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-exp2-4" block_type="mn2">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p202" block_type="fg1-t"><image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-img-25" alt="image" src="images/launchpad_logo_cmyk.jpg"/> &#124; interactive activity</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p203" block_type="bx2-first"><phrase block_type="dropcap">H</phrase>ow often do supply shocks and demand shocks, respectively, cause recessions? The verdict of most, though not all, macroeconomists is that recessions are mainly caused by demand shocks. But when a negative supply shock does happen, the resulting recession tends to be particularly severe.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p204" block_type="bx2-txt">Let&#8217;s get specific. Officially there have been twelve recessions in the United States since World War II. However, two of these, in 1979&#8211;1980 and 1981&#8211;1982, are often treated as a single &#8220;double-dip&#8221; recession, bringing the total number down to eleven. Of these eleven recessions, only two&#8212;the recession of 1973&#8211;1975 and the double-dip recession of 1979&#8211;1982&#8212;showed the distinctive combination of falling aggregate output and a surge in the price level that we call stagflation. </p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_464" block_type="page_start">464</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p205" block_type="bx2-txt">In each case, the cause of the supply shock was political turmoil in the Middle East&#8212;the Arab&#8211;Israeli war of 1973 and the Iranian revolution of 1979&#8212;that disrupted world oil supplies and sent oil prices skyrocketing. In fact, economists sometimes refer to the two slumps as &#8220;OPEC I&#8221; and &#8220;OPEC II,&#8221; after the Organization of Petroleum Exporting Countries, the world oil cartel. A third recession that began in 2007 and lasted until 2009 was at least partially exacerbated, if not at least partially caused, by a spike in oil prices.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p206" block_type="bx2-txt">So eight of eleven postwar recessions were purely the result of demand shocks, not supply shocks. The few supply-shock recessions, however, were the worst as measured by the unemployment rate. <link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16.xml#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-fig-19">Figure 16-15</link> shows the U.S. unemployment rate since 1948, with the dates of the 1973 Arab&#8211;Israeli war and the 1979 Iranian revolution marked on the graph. Some of the highest unemployment rates since World War II came after these big negative supply shocks.</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-fig-19" block_type="figure" numbered="true" number="16-15" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="right" width="medium" border="true"/>
<caption><link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16.xml#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-fig-19"><phrase block_type="fig-label"><phrase block_type="fig"><strong>FIGURE</strong></phrase></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_num"><strong>16-15</strong></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_title">Negative Supply Shocks Are Relatively Rare But Nasty</phrase></link></caption>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-img-26" alt="image" src="images/KrugESS4e_fig_16_15.jpg"/>
</figure>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p207" block_type="bx2-txt">There&#8217;s a reason the aftermath of a supply shock tends to be particularly severe for the economy: macroeconomic policy has a much harder time dealing with supply shocks than with demand shocks. Indeed, the reason the Federal Reserve was having a hard time in 2008, as described in the opening story, was the fact that in early 2008 the U.S. economy was in a recession partially caused by a supply shock (although it was also facing a demand shock). Next we&#8217;ll see why supply shocks present such a problem. </p>
</box>
<box title="Quick Review" numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-bx5-3" block_type="sr-1-h">
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-list-4" type="unordered" block_type="redbullet">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p208" block_type="sr1-bl">The <strong>AD&#8211;AS model</strong> is used to study economic fluctuations.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p209" block_type="sr1-bl"><strong>Short-run macroeconomic equilibrium</strong> occurs at the intersection of the short-run aggregate supply and aggregate demand curves. This determines the <strong>short-run equilibrium aggregate price level</strong> and the level of <strong>short-run equilibrium aggregate output.</strong></p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p210" block_type="sr1-bl">A <strong>demand shock,</strong> a shift of the <em>AD</em> curve, causes the aggregate price level and aggregate output to move in the same direction. A <strong>supply shock,</strong> a shift of the <em>SRAS</em> curve, causes them to move in opposite directions. <strong>Stagflation</strong> is the consequence of a negative supply shock.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p211" block_type="sr1-bl">A fall in nominal wages occurs in response to a <strong>recessionary gap,</strong> and a rise in nominal wages occurs in response to an <strong>inflationary gap.</strong> Both move the economy to <strong>long-run macroeconomic equilibrium,</strong> where the <em>AD, SRAS,</em> and <em>LRAS</em> curves intersect.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p212" block_type="sr1-bl">The <strong>output gap</strong> always tends toward zero because the economy is <strong>self-correcting</strong> in the long run.</p></li>
</list>
</box>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-bx6-3" block_type="sr2-h">
<box-metadata><box-title><phrase block_type="title">Check Your Understanding</phrase><phrase block_type="number">16-3</phrase></box-title></box-metadata>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-cyuquestion-4" block_type="q_cyu" number="1">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p213" block_type="sr2-nl-first"><phrase block_type="qnum">1.</phrase> Describe the short-run effects of each of the following shocks on the aggregate price level and on aggregate output.</p>
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-list-4" type="ordered" block_type="loweralpha">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p214" block_type="sr2-nl-lvl2">The government sharply increases the minimum wage, raising the wages of many workers.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p215" block_type="sr2-nl-lvl2">Solar energy firms launch a major program of investment spending.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p216" block_type="sr2-nl-lvl2">Congress raises taxes and cuts spending.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p217" block_type="sr2-nl-lvl2">Severe weather destroys crops around the world.</p></li>
</list>
</question>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-cyuquestion-5" block_type="q_cyu" number="1">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p218" block_type="sr2-nl-last"><phrase block_type="qnum">2.</phrase> A rise in productivity increases potential output, but some worry that demand for the additional output will be insufficient even in the long run. How would you respond?</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p219" block_type="sr2-nl-fn">Solutions appear at back of book.</p>
</question>
</box>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-sec1-004" block_type="h1" title="" chapter="ch16" numbered="true" level="1" print_page="464">
<section-metadata><section-title>Macroeconomic Policy</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p220" block_type="txt-ni">We&#8217;ve just seen that the economy is self-correcting in the long run: it will eventually trend back to potential output. Most macroeconomists believe, however, that the process of self-correction typically takes a decade or more. In particular, if aggregate output is below potential output, the economy can suffer an extended period of depressed aggregate output and high unemployment before it returns to normal.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p221" block_type="txt">This belief is the background to one of the most famous quotations in economics: John Maynard Keynes&#8217;s declaration, &#8220;In the long run we are all dead&#8221; (the remark is explained in the accompanying For Inquiring Minds).</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_465" block_type="page_start">465</p>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-bx3-4" block_type="bx3-t">
<box-metadata><box-title><strong>FOR INQUIRING MINDS</strong> &#124; Keynes and the Long Run<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-img-7a2" alt="image" src="images/world_view_icon.jpg"/></box-title></box-metadata>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-fig-20" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="right" width="medium" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-img-27" alt="image" src="images/KrugESS4e_16UN03.jpg"/>
<caption>Keynes focused the attention of economists of his day on the short run.</caption>
<asset_source>Bettmann/Corbis</asset_source>
</figure>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p222" block_type="bx-3-txt-ni">The British economist Sir John Maynard Keynes (1883&#8211;1946), probably more than any other single economist, created the modern field of macroeconomics. One of his most lasting contributions was a famous quote on the meaning of the long run.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p223" block_type="bx-3-txt">In 1923 Keynes published <em>A Tract on Monetary Reform,</em> a small book on the economic problems of Europe after World War I. In it he decried the tendency of many of his colleagues to focus on how things work out in the long run&#8212;as in the long-run macroeconomic equilibrium we have just analyzed&#8212;while ignoring the often very painful and possibly disastrous things that can happen along the way. Here&#8217;s a fuller version of the quote:</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p224" block_type="bx-3-txt-ni"><em>This long run is a misleading guide to current affairs. In the long run we are all dead. Economists set themselves too easy, too useless a task if in tempestuous seasons they can only tell us that when the storm is long past the sea is flat again.</em></p>
</box>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-exp3-21" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p225" block_type="mn-gl-def"><strong>Stabilization policy</strong> is the use of government policy to reduce the severity of recessions and rein in excessively strong expansions.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p226" block_type="txt">Economists usually interpret Keynes as having recommended that governments not wait for the economy to correct itself. Instead, it is argued by many economists, but not all, that the government should use monetary and fiscal policy to get the economy back to potential output in the aftermath of a shift of the aggregate demand curve. This is the rationale for an active <strong>stabilization policy,</strong> which is the use of government policy to reduce the severity of recessions and rein in excessively strong expansions.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p227" block_type="txt">Can stabilization policy improve the economy&#8217;s performance? If we reexamine <link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16.xml#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-fig-8">Figure 16-6</link>, the answer certainly appears to be yes. Under active stabilization policy, the U.S. economy returned to potential output in 1996 after an approximately five-year recessionary gap. Likewise, in 2001 it also returned to potential output after an approximately four-year inflationary gap. These periods are much shorter than the decade or more that economists believe it would take for the economy to self-correct in the absence of active stabilization policy. However, as we&#8217;ll see shortly, the ability to improve the economy&#8217;s performance is not always guaranteed. It depends on the kinds of shocks the economy faces.</p>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-sec2-012" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="ch16" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="465">
<section-metadata><section-title>Policy in the Face of Demand Shocks</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p228" block_type="txt-ni">Imagine that the economy experiences a negative demand shock, like the one shown in <link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16.xml#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-fig-16">Figure 16-13</link>. As we&#8217;ve discussed, monetary and fiscal policy shift the aggregate demand curve. If policy makers react quickly to the fall in aggregate demand, they can use monetary or fiscal policy to shift the aggregate demand curve back to the right. And if policy were able to perfectly anticipate shifts of the aggregate demand curve, it could short-circuit the whole process shown in <link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16.xml#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-fig-16">Figure 16-13</link>. Instead of going through a period of low aggregate output and falling prices, the government could manage the economy so that it would stay at <em>E</em><sub>1</sub>.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p229" block_type="txt">Why might a policy that short-circuits the adjustment shown in <link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16.xml#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-fig-16">Figure 16-13</link> and maintains the economy at its original equilibrium be desirable? For two reasons. First, the temporary fall in aggregate output that would happen without policy intervention is a bad thing, particularly because such a decline is associated with high unemployment. Second, as we explained in <link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch14.xml">Chapter 14</link>, <em>price stability</em> is generally regarded as a desirable goal. So preventing deflation&#8212;a fall in the aggregate price level&#8212;is a good thing.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p230" block_type="txt">Does this mean that policy makers should always act to offset declines in aggregate demand? Not necessarily. Some policy measures to increase aggregate demand, especially those that increase budget deficits, may have long-term costs in terms of lower long-run growth. Furthermore, in the real world policy makers aren&#8217;t perfectly informed, and the effects of their policies aren&#8217;t perfectly predictable. This creates the danger that stabilization policy will do more harm than good; that is, attempts to stabilize the economy may end up creating more instability. Despite these qualifications, most economists believe that a good case can be made for using macroeconomic policy to offset major negative shocks to the <em>AD</em> curve.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_466" block_type="page_start">466</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p231" block_type="txt">Should policy makers also try to offset positive shocks to aggregate demand? It may not seem obvious that they should. After all, even though inflation may be a bad thing, isn&#8217;t more output and lower unemployment a good thing? Not necessarily. Most economists now believe that any short-run gains from an inflationary gap must be paid back later. So policy makers today usually try to offset positive as well as negative demand shocks. For reasons we&#8217;ll explain in <link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch19.xml">Chapter 19</link>, attempts to eliminate recessionary gaps and inflationary gaps usually rely on monetary rather than fiscal policy. In 2007 and 2008 the Federal Reserve sharply cut interest rates in an attempt to head off a rising recessionary gap; earlier in the decade, when the U.S. economy seemed headed for an inflationary gap, it raised interest rates to generate the opposite effect.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p232" block_type="txt">But how should macroeconomic policy respond to supply shocks?</p>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-sec2-013" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="ch16" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="466">
<section-metadata><section-title>Responding to Supply Shocks</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p233" block_type="txt-ni">We&#8217;ve now come full circle to the story that began this chapter. We can now explain why FOMC committee members dread stagflation.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p234" block_type="txt">In panel (a) of <link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16.xml#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-fig-13">Figure 16-11</link> we showed the effects of a negative supply shock: in the short run such a shock leads to lower aggregate output but a higher aggregate price level. As we&#8217;ve noted, policy makers can respond to a negative <em>demand</em> shock by using monetary and fiscal policy to return aggregate demand to its original level. But what can or should they do about a negative <em>supply</em> shock?</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p235" block_type="txt">In contrast to the aggregate demand curve, there are no easy policies that shift the short-run aggregate supply curve. That is, there is no government policy that can easily affect producers&#8217; profitability and so compensate for shifts of the short-run aggregate supply curve. So the policy response to a negative supply shock cannot aim to simply push the curve that shifted back to its original position. </p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p236" block_type="txt">And if you consider using monetary or fiscal policy to shift the aggregate demand curve in response to a supply shock, the right response isn&#8217;t obvious. Two bad things are happening simultaneously: a fall in aggregate output, leading to a rise in unemployment, <em>and</em> a rise in the aggregate price level. Any policy that shifts the aggregate demand curve helps one problem only by making the other worse. If the government acts to increase aggregate demand and limit the rise in unemployment, it reduces the decline in output but causes even more inflation. If it acts to reduce aggregate demand, it curbs inflation but causes a further rise in unemployment.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p237" block_type="txt">It&#8217;s a trade-off with no good answer. In the end, the United States and other economically advanced nations suffering from the supply shocks of the 1970s eventually chose to stabilize prices even at the cost of higher unemployment. But being an economic policy maker in the 1970s, or in early 2008, meant facing even harder choices than usual.</p>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-bx2-4" block_type="bx-2-h">
<box-metadata><box-title><phrase block_type="title">ECONOMICS</phrase><phrase block_type="number"><em>in Action</em></phrase></box-title></box-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p238" block_type="bx-2-t"><strong>Is Stabilization Policy Stabilizing?</strong></p>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-exp2-5" block_type="mn2">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p239" block_type="fg1-t"><image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-img-28" alt="image" src="images/launchpad_logo_cmyk.jpg"/> &#124; interactive activity</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p240" block_type="bx2-first"><phrase block_type="dropcap">W</phrase>e&#8217;ve described the theoretical rationale for stabilization policy as a way of responding to demand shocks. But does stabilization policy actually stabilize the economy? One way we might try to answer this question is to look at the long-term historical record. Before World War II, the U.S. government didn&#8217;t really have a stabilization policy, largely because macroeconomics as we know it didn&#8217;t exist, and there was no consensus about what to do. Since World War II, and especially since 1960, active stabilization policy has become standard practice.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_467" block_type="page_start">467</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p241" block_type="bx2-txt">So here&#8217;s the question: has the economy actually become more stable since the government began trying to stabilize it? The answer is a qualified yes. It&#8217;s qualified for two reasons. One is that data from the pre&#8211;World War II era are less reliable than more modern data. The other is that the severe and protracted slump that began in 2007 has shaken confidence in the effectiveness of government policy. Still, there seems to have been a reduction in the size of fluctuations.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p242" block_type="bx2-txt"><link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16.xml#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-fig-21">Figure 16-16</link> shows the number of unemployed as a percentage of the nonfarm labor force since 1890. (We focus on nonfarm workers because farmers, though they often suffer economic hardship, are rarely reported as unemployed.) Even ignoring the huge spike in unemployment during the Great Depression, unemployment seems to have varied a lot more before World War II than after. It&#8217;s also worth noticing that the peaks in postwar unemployment, in 1975, 1982, and to some extent in 2010 (as described in the earlier Global Comparison), corresponded to major supply shocks&#8212;the kind of shock for which stabilization policy has no good answer.</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-fig-21" block_type="figure" numbered="true" number="16-16" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="right" width="medium" border="true"/>
<caption><link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16.xml#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-fig-21"><phrase block_type="fig-label"><phrase block_type="fig"><strong>FIGURE</strong></phrase></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_num"><strong>16-16</strong></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_title">Has Stabilization Policy Been Stabilizing? </phrase></link></caption>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-img-29" alt="image" src="images/KrugESS4e_fig_16_16.jpg"/>
</figure>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p243" block_type="bx2-txt">It&#8217;s possible that the greater stability of the economy reflects good luck rather than policy. But on the face of it, the evidence suggests that stabilization policy is indeed stabilizing.</p>
</box>
<box title="Quick Review" numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-bx5-4" block_type="sr-1-h">
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-list-5" type="unordered" block_type="redbullet">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p244" block_type="sr1-bl"><strong>Stabilization policy</strong> is the use of fiscal or monetary policy to offset demand shocks. There can be drawbacks, however. Such policies may lead to a long-term rise in the budget deficit and lower long-run growth because of crowding out. And, due to incorrect predictions, a misguided policy can increase economic instability.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p245" block_type="sr1-bl">Negative supply shocks pose a policy dilemma because fighting the slump in aggregate output worsens inflation and fighting inflation worsens the slump.</p></li>
</list>
</box>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-bx6-4" block_type="sr2-h">
<box-metadata><box-title><phrase block_type="title">Check Your Understanding</phrase><phrase block_type="number">16-4</phrase></box-title></box-metadata>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-cyuquestion-6" block_type="q_cyu" number="1">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p246" block_type="sr2-nl-first"><phrase block_type="qnum">1.</phrase> Suppose someone says, &#8220;Using monetary or fiscal policy to pump up the economy is counterproductive&#8212;you get a brief high, but then you have the pain of inflation.&#8221;</p>
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-list-5" type="ordered" block_type="loweralpha">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p247" block_type="sr2-nl-lvl2">Explain what this means in terms of the <em>AD&#8211;AS</em> model.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p248" block_type="sr2-nl-lvl2">Is this a valid argument against stabilization policy? Why or why not?</p></li>
</list>
</question>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-cyuquestion-7" block_type="q_cyu" number="1">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p249" block_type="sr2-nl-last"><phrase block_type="qnum">2.</phrase> In 2008, in the aftermath of the collapse of the housing bubble and a sharp rise in the price of commodities, particularly oil, there was much internal disagreement within the Fed about how to respond, with some advocating lowering interest rates and others contending that this would set off a rise in inflation. Explain the reasoning behind each one of these views in terms of the <em>AD</em>&#8211;<em>AS</em> model.</p>
</question>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p250" block_type="sr2-nl-fn">Solutions appear at back of book.</p>
</box>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-sec1-6" block_type="solved_problem" title="" chapter="16" numbered="true" level="1" print_page="467">
<section-metadata><section-title>Solved Problem</section-title></section-metadata>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-bx7-1" block_type="sum-h">
<box-metadata><box-title><phrase block_type="gc1">SOLVED PROBLEM</phrase> <phrase block_type="gc2">A Shocking Analysis</phrase></box-title></box-metadata>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-exp2-6" block_type="mn2">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p251" block_type="fg1-t"><image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-solution-img-1" alt="image" src="images/launchpad_logo_cmyk.jpg"/> for interactive tutorials with step-by-step guidance on how to solve problems</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p252" block_type="wio-txt-ni">During the financial crisis in autumn 2008, the financial system delivered a sobering shock to the economy when the stock market lost about half of its value. Soon afterward, consumer spending came to a screeching halt. Within six months of the crash, GDP fell by 2.5&#37; and the price level fell by 2.8&#37;. Show how an analysis of aggregate demand and aggregate supply could have predicted this short-run effect on aggregate output and the aggregate price level. Assuming no government intervention, what would you have predicted in the long run?</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_468" block_type="page_start">468</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p253" block_type="sp-stp-txt"><phrase block_type="step"><phrase block_type="step-green">STEP</phrase> &#124; <phrase block_type="step-green">1</phrase></phrase> <phrase block_type="step-title"><strong>Begin by drawing and labeling the aggregate demand curve. Then draw and label the short-run aggregate supply curve Next, find the initial equilibrium price and output levels and label them on your graph as well.</strong>
<phrase block_type="step-subtext">Read pages 457&#8211;458 and review <link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16.xml#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-fig-11">Figure 16-9</link>.</phrase></phrase></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p254" block_type="wio-txt-ni">The aggregate demand curve and the short-run aggregate supply curve are shown in the following diagram. The initial equilibrium point is labeled <em>E</em><sub>1</sub>, the initial price level is labeled <em>P</em><sub>1</sub>, and the initial output level is labeled <em>Y</em><sub>1</sub>.</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-fig-22" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-img-30" alt="image" src="images/KrugESS4e_16UN04.jpg"/>
</figure>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p255" block_type="sp-stp-txt"><phrase block_type="step"><phrase block_type="step-green">STEP</phrase></phrase> &#124; <phrase block_type="step-green">2</phrase> <phrase block_type="step-title"><strong>Using your graph from Step 1, analyze the short-run effect of the stock market fall on aggregate demand and aggregate supply by drawing a new curve representing aggregate demand after the stock market fall.</strong>
<phrase block_type="step-subtext">Read page 458 and review <link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16.xml#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-fig-12">Figure 16-10</link>, panel (a).</phrase></phrase></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p256" block_type="wio-txt-ni">A decrease in household wealth will reduce consumer spending. Beginning at the equilibrium point, <em>E</em><sub>1</sub> in the diagram below, the aggregate demand curve will shift from <em>AD</em><sub>1</sub> to <em>AD</em><sub>2</sub>. The economy will be in short-run macroeconomic equilibrium at point <em>E</em><sub>2</sub>. The aggregate price level will be lower than at <em>P</em><sub>1</sub>, and aggregate output will be lower than output at the original equilibrium point.</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-fig-23" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-img-31" alt="image" src="images/KrugESS4e_16UN05.jpg"/>
</figure>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p257" block_type="sp-stp-txt"><phrase block_type="step"><phrase block_type="step-green">STEP</phrase> &#124; <phrase block_type="step-green">3</phrase></phrase> <phrase block_type="step-title"><strong>Draw the long-run aggregate supply curve through the initial equilibrium point <em>E</em><sub>1</sub>, and label the recessionary gap.</strong>
<phrase block_type="step-subtext">Read pages 460&#8211;462 and review <link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16.xml#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-fig-15">Figures 16-12</link> and <link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16.xml#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-fig-16">16-13</link>.</phrase></phrase></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p258" block_type="wio-txt-ni">The long-run aggregate supply curve is drawn in the following diagram. The economy now faces a recessionary gap between <em>Y</em><sub>1</sub> and <em>Y</em><sub>2</sub>.</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-fig-24" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-img-32" alt="image" src="images/KrugESS4e_16UN06.jpg"/>
</figure>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p259" block_type="sp-stp-txt"><phrase block_type="step"><phrase block_type="step-green">STEP</phrase></phrase> &#124; <phrase block_type="step-green">4</phrase> <phrase block_type="step-title"><strong>What would you predict in the long run?</strong>
<phrase block_type="step-subtext">Read pages 460&#8211;462 and review <link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16.xml#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-fig-16">Figure 16-13</link>.</phrase></phrase></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p260" block_type="wio-txt-ni">As wage contracts are renegotiated, nominal wages will fall and the short-run aggregate supply curve will shift gradually to the right over time until it reaches <em>SRAS</em><sub>2</sub> and intersects <em>AD</em><sub>2</sub> at point <em>E</em><sub>3</sub>. At <em>E</em><sub>3</sub>, the economy is back at its potential output but at a much lower aggregate price level, as shown in the following diagram.</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-fig-25" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-img-33" alt="image" src="images/KrugESS4e_16UN07.jpg"/>
</figure>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_469" block_type="page_start">469</p>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-sec1-005" block_type="cr-que-t" title="" chapter="ch16" numbered="true" level="1" print_page="469">
<section-metadata><section-title>SUMMARY</section-title></section-metadata>
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-list-6" type="ordered" block_type="numbered">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p261" block_type="sum-nl">The <strong>aggregate demand curve</strong> shows the relationship between the aggregate price level and the quantity of aggregate output demanded.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p262" block_type="sum-nl">The aggregate demand curve is downward sloping for two reasons. The first is the <strong>wealth effect of a change in the aggregate price level&#8212;</strong>a higher aggregate price level reduces the purchasing power of households&#8217; wealth and reduces consumer spending. The second is the <strong>interest rate effect of a change in the aggregate price level&#8212;</strong>a higher aggregate price level reduces the purchasing power of households&#8217; and firms&#8217; money holdings, leading to a rise in interest rates and a fall in investment spending and consumer spending.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p263" block_type="sum-nl">The aggregate demand curve shifts because of changes in expectations, changes in wealth not due to changes in the aggregate price level, and the effect of the size of the existing stock of physical capital. Policy makers can use fiscal policy and monetary policy to shift the aggregate demand curve.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p264" block_type="sum-nl">The <strong>aggregate supply curve</strong> shows the relationship between the aggregate price level and the quantity of aggregate output supplied.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p265" block_type="sum-nl">The <strong>short-run aggregate supply curve</strong> is upward sloping because <strong>nominal wages</strong> are <strong>sticky</strong> in the short run: a higher aggregate price level leads to higher profit per unit of output and increased aggregate output in the short run.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p266" block_type="sum-nl">Changes in commodity prices, nominal wages, and productivity lead to changes in producers&#8217; profits and shift the short-run aggregate supply curve.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p267" block_type="sum-nl">In the long run, all prices, including nominal wages, are flexible and the economy produces at its <strong>potential output.</strong> If actual aggregate output exceeds potential output, nominal wages will eventually rise in response to low unemployment and aggregate output will fall. If potential output exceeds actual aggregate output, nominal wages will eventually fall in response to high unemployment and aggregate output will rise. So the <strong>long-run aggregate supply curve</strong> is vertical at potential output.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p268" block_type="sum-nl">In the <strong><em>AD&#8211;AS</em> model,</strong> the intersection of the short-run aggregate supply curve and the aggregate demand curve is the point of <strong>short-run macroeconomic equilibrium.</strong> It determines the <strong>short-run equilibrium aggregate price level</strong> and the level of <strong>short-run equilibrium aggregate output.</strong></p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p269" block_type="sum-nl">Economic fluctuations occur because of a shift of the aggregate demand curve (a <em>demand shock</em>) or the short-run aggregate supply curve (a <em>supply shock</em>). A <strong>demand shock</strong> causes the aggregate price level and aggregate output to move in the same direction as the economy moves along the short-run aggregate supply curve. A <strong>supply shock</strong> causes them to move in opposite directions as the economy moves along the aggregate demand curve. A particularly nasty occurrence is <strong>stagflation&#8212;</strong>inflation and falling aggregate output&#8212;which is caused by a negative supply shock.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p270" block_type="sum-nl">Demand shocks have only short-run effects on aggregate output because the economy is <strong>self-correcting</strong> in the long run. In a <strong>recessionary gap,</strong> an eventual fall in nominal wages moves the economy to <strong>long-run macroeconomic equilibrium,</strong> where aggregate output is equal to potential output. In an <strong>inflationary gap,</strong> an eventual rise in nominal wages moves the economy to long-run macroeconomic equilibrium. We can use the <strong>output gap,</strong> the percentage difference between actual aggregate output and potential output, to summarize how the economy responds to recessionary and inflationary gaps. Because the economy tends to be self-correcting in the long run, the output gap always tends toward zero.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p271" block_type="sum-nl">The high cost&#8212;in terms of unemployment&#8212;of a recessionary gap and the future adverse consequences of an inflationary gap lead many economists to advocate active <strong>stabilization policy:</strong> using fiscal or monetary policy to offset demand shocks. There can be drawbacks, however, because such policies may contribute to a long-term rise in the budget deficit and crowding out of private investment, leading to lower long-run growth. Also, poorly timed policies can increase economic instability.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p272" block_type="sum-nl">Negative supply shocks pose a policy dilemma: a policy that counteracts the fall in aggregate output by increasing aggregate demand will lead to higher inflation, but a policy that counteracts inflation by reducing aggregate demand will deepen the output slump.</p></li>
</list>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-sec1-006" block_type="cr-kt-t" title="" chapter="ch16" numbered="true" level="1" print_page="469">
<section-metadata><section-title>KEY TERMS</section-title></section-metadata>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-exp2-7" block_type="mn2">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p273" block_type="fg1-t"><image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-img-34" alt="image" src="images/launchpad_logo_cmyk.jpg"/> &#124; interactive activity</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p274" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16.xml#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p23">Aggregate demand curve, p. 440</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p275" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16.xml#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p35">Wealth effect of a change in the aggregate price level, p. 442</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p276" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16.xml#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p42">Interest rate effect of a change in the aggregate price level, p. 442</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p277" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16.xml#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p78">Aggregate supply curve, p. 447</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p278" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16.xml#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p85">Nominal wage, p. 447</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p279" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16.xml#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p87">Sticky wages, p. 447</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p280" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16.xml#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p94">Short-run aggregate supply curve, p. 449</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p281" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16.xml#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p118">Long-run aggregate supply curve, p. 452</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p282" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16.xml#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p120">Potential output, p. 453</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p283" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16.xml#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p156"><em>AD&#8211;AS</em> model, p. 457</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p284" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16.xml#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p160">Short-run macroeconomic equilibrium, p. 457</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p285" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16.xml#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p160">Short-run equilibrium aggregate price level, p. 457</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p286" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16.xml#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p160">Short-run equilibrium aggregate output, p. 457</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p287" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16.xml#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p166">Demand shock, p. 458</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p288" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16.xml#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p170">Supply shock, p. 458</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p289" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16.xml#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p174">Stagflation, p. 459</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p290" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16.xml#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p183">Long-run macroeconomic equilibrium, p. 460</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p291" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16.xml#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p187">Recessionary gap, p. 462</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p292" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16.xml#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p191">Inflationary gap, p. 462</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p293" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16.xml#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p197">Output gap, p. 463</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p294" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16.xml#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p200">Self-correcting, p. 463</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p295" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16.xml#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p226">Stabilization policy, p. 465</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_470" block_type="page_start">470</p>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-sec1-007" block_type="cr-que-t" title="" chapter="ch16" numbered="true" level="1" print_page="470">
<section-metadata><section-title>PROBLEMS</section-title></section-metadata>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-question-1" block_type="q_prob" number="1">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p296" block_type="cr-que-nl-first"><phrase block_type="qnum">1.</phrase> A fall in the value of the dollar against other currencies makes U.S. final goods and services cheaper to foreigners even though the U.S. aggregate price level stays the same. As a result, foreigners demand more American aggregate output. Your study partner says that this represents a movement down the aggregate demand curve because foreigners are demanding more in response to a lower price. You, however, insist that this represents a rightward shift of the aggregate demand curve. Who is right? Explain.</p>
</question>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-question-2" block_type="q_prob" number="2">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p297" block_type="cr-que-nl-mid"><phrase block_type="qnum">2.</phrase> Your study partner is confused by the upward-sloping short-run aggregate supply curve and the vertical long-run aggregate supply curve. How would you explain this?</p>
</question>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-question-3" block_type="q_prob" number="3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p298" block_type="cr-que-nl-mid"><phrase block_type="qnum">3.</phrase> Suppose that in Wageland all workers sign annual wage contracts each year on January 1. No matter what happens to prices of final goods and services during the year, all workers earn the wage specified in their annual contract. This year, prices of final goods and services fall unexpectedly after the contracts are signed. Answer the following questions using a diagram and assume that the economy starts at potential output.</p>
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-list-7" type="ordered" block_type="loweralpha">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p299" block_type="cr-que-ans-first">In the short run, how will the quantity of aggregate output supplied respond to the fall in prices?</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p300" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">What will happen when firms and workers renegotiate their wages?</p></li>
</list>
</question>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-question-4" block_type="q_prob" number="4">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p301" block_type="cr-que-nl-first"><phrase block_type="qnum">4.</phrase> The economy is at point <em>A</em> in the accompanying diagram. Suppose that the aggregate price level rises from <em>P</em><sub>1</sub> to <em>P</em><sub>2</sub>. How will aggregate supply adjust in the short run and in the long run to the increase in the aggregate price level? Illustrate with a diagram.</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-fig-26" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="right" width="medium" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-img-35" alt="image" src="images/KrugESS4e_16UN08.jpg"/>
</figure>
</question>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-question-5" block_type="q_prob" number="5">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p302" block_type="cr-que-nl-first"><phrase block_type="qnum">5.</phrase> Suppose that all households hold all their wealth in assets that automatically rise in value when the aggregate price level rises (an example of this is what is called an &#8220;inflation-indexed bond&#8221;&#8212;a bond whose interest rate, among other things, changes one-for-one with the inflation rate). What happens to the wealth effect of a change in the aggregate price level as a result of this allocation of assets? What happens to the slope of the aggregate demand curve? Will it still slope downward? Explain.</p>
</question>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-question-6" block_type="q_prob" number="6">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p303" block_type="cr-que-nl-mid"><phrase block_type="qnum">6.</phrase> Suppose that the economy is currently at potential output. Also suppose that you are an economic policy maker and that a college economics student asks you to rank, if possible, your most preferred to least preferred type of shock: positive demand shock, negative demand shock, positive supply shock, negative supply shock. How would you rank them and why?</p>
</question>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-question-7" block_type="q_prob" number="7">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p304" block_type="cr-que-nl-mid"><phrase block_type="qnum">7.</phrase> Explain whether the following government policies affect the aggregate demand curve or the short-run aggregate supply curve and how.</p>
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-list-8" type="ordered" block_type="loweralpha">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p305" block_type="cr-que-ans-first">The government reduces the minimum nominal wage.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p306" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">The government increases Temporary Assistance to Needy Families (TANF) payments, government transfers to families with dependent children.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p307" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">To reduce the budget deficit, the government announces that households will pay much higher taxes beginning next year.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p308" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">The government reduces military spending.</p></li>
</list>
</question>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-question-8" block_type="q_prob" number="8">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p309" block_type="cr-que-nl-mid"><phrase block_type="qnum">8.</phrase> In Wageland, all workers sign an annual wage contract each year on January 1. In late January, a new computer operating system is introduced that increases labor productivity dramatically. Explain how Wageland will move from one short-run macroeconomic equilibrium to another. Illustrate with a diagram.</p>
</question>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-question-9" block_type="q_prob" number="9">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p310" block_type="cr-que-nl-mid"><phrase block_type="qnum">9.</phrase> The Conference Board publishes the Consumer Confidence Index (CCI) every month based on a survey of 5,000 representative U.S. households. It is used by many economists to track the state of the economy. A press release by the Board on June 28, 2011, stated: &#8220;The Conference Board Consumer Confidence Index, which had declined in May, decreased again in June. The Index now stands at 58.5 (1985 = 100), down from 61.7 in May.&#8221;</p>
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-list-9" type="ordered" block_type="loweralpha">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p311" block_type="cr-que-ans2-first">As an economist, is this news encouraging for economic growth?</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p312" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">Explain your answer to part a with the help of the <em>AD&#8211;AS</em> model. Draw a typical diagram showing two equilibrium points (<em>E</em><sub>1</sub>) and (<em>E</em><sub>2</sub>). Label the vertical axis &#8220;Aggregate price level&#8221; and the horizontal axis &#8220;Real GDP.&#8221; Assume that all other major macroeconomic factors remain unchanged.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p313" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">How should the government respond to this news? What are some policy measures that could be used to help neutralize the effect of falling consumer confidence?</p></li>
</list>
</question>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-question-10" block_type="q_prob" number="10">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p314" block_type="cr-que-nl-mid"><phrase block_type="qnum">10.</phrase> There were two major shocks to the U.S. economy in 2007, leading to the severe recession of 2007&#8211;2009. One shock was related to oil prices; the other was the slump in the housing market. This question analyzes the effect of these two shocks on GDP using the <em>AD&#8211;AS</em> framework.</p>
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-list-10" type="ordered" block_type="loweralpha">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p315" block_type="cr-que-ans-first">Draw typical aggregate demand and short-run aggregate supply curves. Label the horizontal axis &#8220;Real GDP&#8221; and the vertical axis &#8220;Aggregate price level.&#8221; Label the equilibrium point <em>E</em><sub>1</sub>, the equilibrium quantity <em>Y</em><sub>1</sub>, and equilibrium price <em>P</em><sub>1</sub>.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p316" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">Data taken from the Department of Energy indicate that the average price of crude oil in the world increased from &#36;54.63 per barrel on January 5, 2007, to &#36;92.93 on December 28, 2007. Would an increase in oil prices cause a demand shock or a supply shock? Redraw the diagram from part a to illustrate the effect of this shock by shifting the appropriate curve.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p317" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">The Housing Price Index, published by the Office of Federal Housing Enterprise Oversight, calculates that U.S<em>.</em> home prices fell by an average of 3.0&#37; in the 12 months between January 2007 and January 2008. Would the fall in home prices cause a supply shock or demand shock? Redraw the diagram from part b to illustrate the effect of this shock by shifting the appropriate curve. Label the new equilibrium point <em>E</em><sub>3</sub>, the equilibrium quantity <em>Y</em><sub>3</sub>, and equilibrium price <em>P</em><sub>3</sub>.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p318" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">Compare the equilibrium points <em>E</em><sub>1</sub> and <em>E</em><sub>3</sub> in your diagram for part c. What was the effect of the two shocks on real GDP and the aggregate price level (increase, decrease, or indeterminate)?</p></li>
</list>
</question>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_471" block_type="page_start">471</p>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-question-11" block_type="q_prob" number="11">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p319" block_type="cr-que-nl-mid"><phrase block_type="qnum">11.</phrase> Using aggregate demand, short-run aggregate supply, and long-run aggregate supply curves, explain the process by which each of the following economic events will move the economy from one long-run macroeconomic equilibrium to another. Illustrate with diagrams. In each case, what are the short-run and long-run effects on the aggregate price level and aggregate output?</p>
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-list-11" type="ordered" block_type="loweralpha">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p320" block_type="cr-que-ans-first">There is a decrease in households&#8217; wealth due to a decline in the stock market.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p321" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">The government lowers taxes, leaving households with more disposable income, with no corresponding reduction in government purchases.</p></li>
</list>
</question>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-question-12" block_type="q_prob" number="12">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p322" block_type="cr-que-nl-mid"><phrase block_type="qnum">12.</phrase> Using aggregate demand, short-run aggregate supply, and long-run aggregate supply curves, explain the process by which each of the following government policies will move the economy from one long-run macroeconomic equilibrium to another. Illustrate with diagrams. In each case, what are the short-run and long-run effects on the aggregate price level and aggregate output?</p>
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-list-12" type="ordered" block_type="loweralpha">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p323" block_type="cr-que-ans-first">There is an increase in taxes on households.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p324" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">There is an increase in the quantity of money.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p325" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">There is an increase in government spending.</p></li>
</list>
</question>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-question-13" block_type="q_prob" number="13">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p326" block_type="cr-que-nl-mid"><phrase block_type="qnum">13.</phrase> The economy is in short-run macroeconomic equilibrium at point <em>E</em><sub>1</sub> in the accompanying diagram. Based on the diagram, answer the following questions.</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-fig-27" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="right" width="medium" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-img-36" alt="image" src="images/KrugESS4e_16UN09.jpg"/>
</figure>
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-list-13" type="ordered" block_type="loweralpha">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p327" block_type="cr-que-ans-first">Is the economy facing an inflationary or a recessionary gap?</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p328" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">What policies can the government implement that might bring the economy back to long-run macroeconomic equilibrium? Illustrate with a diagram.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p329" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">If the government did not intervene to close this gap, would the economy return to long-run macroeconomic equilibrium? Explain and illustrate with a diagram.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p330" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">What are the advantages and disadvantages of the government implementing policies to close the gap?</p></li>
</list>
</question>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-question-14" block_type="q_prob" number="14">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p331" block_type="cr-que-nl-mid"><phrase block_type="qnum">14.</phrase> In the accompanying diagram, the economy is in long-run macroeconomic equilibrium at point <em>E</em><sub>1</sub> when an oil shock shifts the short-run aggregate supply curve to <em>SRAS</em><sub>2</sub>. Based on the diagram, answer the following questions.</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-fig-28" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="right" width="medium" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-img-37" alt="image" src="images/KrugESS4e_16UN10.jpg"/>
</figure>
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-list-14" type="ordered" block_type="loweralpha">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p332" block_type="cr-que-ans-first">How do the aggregate price level and aggregate output change in the short run as a result of the oil shock? What is this phenomenon known as?</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p333" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">What fiscal or monetary policies can the government use to address the effects of the supply shock? Use a diagram that shows the effect of policies chosen to address the change in real GDP. Use another diagram to show the effect of policies chosen to address the change in the aggregate price level.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p334" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">Why do supply shocks present a dilemma for government policy makers?</p></li>
</list>
</question>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-question-15" block_type="q_prob" number="15">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p335" block_type="cr-que-nl-mid"><phrase block_type="qnum">15.</phrase> The late 1990s in the United States were characterized by substantial economic growth with low inflation; that is, real GDP increased with little, if any, increase in the aggregate price level. Explain this experience using aggregate demand and aggregate supply curves. Illustrate with a diagram.</p>
</question>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_472" block_type="page_start">472</p>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-sec1-008" block_type="sum-h" title="" chapter="ch16" numbered="true" level="1" print_page="472">
<section-metadata><section-title>WORK IT OUT</section-title></section-metadata>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-exp2-8" block_type="mn2">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p336" block_type="fg1-t"><image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-img-38" alt="image" src="images/launchpad_logo_cmyk.jpg"/> &#124; interactive activity</p>
</box>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-question-16" block_type="q_prob" number="16">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p337" block_type="cr-wio-nl-first"><phrase block_type="qnum">16.</phrase> In each of the following cases, in the short run, determine whether the events cause a shift of a curve or a movement along a curve. Determine which curve is involved and the direction of the change.</p>
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-list-15" type="ordered" block_type="loweralpha">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p338" block_type="cr-wio-ans-first">As a result of an increase in the value of the dollar in relation to other currencies, American producers now pay less in dollar terms for foreign steel, a major commodity used in production.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p339" block_type="cr-wio-ans-mid">An increase in the quantity of money by the Federal Reserve increases the quantity of money that people wish to lend, lowering interest rates.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p340" block_type="cr-wio-ans-mid">Greater union activity leads to higher nominal wages.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p341" block_type="cr-wio-ans-last">A fall in the aggregate price level increases the purchasing power of households&#8217; and firms&#8217; money holdings. As a result, they borrow less and lend more.</p></li>
</list>
</question>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-sec1-8" block_type="business_case" title="" chapter="16" numbered="true" level="1" print_page="473">
<section-metadata><section-title>Business Case</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_473" block_type="page_start">473</p>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-bx5-5" block_type="bcbx5-h">
<box-metadata><box-title><phrase block_type="bc1">BUSINESS</phrase> <phrase block_type="bc2">CASE</phrase><strong>How Boeing Got Better</strong></box-title></box-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p343" block_type="bx5-txt-ni"><phrase block_type="dropcap">W</phrase>hen we think about innovation and technological progress, we tend to focus on the big, dramatic changes: cars replacing horses and buggies, electric lightbulbs replacing gaslights, computers replacing adding machines and typewriters. A lot of progress, however, is incremental and almost invisible to most people&#8212;yet such unglamorous change can have huge effects over time. Consider, for example, the progress of jet travel, as illustrated by the history of Boeing Corporation.</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-fig-29" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="right" width="medium" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-img-39" alt="image" src="images/KrugESS4e_16UN11.jpg"/>
<asset_source>Chris Edwards/Woodys Aero Images</asset_source>
</figure>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p344" block_type="bx5-txt">The Boeing 707, introduced in 1957, was the first commercially successful jetliner, and for a number of years it ruled the skies. When the Beatles made their famous 1964 arrival in America, it was a 707 that brought them there. So what did the 707 look like? What&#8217;s striking about it, from a modern perspective, is how ordinary it appears. Basically, it looks like a jet airliner. If you walked past one today, and nobody told you it was an antique, you probably wouldn&#8217;t notice; 50-year old jets aren&#8217;t nearly as different on the outside from their contemporary descendants.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p345" block_type="bx5-txt">Furthermore, the visible performance of modern jets, like the Boeing 777 or the even more advanced 787, isn&#8217;t that much better than that of the old 707. They only fly slightly faster; once you take extra security and flight delays into account, traveling from London to New York probably takes more time now than in 1964. It&#8217;s nice to have a selection of movies (although there may not be anything you want to watch), and business-class travelers now get flatbed seats that make sleeping easier. Still, all of this seems fairly marginal.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p346" block_type="bx5-txt">Yet Boeing&#8217;s modern jets (and those of its main competitor, Airbus) are vastly more efficient than jets half a century ago&#8212;so much so that average air fares, adjusted for inflation, are only about a third what they were in 1960. What changed?</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p347" block_type="bx5-txt">The answer is, things passengers can&#8217;t see. Most important, there has been a drastic improvement in fuel efficiency, with modern planes using less than a third as much fuel per passenger-mile than their ancestors. Behind this improvement, in turn, lie fundamental changes in engine design (high-bypass engines that direct most of their intake around the combustion chamber rather than through it), small but important improvements in aerodynamics, and the use of new materials to make airframes much lighter.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p348" block_type="bx5-txt">The moral is that the technological progress that drives growth is much broader and more powerful than meets the eye. Even when things look more or less the same, there is often enormous change beneath the surface.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p349" block_type="bx5-nl-h"><strong>QUESTIONS FOR THOUGHT</strong></p>
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-list-16" type="ordered" block_type="numbered">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p350" block_type="bx5-nl">A modern jet airliner does pretty much the same thing as an airliner from the 1960s: it gets you there from here, in about the same time. Where&#8217;s the technological progress?</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p351" block_type="bx5-nl">Do scientific advances play any role in the progress we&#8217;ve described? Explain.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p352" block_type="bx5-nl">Some travelers complain that the flight experience has gone downhill. Does this refute the claim of technological progress?</p></li>
</list>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_474" block_type="page_start">474</p>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-bx5-6" block_type="bcbx5-h">
<box-metadata><box-title><image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-img-7a2" alt="image" src="images/world_view_icon.jpg"/><phrase block_type="bc1">BUSINESS</phrase> <phrase block_type="bc2">CASE</phrase> <strong>Slow Steaming</strong></box-title></box-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p353" block_type="bx5-txt-ni"><phrase block_type="dropcap">T</phrase>he global economic slump of 2008&#8211;2009 took a toll on almost everyone. By 2011, however, the acute crisis was receding in the rearview mirror. Unemployment remained high in wealthy countries, but the world economy as a whole was growing fairly fast, and so were corporate profits.</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-fig-30" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-img-40" alt="image" src="images/KrugESS4e_16UN12.jpg"/>
<asset_source>Peter Titmuss/Alamy</asset_source>
</figure>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p354" block_type="bx5-txt">One industry that wasn&#8217;t doing well, however, was shipping. A 2012 report from the Boston Consulting Group declared that executives in the container-shipping industry&#8212;which moves the ubiquitous standard-sized boxes of cargo that are transferred between ships and trucks by the giant cranes visible at every major port&#8212;&#8220;would probably like to forget 2011.&#8221; The world&#8217;s largest shipping company, the Danish firm Maersk, saw its profits fall more than 30&#37;, even though world trade was growing at a fairly rapid clip and it was carrying more cargo than it did the year before.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p355" block_type="bx5-txt">Why was 2011 a bad year to be in the shipping business? The answer is that while world trade and hence the overall demand for shipping were rising, there was a surge in oil prices. This was bad news for shippers, for whom the cost of fuel oil is a major expense. As you can see in the figure, profits temporarily increased immediately after the Great Recession when fuel costs were low. But that changed near the end of 2010, as the price of fuel started to rise. And in 2011, as fuel prices spiked at almost &#36;700 per ton, profits fell by more than &#36;1 billion.</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-fig-31" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="right" width="medium" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-img-41" alt="image" src="images/KrugESS4e_16UN13.jpg"/>
<caption><strong>An Oil Price Shock in the Shipping Industry</strong></caption>
</figure>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p356" block_type="bx5-txt">One consequence of the oil price shock was a literal slowdown in world trade: shippers turned to <em>slow steaming</em>, in which ships get somewhat better fuel economy by traveling more slowly, typically 17 knots rather than their usual 20. Some carriers even went to <em>super-slow</em> steaming, dropping their speed to 15 knots, although this damaged their engines.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p357" block_type="bx5-txt">Maersk and other shippers did better in 2012, as oil prices receded somewhat. But the troubles of 2011 were a reminder that there is more than one way to get into economic trouble.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p358" block_type="bx5-nl-h"><strong>QUESTIONS FOR THOUGHT</strong></p>
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-list-17" type="ordered" block_type="numbered">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p359" block_type="bx5-nl">How did Maersk&#8217;s problem in 2011 relate to our analysis of the causes of recessions?</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p360" block_type="bx5-nl">The Fed had to make a choice between fighting two evils in early 2008. How would that choice affect Maersk compared with, say, a company producing a service without expensive raw-material inputs, like health care?</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch16-p361" block_type="bx5-nl">In 2011, the world economy was holding up fairly well, but Europe was sliding back into recession. What do you think was happening to the business of intra-European transport (which mainly goes by truck, not ship)? Why?</p></li>
</list>
</box>
</section>
</chapter>
</manuscript>
