<chapter number="18" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-chapter-18" title="CHAPTER 18: Money, Banking, and the Federal Reserve System" start-numbering-at="18" numbered="true">
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-sec1-1a" block_type="intro" title="Chapter Introduction" numbered="false" level="1" print_page="506">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_506" block_type="page_start">506</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p1" block_type="chapter_title">Money, Banking, and the Federal Reserve System</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p2" block_type="chapter_number"><phrase block_type="chap">CHAPTER</phrase> <phrase block_type="chapnum">18</phrase></p>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-bx3-1" block_type="bx3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p3a" block_type="co-t"><image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-img-1" alt="image" src="asset/images/world_view_icon.jpg"/> <strong>FUNNY MONEY</strong></p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-fig-1" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-img-2" alt="image" src="asset/ch18/KrugESS4e_CO18.jpg"/>
<caption>Money is the essential channel that links the various parts of the modern economy.</caption>
<asset_source>&#169; Anna Delaw/Alamy</asset_source>
</figure>
</box>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-exp1-1" block_type="mn1">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p3" block_type="obj-h">What You Will Learn in This Chapter</p>
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-list-1" type="unordered" block_type="greensquare">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p4" block_type="obj-bl">The various roles money plays and the many forms it takes in the economy</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p5" block_type="obj-bl">How the actions of private banks and the Federal Reserve determine the money supply</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p6" block_type="obj-bl">How the Federal Reserve uses open-market operations to change the monetary base</p></li>
</list>
</box>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-exp2-1" block_type="mn2">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p7" block_type="fg1-t"><image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-img-3" alt="image" src="asset/images/learningcurve_logo_cmyk.jpg"/> &#124; interactive activity</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p8" block_type="co-txt-ni"><phrase block_type="dropcap">I</phrase>N 2013, POLICE IN LIMA, PERU, WERE stunned when they arrested a 13-year-old boy carrying a sack filled with &#36;700,000 in counterfeit U.S. dollars. The boy, along with several other children, worked for one of the many highly successful counterfeiting rings in Peru.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p9" block_type="co-txt">In recent years, Peru has become a major source for the production of counterfeit U.S. currency. Workers in these rings meticulously add decorative details to printed bills by hand, creating high-quality fakes that are very hard to detect. </p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p10" block_type="co-txt">The funny thing is that elaborately decorated pieces of paper have little or no intrinsic value. Indeed, a &#36;100 bill printed with blue or orange ink wouldn&#8217;t be worth the paper it was printed on.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p11" block_type="co-txt">But if the ink on that piece of paper is just the right shade of green, people will think that it&#8217;s <em>money</em> and will accept it as payment for very real goods and services. Why? Because they believe, correctly, that they can do the same thing: exchange that piece of green paper for real goods and services. </p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p12" block_type="co-txt">In fact, here&#8217;s a riddle: If a fake &#36;100 bill from Peru enters the United States and is successfully exchanged for a good or service with nobody ever realizing it&#8217;s fake, who gets hurt? Accepting a fake &#36;100 bill isn&#8217;t like buying a car that turns out to be a lemon or a meal that turns out to be inedible. As long as the bill&#8217;s counterfeit nature remains undiscovered, it will pass from hand to hand just like a real &#36;100 bill. </p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p13" block_type="co-txt">The answer to the riddle is that the actual victims of the counterfeiting are U.S. taxpayers because counterfeit dollars reduce the revenues available to pay for the operations of the U.S. government. Accordingly, the Secret Service diligently monitors the integrity of U.S. currency, promptly investigating any reports of counterfeit dollars. </p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p14" block_type="co-txt">The efforts of the Secret Service attest to the fact that money isn&#8217;t like ordinary goods and services, and it certainly is not like a piece of colored paper. In this chapter we&#8217;ll look at what money is, the role that it plays, the workings of a modern monetary system, and the institutions that sustain and regulate it, including the <em>Federal Reserve.</em> This topic is important in itself, and it&#8217;s also essential background for the understanding of monetary policy, which we will examine in the next chapter.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_507" block_type="page_start">507</p>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-sec1-1" block_type="h1" title="" chapter="18" numbered="true" level="1" print_page="507">
<section-metadata><section-title>The Meaning of Money</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p15" block_type="txt-ni">In everyday conversation, people often use the word <em>money</em> to mean wealth. If you ask, &#8220;How much money does Mark Zuckerberg have?&#8221; the answer will be something like, &#8220;Oh, &#36;30 billion or so, but who&#8217;s counting?&#8221; That is, the number will include the value of the stocks, bonds, real estate, and other assets he owns.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p16" block_type="txt">But the economist&#8217;s definition of money doesn&#8217;t include all forms of wealth. The dollar bills in your wallet are money; other forms of wealth&#8212;such as cars, houses, and stock certificates&#8212;aren&#8217;t money. What, according to economists, distinguishes money from other forms of wealth?</p>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-sec2-1" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="18" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="507">
<section-metadata><section-title>What Is Money?</section-title></section-metadata>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-exp3-1" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p17" block_type="mn-gl-def"><strong>Money</strong> is any asset that can easily be used to purchase goods and services.</p>
</box>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-exp3-2" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p18" block_type="mn-gl-def">An asset is <strong>liquid</strong> if it can be quickly converted into cash without much loss of value.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p19" block_type="txt-ni">Money is defined in terms of what it does: <strong>money</strong> is any asset that can easily be used to purchase goods and services. An asset is <strong>liquid</strong> if it can easily be converted into cash. Money consists of cash itself, which is liquid by definition, as well as other assets that are highly liquid.</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-fig-2" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="right" width="medium" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-img-4" alt="image" src="asset/ch18/KrugESS4e_18UN01.jpg"/>
<caption>Without a liquid asset like money, making purchases would be much harder.</caption>
<asset_source>Joe Raedle/Getty Images</asset_source>
</figure>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p20" block_type="txt">You can see the distinction between money and other assets by asking yourself how you pay for groceries. The person at the cash register will accept dollar bills in return for milk and frozen pizza&#8212;but he or she won&#8217;t accept stock certificates or a collection of vintage baseball cards. If you want to convert stock certificates or vintage baseball cards into groceries, you have to sell them&#8212;trade them for money&#8212;and then use the money to buy groceries. </p>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-exp3-3" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p21" block_type="mn-gl-def"><strong>Currency in circulation</strong> is cash held by the public.</p>
</box>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-exp3-4" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p22" block_type="mn-gl-def"><strong>Checkable bank deposits</strong> are bank accounts on which people can write checks.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p23" block_type="txt">Of course, many stores allow you to write a check on your bank account in payment for goods (or to pay with a debit card that is linked to your bank account). Does that make your bank account money, even if you haven&#8217;t converted it into cash? Yes. <strong>Currency in circulation</strong>&#8212;actual cash in the hands of the public&#8212;is considered money. So are <strong>checkable bank deposits</strong>&#8212;bank accounts on which people can write checks.</p>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-exp3-5" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p24" block_type="mn-gl-def">The <strong>money supply</strong> is the total value of financial assets in the economy that are considered money.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p25" block_type="txt">Are currency and checkable bank deposits the only assets that are considered money? It depends. As we&#8217;ll see later, there are two widely used definitions of the <strong>money supply,</strong> the total value of financial assets in the economy that are considered money. The narrower definition considers only the most liquid assets to be money: currency in circulation, traveler&#8217;s checks, and checkable bank deposits. The broader definition includes these three categories plus other assets that are &#8220;almost&#8221; checkable, such as savings account deposits that can be transferred into a checking account with a phone call or a mouse click. Both definitions of the money supply, however, make a distinction between those assets that can easily be used to purchase goods and services and those that can&#8217;t.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p26" block_type="txt">Money plays a crucial role in generating <em>gains from trade</em> because it makes indirect exchange possible. Think of what happens when a cardiac surgeon buys a new refrigerator. The surgeon has valuable services to offer&#8212;namely, heart operations. The owner of the store has valuable goods to offer&#8212;refrigerators and other appliances. It would be extremely difficult for both parties if, instead of using money, they had to directly barter the goods and services they sell. In a barter system, a cardiac surgeon and an appliance store owner could trade only if the store owner happened to want a heart operation and the surgeon happened to want a new refrigerator.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p27" block_type="txt">This is known as the problem of finding a <em>double coincidence of wants:</em> in a barter system, two parties can trade only when each wants what the other has to offer. Money solves this problem: individuals can trade what they have to offer for money and trade money for what they want.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p28" block_type="txt">Because the ability to make transactions with money rather than relying on bartering makes it easier to achieve gains from trade, the existence of money increases welfare, even though money does not directly produce anything. As Adam Smith put it, money &#8220;may very properly be compared to a highway, which, while it circulates and carries to market all the grass and corn of the country, produces itself not a single pile of either.&#8221;</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_508" block_type="page_start">508</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p29" block_type="txt">Let&#8217;s take a closer look at the roles money plays in the economy.</p>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-sec2-2" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="18" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="508">
<section-metadata><section-title>Roles of Money</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p30" block_type="txt-ni">Money plays three main roles in any modern economy: it is a <em>medium of exchange,</em> a <em>store of value,</em> and a <em>unit of account</em>.</p>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-exp3-6" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p31" block_type="mn-gl-def">A <strong>medium of exchange</strong> is an asset that individuals acquire for the purpose of trading goods and services rather than for their own consumption.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p32" block_type="txt-3"><phrase block_type="h3"><strong>1. Medium of Exchange</strong></phrase> Our cardiac surgeon/refrigerator example illustrates the role of money as a <strong>medium of exchange</strong>&#8212;an asset that individuals use to trade for goods and services rather than for consumption. People can&#8217;t eat dollar bills; rather, they use dollar bills to trade for edible goods and their accompanying services.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p33" block_type="txt">In normal times, the official money of a given country&#8212;the dollar in the United States, the peso in Mexico, and so on&#8212;is also the medium of exchange in virtually all transactions in that country. During troubled economic times, however, other goods or assets often play that role instead. For example, during economic turmoil people often turn to other countries&#8217; moneys as the medium of exchange: U.S. dollars have played this role in troubled Latin American countries, as have euros in troubled Eastern European countries.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p34" block_type="txt">In a famous example, cigarettes functioned as the medium of exchange in World War II prisoner-of-war camps: even nonsmokers traded goods and services for cigarettes because the cigarettes could in turn be easily traded for other items. During the extreme German inflation of 1923, goods such as eggs and lumps of coal briefly became mediums of exchange.</p>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-exp3-7" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p35" block_type="mn-gl-def">A <strong>store of value</strong> is a means of holding purchasing power over time.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p36" block_type="txt-3"><phrase block_type="h3"><strong>2. Store of Value</strong> </phrase>In order to act as a medium of exchange, money must also be a <strong>store of value</strong>&#8212;a means of holding purchasing power over time. To see why this is necessary, imagine trying to operate an economy in which ice-cream cones were the medium of exchange. Such an economy would quickly suffer from, well, monetary meltdown: your medium of exchange would often turn into a sticky puddle before you could use it to buy something else. Any asset that holds its purchasing power over time is a store of value. So the store-of-value role is a necessary but not distinctive feature of money.</p>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-bx4-1" block_type="bx4-h">
<box-metadata><box-title><image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-img-5" alt="image" src="asset/images/World_icon_no_type.jpg"/> <phrase block_type="gc1">GLOBAL</phrase> <phrase block_type="gc2">COMPARISION</phrase></box-title></box-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p37" block_type="bx4-t"><strong>The Big Moneys</strong></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p38" block_type="bx4-txt-ni"><phrase block_type="dropcap">A</phrase>mericans tend to think of the dollar as the world&#8217;s leading currency&#8212;and it does remain the currency most likely to be accepted in payment around the globe. But there are other important currencies, too. One simple measure of a currency&#8217;s importance is the value of the quantity of that currency in circulation. This figure shows the value, in billions of dollars, of the quantity of four major currencies in circulation at the end of 2015.</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-fig-3" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="right" width="medium" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-img-6" alt="image" src="asset/ch18/KrugESS4e_18UN02.jpg"/>
</figure>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p39" block_type="bx4-txt">The dollar is the most widely circulated currency. Its prominence isn&#8217;t that surprising since the United States economy is the largest in the world. The euro is a close second, behind the dollar. The combined economies of the countries using the euro, the eurozone, are about as big as the U.S. economy. And despite the fact that its economy is much smaller, Japan is closely behind the United States, largely because the Japanese make much more use of cash, as opposed to checks and credit cards, than either Europeans or Americans. Finally, China, with its rapidly growing economy, is moving up the charts, and has now passed Japan. </p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p40" block_type="bx-4-sc"><em>Data from:</em> Federal Reserve Bank of St. Louis; European Central Bank; Bank of Japan; The People&#8217;s Bank of China.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_509" block_type="page_start">509</p>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-exp3-8" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p41" block_type="mn-gl-def">A <strong>unit of account</strong> is a measure used to set prices and make economic calculations.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p42" block_type="txt-3"><phrase block_type="h3"><strong>3. Unit of Account</strong></phrase> Finally, money normally serves as the <strong>unit of account</strong>&#8212;the commonly accepted measure individuals use to set prices and make economic calculations. To understand the importance of this role, consider a historical fact: during the Middle Ages, peasants typically were required to provide landowners with goods and labor rather than money. A peasant might, for example, be required to work on the lord&#8217;s land one day a week and hand over one-fifth of his harvest.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p43" block_type="txt">Today, rents, like other prices, are almost always specified in money terms. That makes things much clearer: imagine how hard it would be to decide which apartment to rent if modern landlords followed medieval practice. Suppose, for example, that Mr. Smith says he&#8217;ll let you have a place if you clean his house twice a week and bring him a pound of steak every day, whereas Ms. Jones wants you to clean her house just once a week but wants four pounds of chicken every day. Who&#8217;s offering the better deal? It&#8217;s hard to say. If, instead, Smith wants &#36;600 a month and Jones wants &#36;700, the comparison is easy. In other words, without a commonly accepted measure, the terms of a transaction are harder to determine, making it more difficult to make transactions and achieve gains from trade.</p>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-sec2-3" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="18" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="509">
<section-metadata><section-title>Types of Money</section-title></section-metadata>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-exp3-9" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p44" block_type="mn-gl-def"><strong>Commodity money</strong> is a good used as a medium of exchange that has intrinsic value in other uses.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p45" block_type="txt-ni">In some form or another, money has been in use for thousands of years. For most of that period, people used <strong>commodity money:</strong> the medium of exchange was a good, normally gold or silver, that had intrinsic value in other uses. These alternative uses gave commodity money value independent of its role as a medium of exchange. For example, cigarettes, which served as money in World War II prisoner-of-war camps, were also valuable because many prisoners smoked. Gold was valuable because it was used for jewelry and ornamentation, aside from the fact that it was minted into coins.</p>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-exp3-10" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p46" block_type="mn-gl-def"><strong>Commodity-backed money</strong> is a medium of exchange with no intrinsic value whose ultimate value is guaranteed by a promise that it can be converted into valuable goods.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p47" block_type="txt">By 1776, the year in which the United States declared independence and Adam Smith published <em>The Wealth of Nations,</em> there was widespread use of paper money in addition to gold or silver coins. Unlike modern dollar bills, however, this paper money consisted of notes issued by private banks, which promised to exchange their notes for gold or silver coins on demand. So the paper currency that initially replaced commodity money was <strong>commodity-backed money,</strong> a medium of exchange with no intrinsic value whose ultimate value was guaranteed by a promise that it could always be converted into valuable goods on demand.</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-fig-4" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="right" width="medium" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-img-7" alt="image" src="asset/ch18/KrugESS4e_18UN03.jpg"/>
<caption>For centuries, people used goods with value, like gold and silver, as a medium of exchange.</caption>
<asset_source>DenisKot/Thinkstock</asset_source>
</figure>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p48" block_type="txt">The big advantage of commodity-backed money over simple commodity money, like gold and silver coins, was that it tied up fewer valuable resources. Although a note-issuing bank still had to keep some gold and silver on hand, it had to keep only enough to satisfy demands for redemption of its notes. And it could rely on the fact that on a normal day only a fraction of its paper notes would be redeemed. So the bank needed to keep only a portion of the total value of its notes in circulation in the form of gold and silver in its vaults. It could lend out the remaining gold and silver to those who wished to use it. This allowed society to use the remaining gold and silver for other purposes, all with no loss in the ability to achieve gains from trade.</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-fig-5" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="right" width="medium" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-img-8" alt="image" src="asset/ch18/KrugESS4e_18UN04.jpg"/>
<caption>By issuing paper notes to be used instead of gold and silver coins, banks freed up valuable resources that had been used to function as money.</caption>
<asset_source> Prints &#38; Photographs Division, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C. [LC-DIG&#8212;ds-11255]</asset_source>
</figure>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_510" block_type="page_start">510</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p49" block_type="txt">In a famous passage in <em>The Wealth of Nations,</em> Adam Smith described paper money as a &#8220;waggon-way through the air.&#8221; Smith was making an analogy between money and an imaginary highway that did not absorb valuable land beneath it. An actual highway provides a useful service but at a cost: land that could be used to grow crops is instead paved over. If the highway could be built through the air, it wouldn&#8217;t destroy useful land. As Smith understood, when banks replaced gold and silver money with paper notes, they accomplished a similar feat: they reduced the amount of real resources used by society to provide the functions of money.</p>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-exp3-11" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p50" block_type="mn-gl-def"><strong>Fiat money</strong> is a medium of exchange whose value derives entirely from its official status as a means of payment.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p51" block_type="txt">At this point you may ask: why make any use at all of gold and silver in the monetary system, even to back paper money? In fact, today&#8217;s monetary system goes even further than the system Smith admired, having eliminated any role for gold and silver. A U.S. dollar bill isn&#8217;t commodity money, and it isn&#8217;t even commodity-backed. Rather, its value arises entirely from the fact that it is generally accepted as a means of payment, a role that is ultimately decreed by the U.S. government. Money whose value derives entirely from its official status as a means of exchange is known as <strong>fiat money</strong> because it exists by government fiat, a historical term for a policy declared by a ruler.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p52" block_type="txt">Fiat money has two major advantages over commodity-backed money. First, it is even more of a &#8220;waggon-way through the air&#8221;&#8212;creating it doesn&#8217;t use up any real resources beyond the paper it&#8217;s printed on. Second, the supply of money can be adjusted based on the needs of the economy, instead of being determined by the amount of gold and silver prospectors happen to discover.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p53" block_type="txt">Fiat money, though, poses some risks. We described one such risk in the opening story&#8212;counterfeiting. Counterfeiters usurp a privilege of the U.S. government, which has the sole legal right to print dollar bills. And the benefit that counterfeiters get by exchanging fake bills for real goods and services comes at the expense of the U.S. federal government, which covers a small but nontrivial part of its own expenses by issuing new currency to meet a growing demand for money. Another larger risk is that governments that can create money whenever they feel like it will be tempted to abuse the privilege.</p>
<box title="PITFALLS" numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-bx1-1" block_type="bx-1-h">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p54" block_type="bx1-t"><strong>WHAT&#8217;S NOT IN THE MONEY SUPPLY</strong></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p55" block_type="bx1-txt-ni">Are financial assets like stocks and bonds part of the money supply? No, not under any definition, because they&#8217;re not liquid enough.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p56" block_type="bx1-txt">M1 consists, roughly speaking, of assets you can use to buy groceries: currency, traveler&#8217;s checks, and checkable deposits (which work as long as your grocery store accepts either checks or debit cards). M2 is broader, because it includes things like savings accounts that can easily and quickly be converted into M1. Normally, for example, you can switch funds between your savings and checking accounts with a quick call, a few taps on your phone, or some mouse clicks.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p57" block_type="bx1-txt">By contrast, converting a stock or a bond into cash requires selling the stock or bond&#8212;something that usually takes some time and also involves paying a broker&#8217;s fee. That makes these assets much less liquid than bank deposits. So stocks and bonds, unlike bank deposits, aren&#8217;t considered money.</p>
</box>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-sec2-4" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="18" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="510">
<section-metadata><section-title>Measuring the Money Supply</section-title></section-metadata>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-exp3-12" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p58" block_type="mn-gl-def">A <strong>monetary aggregate</strong> is an overall measure of the money supply.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p59" block_type="txt-ni">The Federal Reserve calculates the size of two <strong>monetary aggregates,</strong> overall measures of the money supply, which differ in how strictly money is defined. The two aggregates are known, rather cryptically, as M1 and M2. (There used to be a third aggregate named&#8212;you guessed it&#8212;M3, but in 2006 the Federal Reserve concluded that measuring it was no longer useful.)</p>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-exp3-13" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p60" block_type="mn-gl-def"><strong>Near-moneys</strong> are financial assets that can&#8217;t be directly used as a medium of exchange but can be readily converted into cash or checkable bank deposits.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p61" block_type="txt">M1, the narrowest definition, contains only currency in circulation (also known as cash), traveler&#8217;s checks, and checkable bank deposits. M2 adds several other kinds of assets, often referred to as <strong>near-moneys</strong>&#8212;financial assets that aren&#8217;t directly usable as a medium of exchange but can be readily converted into cash or checkable bank deposits, such as savings accounts. Examples are time deposits such as small-denomination CDs, which aren&#8217;t checkable but can be withdrawn at any time before their maturity date by paying a penalty. Because currency and checkable deposits are directly usable as a medium of exchange, M1 is the most liquid measure of money.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p62" block_type="txt"><link href="asset/ch18/KrugESS4e_fig_18_01.html">Figure 18-1</link> shows the actual composition of M1 and M2 in November 2015, in billions of dollars. M1 was valued at &#36;3,093 billion, with about 43&#37; accounted for by currency in circulation, almost all the rest accounted for by checkable bank deposits, and a tiny slice accounted for by traveler&#8217;s checks. In turn, M1 made up 25&#37; of M2, valued at &#36;12,289 billion. M2 consists of M1 plus other types of assets: two types of bank deposits, known as savings deposits and time deposits, both of which are considered noncheckable, plus money market funds, which are mutual funds that invest only in liquid assets and bear a close resemblance to bank deposits. These near-moneys pay interest, although cash (currency in circulation) does not, and they typically pay higher interest rates than any offered on checkable bank deposits.</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-fig-6" block_type="figure" numbered="true" number="18-1" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<caption><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-fig-6"><phrase block_type="fig-lable"><phrase block_type="fig"><strong>FIGURE</strong></phrase></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_num"><strong>18-1</strong></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_title">Monetary Aggregates, November 2015</phrase></link></caption>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-img-9" alt="image" src="asset/ch18/KrugESS4e_fig_18_01.jpg"/>
<caption>The Federal Reserve uses two definitions of the money supply, M1 and M2. As panel (a) shows, more than half of M1 consists of checkable bank deposits with currency in circulation making up virtually all of the rest. M2, as panel (b) shows, has a much broader definition: it includes M1 plus a range of other deposits and deposit-like assets, making it almost five times as large.</caption>
<asset_source><em>Data from:</em> Federal Reserve Bank of St. Louis.</asset_source>
</figure>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_511" block_type="page_start">511</p>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-bx3-2" block_type="bx3-h">
<box-metadata><box-title><phrase block_type="title">FOR INQUIRING MINDS</phrase> &#124; <strong>What&#8217;s With All The Currency?</strong> <image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-img-10" alt="image" src="asset/images/world_view_icon.jpg"/></box-title></box-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p63" block_type="bx3-txt-ni">Alert readers may be a bit startled at one of the numbers in the money supply: more than &#36;1 trillion of currency in circulation. That&#8217;s over &#36;3,000 in cash for every man, woman, and child in the United States. How many people do you know who carry &#36;3,000 in their wallets? Not many. So where is all that cash?</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p64" block_type="bx3-txt">Part of the answer is that it isn&#8217;t in individuals&#8217; wallets&#8212;it&#8217;s in cash registers. Businesses as well as individuals need to hold cash.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p65" block_type="bx3-txt">Economists believe that cash also plays an important role in transactions that people want to keep hidden. Small businesses and the self-employed sometimes prefer to be paid in cash so they can avoid paying taxes by hiding income from the Internal Revenue Service. Also, drug dealers and other criminals obviously don&#8217;t want bank records of their dealings. In fact, some analysts have tried to infer the amount of illegal activity in the economy from the total amount of cash holdings held by the public.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p66" block_type="bx3-txt">The most important reason for those huge currency holdings, however, is foreign use of dollars. The Federal Reserve estimates that 60&#37; of U.S. currency is actually held outside the United States&#8212;largely in countries in which residents are so distrustful of their national currencies that the U.S. dollar has become a widely accepted medium of exchange.</p>
</box>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-bx2-1" block_type="bx-2-h">
<box-metadata><box-title><phrase block_type="title">ECONOMICS</phrase> <phrase block_type="number"><em>in Action</em></phrase></box-title></box-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p67" block_type="bx-2-t"><strong>The History of the Dollar</strong></p>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-exp2-2" block_type="mn2">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p68" block_type="fg1-t"><image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-img-11" alt="image" src="asset/images/launchpad_logo_cmyk.jpg"/> &#124; interactive activity</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p69" block_type="bx2-first"><phrase block_type="dropcap">U.S.</phrase> dollar bills are pure fiat money: they have no intrinsic value, and they are not backed by anything that does. But American money wasn&#8217;t always like that. In the early days of European settlement, the colonies that would become the United States used commodity money, partly consisting of gold and silver coins minted in Europe. But such coins were scarce on this side of the Atlantic, so the colonists relied on a variety of other forms of commodity money. For example, settlers in Virginia used tobacco as money and settlers in the Northeast used &#8220;wampum,&#8221; a type of clamshell.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_512" block_type="page_start">512</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-fig-7" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="right" width="medium" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-img-12" alt="image" src="asset/ch18/KrugESS4e_18UN05.jpg"/>
<caption>Not until the Civil War did the U.S. government issue official paper money.</caption>
<asset_source>Win McNamee/Reuters/Corbis</asset_source>
</figure>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p70" block_type="bx2-txt">Later in American history, commodity-backed paper money came into widespread use. But this wasn&#8217;t paper money as we now know it, issued by the U.S. government and bearing the signature of the Secretary of the Treasury. Before the Civil War, the U.S. government didn&#8217;t issue any paper money. Instead, dollar bills were issued by private banks, which promised that their bills could be redeemed for silver coins on demand. These promises weren&#8217;t always credible because banks sometimes failed, leaving holders of their bills with worthless pieces of paper. Understandably, people were reluctant to accept currency from any bank rumored to be in financial trouble. In this private money system, some dollars were less valuable than others.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p71" block_type="bx2-txt">A curious legacy of that time was notes issued by the Citizens&#8217; Bank of Louisiana, based in New Orleans, that became among the most widely used bank notes in the southern states. These notes were printed in English on one side and French on the other. (At the time, many people in New Orleans, originally a colony of France, spoke French.) Thus, the &#36;10 bill read <em>Ten</em> on one side and <em>Dix,</em> the French word for &#8220;ten,&#8221; on the other. These &#36;10 bills became known as &#8220;dixies,&#8221; probably the source of the nickname of the U.S. South. </p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p72" block_type="bx2-txt">The U.S. government began issuing official paper money, called &#8220;greenbacks,&#8221; in 1862 as a way to pay for the ongoing Civil War. At first greenbacks had no fixed value in terms of commodities. After 1873, the U.S. government guaranteed the value of a dollar in terms of gold, effectively turning dollars into commodity-backed money.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p73" block_type="bx2-txt">In 1933, when President Franklin D. Roosevelt broke the link between dollars and gold, his own federal budget director&#8212;who feared that the public would lose confidence in the dollar if it wasn&#8217;t ultimately backed by gold&#8212;declared ominously, &#8220;This will be the end of Western civilization.&#8221; It wasn&#8217;t. The link between the dollar and gold was restored a few years later, then dropped again&#8212;seemingly for good&#8212;in August 1971. Despite the warnings of doom, the U.S. dollar went on to become the world&#8217;s most widely used currency. (Now it is the second-most widely used, after the euro.) </p>
</box>
<box title="Quick Review" numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-bx5-1" block_type="sr-1-h">
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-list-2" type="unordered" block_type="redbullet">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p74" block_type="sr1-bl"><strong>Money</strong> is any asset that can easily be used to purchase goods and services. Money consists of cash, which is <strong>liquid</strong> by definition, as well as other highly liquid assets. <strong>Currency in circulation</strong> and <strong>checkable bank deposits</strong> are both part of the <strong>money supply.</strong></p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p75" block_type="sr1-bl">Money plays three roles: a <strong>medium of exchange,</strong> a <strong>store of value,</strong> and a <strong>unit of account.</strong></p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p76" block_type="sr1-bl">Historically, money took the form first of <strong>commodity money,</strong> then of <strong>commodity-backed money.</strong> Today the dollar is pure <strong>fiat money.</strong></p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p77" block_type="sr1-bl">The money supply is measured by two <strong>monetary aggregates:</strong> M1 and M2. M1 consists of currency in circulation, checkable bank deposits, and traveler&#8217;s checks. M2 consists of M1 plus various kinds of <strong>near-moneys.</strong></p></li>
</list>
</box>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-bx6-1" block_type="sr2-h">
<box-metadata><box-title><phrase block_type="title">Check Your Understanding</phrase> <phrase block_type="number">18-1</phrase></box-title></box-metadata>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-cyuquestion-1" block_type="q_cyu" number="1">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p78" block_type="sr2-nl-first"><phrase block_type="qnum">1.</phrase> Suppose you hold a gift card, good for certain products at participating stores. Is this gift card money? Why or why not?</p>
</question>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-cyuquestion-2" block_type="q_cyu" number="2">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p79" block_type="sr2-nl-mid"><phrase block_type="qnum">2.</phrase> Although most bank accounts pay some interest, depositors can get a higher interest rate by buying a certificate of deposit, or CD. The difference between a CD and a checking account is that the depositor pays a penalty for withdrawing the money before the CD comes due&#8212;a period of months or even years. Small CDs are counted in M2 but not in M1. Explain why they are not part of M1.</p>
</question>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-cyuquestion-3" block_type="q_cyu" number="3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p80" block_type="sr2-nl-last"><phrase block_type="qnum">3.</phrase> Explain why a system of commodity-backed money uses resources more efficiently than a system of commodity money.</p>
</question>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p81" block_type="sr2-nl-fn">Solutions appear at back of book.</p>
</box>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-sec1-2" block_type="h1" title="" chapter="18" numbered="true" level="1" print_page="512">
<section-metadata><section-title>The Monetary Role of Banks</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p82" block_type="txt-ni">Roughly 40&#37; of M1, the narrowest definition of the money supply, consists of currency in circulation&#8212;&#36;1 bills, &#36;5 bills, and so on. It&#8217;s obvious where currency comes from: it&#8217;s printed by the U.S. Treasury. But the rest of M1 consists of bank deposits, and deposits account for the great bulk of M2, the broader definition of the money supply. By either measure, then, bank deposits are a major component of the money supply. And this fact brings us to our next topic: the monetary role of banks.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_513" block_type="page_start">513</p>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-sec2-5" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="18" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="513">
<section-metadata><section-title>What Banks Do</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p83" block_type="txt-ni">A bank uses liquid assets in the form of bank deposits to finance the illiquid investments of borrowers. Banks can create liquidity because it isn&#8217;t necessary for a bank to keep all of the funds deposited with it in the form of highly liquid assets. Except in the case of a <em>bank run&#8212;</em>which we&#8217;ll get to shortly&#8212;all of a bank&#8217;s depositors won&#8217;t want to withdraw their funds at the same time. So a bank can provide its depositors with liquid assets yet still invest much of the depositors&#8217; funds in illiquid assets, such as mortgages and business loans.</p>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-exp3-14" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p84" block_type="mn-gl-def"><strong>Bank reserves</strong> are the currency banks hold in their vaults plus their deposits at the Federal Reserve.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p85" block_type="txt">Banks can&#8217;t, however, lend out all the funds placed in their hands by depositors because they have to satisfy any depositor who wants to withdraw his or her funds. In order to meet these demands, a bank must keep substantial quantities of liquid assets on hand. In the modern U.S. banking system, these assets take the form either of currency in the bank&#8217;s vault or deposits held in the bank&#8217;s own account at the Federal Reserve. As we&#8217;ll see shortly, the latter can be converted into currency more or less instantly. Currency in bank vaults and bank deposits held at the Federal Reserve are called <strong>bank reserves.</strong> Because bank reserves are in bank vaults and at the Federal Reserve, not held by the public, they are not part of currency in circulation.</p>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-exp3-15" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p86" block_type="mn-gl-def">A <strong>T-account</strong> is a tool for analyzing a business&#8217;s financial position by showing, in a single table, the business&#8217;s assets (on the left) and liabilities (on the right).</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p87" block_type="txt">To understand the role of banks in determining the money supply, we start by introducing a simple tool for analyzing a bank&#8217;s financial position: a <strong>T-account.</strong> A business&#8217;s T-account summarizes its financial position by showing, in a single table, the business&#8217;s assets and liabilities, with assets on the left and liabilities on the right.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p88" block_type="txt"><link href="asset/ch18/KrugESS4e_fig_18_02.html">Figure 18-2</link> shows the T-account for a hypothetical business that <em>isn&#8217;t</em> a bank&#8212;Samantha&#8217;s Smoothies. According to <link href="asset/ch18/KrugESS4e_fig_18_02.html">Figure 18-2</link>, Samantha&#8217;s Smoothies owns a building worth &#36;30,000 and has &#36;15,000 worth of smoothie-making equipment. These are assets, so they&#8217;re on the left side of the table. To finance its opening, the business borrowed &#36;20,000 from a local bank. That&#8217;s a liability, so the loan is on the right side of the table. By looking at the T-account, you can immediately see what Samantha&#8217;s Smoothies owns and what it owes. Oh, and it&#8217;s called a T-account because the lines in the table make a T-shape.</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-fig-8" block_type="figure" numbered="true" number="18-2" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<caption><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-fig-8"><phrase block_type="fig-lable"><phrase block_type="fig"><strong>FIGURE</strong></phrase></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_num"><strong>18-2</strong> </phrase><phrase block_type="fig_title"><strong>A T-Account For Samantha&#8217;s Smoothies</strong></phrase></link></caption>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-img-13" alt="image" src="asset/ch18/KrugESS4e_fig_18_02.jpg"/>
<caption>A T-account summarizes a business&#8217;s financial position. Its assets, in this case consisting of a building and some smoothie-making machinery, are on the left side. Its liabilities, consisting of the money it owes to a local bank, are on the right side.</caption>
</figure>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p89" block_type="txt">Samantha&#8217;s Smoothies is an ordinary, nonbank business. Now let&#8217;s look at the T-account for a hypothetical bank, First Street Bank, which is the repository of &#36;1 million in bank deposits.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p90" block_type="txt"><link href="asset/ch18/KrugESS4e_fig_18_03.html">Figure 18-3</link> shows First Street Bank&#8217;s financial position. The loans First Street Bank has made are on the left side because they&#8217;re assets: they represent funds that those who have borrowed from the bank are expected to repay. The bank&#8217;s only other assets, in this simplified example, are its reserves, which, as we&#8217;ve learned, can take the form either of cash in the bank&#8217;s vault or deposits at the Federal Reserve. On the right side we show the bank&#8217;s liabilities, which in this example consist entirely of deposits made by customers at First Street Bank. These are liabilities because they represent funds that must ultimately be repaid to depositors.</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-fig-9" block_type="figure" numbered="true" number="18-3" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<caption><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-fig-9"><phrase block_type="fig-lable"><phrase block_type="fig"><strong>FIGURE</strong></phrase></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_num"><strong>18-3</strong></phrase> <phrase block_type="title"><strong>Assets and Liabilities of First Street Bank</strong></phrase></link></caption>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-img-14" alt="image" src="asset/ch18/KrugESS4e_fig_18_03.jpg"/>
<caption>First Street Bank&#8217;s assets consist of &#36;1,200,000 in loans and &#36;100,000 in reserves. Its liabilities consist of &#36;1,000,000 in deposits&#8212;money owed to people who have placed funds in First Street&#8217;s hands.</caption>
</figure>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_514" block_type="page_start">514</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p91" block_type="txt">Notice that in this example First Street Bank&#8217;s assets are larger than its liabilities. That&#8217;s the way it&#8217;s supposed to be! Banks are required by law to maintain assets larger by a specific percentage than their liabilities.</p>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-exp3-16" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p92" block_type="mn-gl-def">The <strong>reserve ratio</strong> is the fraction of bank deposits that a bank holds as reserves.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p93" block_type="txt">In this example, First Street Bank holds reserves equal to 10&#37; of its customers&#8217; bank deposits. The fraction of bank deposits that a bank holds as reserves is its <strong>reserve ratio.</strong> In the modern American system, the Federal Reserve&#8212;which, among other things, regulates banks operating in the United States&#8212;sets a minimum required reserve ratio that banks are required to maintain. To understand why banks are regulated, let&#8217;s consider a problem banks can face: bank runs.</p>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-sec2-6" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="18" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="514">
<section-metadata><section-title>The Problem of Bank Runs</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p94" block_type="txt-ni">A bank can lend out most of the funds deposited in its care because in normal times only a small fraction of its depositors want to withdraw their funds on any given day. But what would happen if, for some reason, all or at least a large fraction of its depositors did try to withdraw their funds during a short period of time, such as a couple of days?</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p95" block_type="txt">If a significant share of its depositors demanded their money back at the same time, the bank wouldn&#8217;t be able to raise enough cash to meet those demands. The reason is that banks convert most of their depositors&#8217; funds into loans made to borrowers; that&#8217;s how banks earn revenue&#8212;by charging interest on loans.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p96" block_type="txt">Bank loans, however, are illiquid: they can&#8217;t easily be converted into cash on short notice. To see why, imagine that First Street Bank has lent &#36;100,000 to Drive-A-Peach Used Cars, a local dealership. To raise cash to meet demands for withdrawals, First Street Bank can sell its loan to Drive-A-Peach to someone else&#8212;another bank or an individual investor. But if First Street Bank tries to sell the loan quickly, potential buyers will be wary: they will suspect that First Street Bank wants to sell the loan because there is something wrong and the loan might not be repaid. As a result, First Street Bank can sell the loan quickly only by offering it for sale at a deep discount&#8212;say, a discount of 40&#37;, for a sale price of &#36;60,000.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p97" block_type="txt">The upshot is that if a significant number of First Street Bank&#8217;s depositors suddenly decided to withdraw their funds, the bank&#8217;s efforts to raise the necessary cash quickly would force it to sell off its assets very cheaply. Inevitably, this leads to a <em>bank failure:</em> the bank would be unable to pay off its depositors in full.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p98" block_type="txt">What might start this whole process? That is, what might lead First Street Bank&#8217;s depositors to rush to pull their money out? A plausible answer is a spreading rumor that the bank is in financial trouble. Even if depositors aren&#8217;t sure the rumor is true, they are likely to play it safe and get their money out while they still can. And it gets worse: a depositor who simply thinks that <em>other</em> depositors are going to panic and try to get their money out will realize that this could &#8220;break the bank.&#8221; So he or she joins the rush. In other words, fear about a bank&#8217;s financial condition can be a self-fulfilling prophecy: depositors who believe that other depositors will rush to the exit will rush to the exit themselves.</p>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-exp3-17" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p99" block_type="mn-gl-def">A <strong>bank run</strong> is a phenomenon in which many of a bank&#8217;s depositors try to withdraw their funds due to fears of a bank failure.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p100" block_type="txt"><phrase block_type="h3">A <strong>bank run</strong> </phrase>is a phenomenon in which many of a bank&#8217;s depositors try to withdraw their funds due to fears of a bank failure. Moreover, bank runs aren&#8217;t bad only for the bank in question and its depositors. Historically, they have often proved contagious, with a run on one bank leading to a loss of faith in other banks, causing additional bank runs. </p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p101" block_type="txt">The upcoming Economics in Action describes an actual case of just such a contagion, the wave of bank runs that swept across the United States in the early 1930s. In response to that experience and similar experiences in other countries, the United States and most other modern governments have established a system of bank regulations that protect depositors and prevent most bank runs.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_515" block_type="page_start">515</p>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-sec2-7" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="18" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="515">
<section-metadata><section-title>Bank Regulation</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p102" block_type="txt-ni">Should you worry about losing money in the United States due to a bank run? No. After the banking crises of the 1930s, the United States and most other countries put into place a system designed to protect depositors and the economy as a whole against bank runs. This system has four main features: <em>deposit insurance, capital requirements, reserve requirements,</em> and, in addition, banks have access to the <em>discount window,</em> a source of cash when it&#8217;s needed.</p>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-exp3-18" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p103" block_type="mn-gl-def"><strong>Deposit insurance</strong> guarantees that a bank&#8217;s depositors will be paid even if the bank can&#8217;t come up with the funds, up to a maximum amount per account.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p104" block_type="txt-3"><phrase block_type="h3"><strong>1. Deposit Insurance</strong></phrase> Almost all banks in the United States advertise themselves as a &#8220;member of the FDIC&#8221;&#8212;the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation. The FDIC provides <strong>deposit insurance,</strong> a guarantee that depositors will be paid even if the bank can&#8217;t come up with the funds, up to a maximum amount per account. The FDIC currently guarantees the first &#36;250,000 per depositor, per insured bank.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p105" block_type="txt">It&#8217;s important to realize that deposit insurance doesn&#8217;t just protect depositors if a bank actually fails. The insurance also eliminates the main reason for bank runs: since depositors know their funds are safe even if a bank fails, they have no incentive to rush to pull them out because of a rumor that the bank is in trouble.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p106" block_type="txt-3"><phrase block_type="h3"><strong>2. Capital Requirements</strong> </phrase> Deposit insurance, although it protects the banking system against bank runs, creates a well-known incentive problem. Because depositors are protected from loss, they have no incentive to monitor their bank&#8217;s financial health, allowing risky behavior by the bank to go undetected. At the same time, the owners of banks have an incentive to engage in overly risky investment behavior, such as making questionable loans at high interest rates. That&#8217;s because if all goes well, the owners profit; if things go badly, the government covers the losses through federal deposit insurance.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p107" block_type="txt">To reduce the incentive for excessive risk taking, regulators require that the owners of banks hold substantially more assets than the value of bank deposits. That way, the bank will still have assets larger than its deposits even if some of its loans go bad, and losses will accrue against the bank owners&#8217; assets, not the government. The excess of a bank&#8217;s assets over its bank deposits and other liabilities is called the <em>bank&#8217;s capital.</em> For example, First Street Bank has capital of &#36;300,000, equal to &#36;300,000/(&#36;1,200,000 &#43; &#36;100,000) = 23&#37; of the total value of its assets. In practice, banks&#8217; capital is required to equal at least 7&#37; of the value of their assets.</p>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-exp3-19" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p108" block_type="mn-gl-def"><strong>Reserve requirements</strong> are rules set by the Federal Reserve that determine the minimum reserve ratio for banks.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p109" block_type="txt-3"><phrase block_type="h3"><strong>3. Reserve Requirements</strong> </phrase>Another regulation used to reduce the risk of bank runs is <strong>reserve requirements,</strong> rules set by the Federal Reserve that specify the minimum reserve ratio for banks. For example, in the United States, the minimum reserve ratio for checkable bank deposits is 10&#37;.</p>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-exp3-20" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p110" block_type="mn-gl-def">The <strong>discount window</strong> is an arrangement in which the Federal Reserve stands ready to lend money to banks in trouble.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p111" block_type="txt-3"><phrase block_type="h3"><strong>4. The Discount Window</strong></phrase> One final protection against bank runs is the fact that the Federal Reserve, which we&#8217;ll discuss more thoroughly later in this chapter, stands ready to lend money to banks in trouble, an arrangement known as the <strong>discount window.</strong> The ability to borrow money means a bank can avoid being forced to sell its assets at fire-sale prices in order to satisfy the demands of a sudden rush of depositors demanding cash. Instead, it can turn to the Fed and borrow the funds it needs to pay off depositors.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_516" block_type="page_start">516</p>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-bx2-2" block_type="bx-2-h">
<box-metadata><box-title><phrase block_type="title">ECONOMICS</phrase> <phrase block_type="number"><em>in Action</em> <image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-img-15" alt="image" src="asset/images/world_view_icon.jpg"/></phrase></box-title></box-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p112" block_type="bx-2-t"><strong>It&#8217;s a Wonderful Banking System</strong></p>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-exp2-3" block_type="mn2">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p113" block_type="fg1-t"><image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-img-16" alt="image" src="asset/images/launchpad_logo_cmyk.jpg"/> &#124; interactive activity</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p114" block_type="bx2-first"><phrase block_type="dropcap">N</phrase>ext Christmastime, it&#8217;s a sure thing that at least one TV channel will show the 1946 film <em>It&#8217;s a Wonderful Life,</em> featuring Jimmy Stewart as George Bailey, a small-town banker whose life is saved by an angel. The movie&#8217;s climactic scene is a run on Bailey&#8217;s bank, as fearful depositors rush to take their funds out.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p115" block_type="bx2-txt">When the movie was made, such scenes were still fresh in Americans&#8217; memories. There was a wave of bank runs in late 1930, a second wave in the spring of 1931, and a third wave in early 1933. By the end, more than a third of the nation&#8217;s banks had failed. To bring the panic to an end, on March 6, 1933, the newly inaugurated president, Franklin Delano Roosevelt, declared a national &#8220;bank holiday,&#8221; closing all banks for a week to give bank regulators time to close unhealthy banks and certify healthy ones.</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-fig-10" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="right" width="medium" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-img-17" alt="image" src="asset/ch18/KrugESS4e_18UN06.jpg"/>
<caption>In July 2008, panicky IndyMac depositors lined up to pull their money out of the troubled California bank.</caption>
<asset_source>Gabriel Bouys/AFP/Getty Images</asset_source>
</figure>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p116" block_type="bx2-txt">Since then, regulation has protected the United States and other wealthy countries against most bank runs. In fact, the scene in <em>It&#8217;s a Wonderful Life</em> was already out of date when the movie was made. But recent decades have seen several waves of bank runs in developing countries. For example, bank runs played a role in an economic crisis that swept Southeast Asia in 1997&#8211;1998 and in the severe economic crisis in Argentina that began in late 2001. And a &#8220;panic&#8221; with strong resemblance to a wave of bank runs swept world financial markets in 2008 during the financial crisis.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p117" block_type="bx2-txt">Notice that we said <em>most bank runs.</em> There are some limits on deposit insurance; in particular, in the United States currently only the first &#36;250,000 of an individual depositor&#8217;s funds in an insured bank is covered. As a result, there can still be a run on a bank perceived as troubled. In fact, that&#8217;s exactly what happened in July 2008 to IndyMac, a Pasadena-based lender that had made a large number of questionable home loans. As questions about IndyMac&#8217;s financial soundness were raised, depositors began pulling out funds, forcing federal regulators to step in and close the bank. In Britain the limits on deposit insurance are much lower, which exposed the bank Northern Rock to a classic bank run that same year. Unlike in the bank runs of the 1930s, however, most depositors at both IndyMac and Northern Rock got all their funds back&#8212;and the panics at these banks didn&#8217;t spread to other institutions.</p>
</box>
<box title="Quick Review" numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-bx5-2" block_type="sr-1-h">
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-list-3" type="unordered" block_type="redbullet">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p118" block_type="sr1-bl">A <strong>T-account</strong> is used to analyze a bank&#8217;s financial position. A bank holds <strong>bank reserves&#8212;</strong>currency in its vaults plus deposits held in its account at the Federal Reserve. The <strong>reserve ratio</strong> is the ratio of bank reserves to customers&#8217; bank deposits.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p119" block_type="sr1-bl">Because bank loans are illiquid, but a bank is obligated to return depositors&#8217; funds on demand, <strong>bank runs</strong> are a potential problem. Although they took place on a massive scale during the 1930s, they have been largely eliminated in the United States through bank regulation in the form of <strong>deposit insurance,</strong> capital requirements, and <strong>reserve requirements,</strong> as well as through the availability of the <strong>discount window.</strong></p></li>
</list>
</box>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-bx6-2" block_type="sr2-h">
<box-metadata><box-title><phrase block_type="title">Check Your Understanding</phrase> <phrase block_type="number">18-2</phrase></box-title></box-metadata>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-cyuquestion-4" block_type="q_cyu" number="1">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p120" block_type="sr2-nl-first"><phrase block_type="qnum">1.</phrase> Suppose you are a depositor at First Street Bank. You hear a rumor that the bank has suffered serious losses on its loans. Every depositor knows that the rumor isn&#8217;t true, but each thinks that most other depositors believe the rumor. Why, in the absence of deposit insurance, could this lead to a bank run? How does deposit insurance change the situation?</p>
</question>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-cyuquestion-5" block_type="q_cyu" number="2">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p121" block_type="sr2-nl-first"><phrase block_type="qnum">2.</phrase> A con artist has a great idea: he&#8217;ll open a bank without investing any capital and lend all the deposits at high interest rates to real estate developers. If the real estate market booms, the loans will be repaid and he&#8217;ll make high profits. If the real estate market goes bust, the loans won&#8217;t be repaid and the bank will fail&#8212;but he will not lose any of his own wealth. How would modern bank regulation frustrate his scheme?</p>
</question>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p122" block_type="sr2-nl-fn">Solutions appear at back of book.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_517" block_type="page_start">517</p>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-sec1-3" block_type="h1" title="" chapter="18" numbered="true" level="1" print_page="517">
<section-metadata><section-title>Determining the Money Supply</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p123" block_type="txt-ni">Without banks, there would be no checkable deposits, so the quantity of currency in circulation would equal the money supply. In that case, the money supply would be solely determined by whoever controls government minting and printing presses. But banks do exist, and through their creation of checkable bank deposits they affect the money supply in two ways.</p>
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-list-4" type="ordered" block_type="numbered">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p124" block_type="nl-first">Banks remove some currency from circulation: dollar bills that are sitting in bank vaults, as opposed to sitting in people&#8217;s wallets, aren&#8217;t part of the money supply. </p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p125" block_type="nl-last">Much more importantly, banks create money by accepting deposits and making loans&#8212;that is, they make the money supply larger than just the value of currency in circulation. </p></li>
</list>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p126" block_type="txt-ni">Our next topic is how banks create money and what determines the amount of money they create.</p>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-sec2-8" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="18" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="517">
<section-metadata><section-title>How Banks Create Money</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p127" block_type="txt-ni">To see how banks create money, let&#8217;s examine what happens when someone decides to deposit currency in a bank. Consider the example of Silas, a miser, who keeps a shoebox full of cash under his bed. Suppose Silas realizes that it would be safer, as well as more convenient, to deposit that cash in the bank and to use his debit card when shopping. Assume that he deposits &#36;1,000 into a checkable account at First Street Bank. What effect will Silas&#8217;s actions have on the money supply?</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p128" block_type="txt">Panel (a) of <link href="asset/ch18/KrugESS4e_fig_18_04.html">Figure 18-4</link> shows the initial effect of his deposit. First Street Bank credits Silas with &#36;1,000 in his account, so the economy&#8217;s checkable bank deposits rise by &#36;1,000. Meanwhile, Silas&#8217;s cash goes into the vault, raising First Street&#8217;s reserves by &#36;1,000 as well.</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-fig-11" block_type="figure" numbered="true" number="18-4a" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<caption><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-fig-11"><phrase block_type="fig-lable"><phrase block_type="fig"><strong>FIGURE</strong></phrase></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_num"><strong>18-4</strong></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_title">Effect on the Money Supply of Turning Cash into a Checkable Deposit at First Street Bank</phrase></link></caption>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-img-18" alt="image" src="asset/ch18/KrugESS4e_fig_18_04a.jpg"/>
</figure>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-fig-12" block_type="figure" numbered="true" number="18-4b" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-img-19" alt="image" src="asset/ch18/KrugESS4e_fig_18_04b.jpg"/>
<caption>When Silas deposits &#36;1,000 (which had been stashed under his bed) into a checkable bank account, there is initially no effect on the money supply: currency in circulation falls by &#36;1,000, but checkable bank deposits rise by &#36;1,000. The corresponding entries on the bank&#8217;s T-account, depicted in panel (a), show deposits initially rising by &#36;1,000 and the bank&#8217;s reserves initially rising by &#36;1,000. In the second stage, depicted in panel (b), the bank holds 10&#37; of Silas&#8217;s deposit (&#36;100) as reserves and lends out the rest (&#36;900) to Maya. As a result, its reserves fall by &#36;900 and its loans increase by &#36;900. Its liabilities, including Silas&#8217;s &#36;1,000 deposit, are unchanged. The money supply, the sum of checkable bank deposits and currency in circulation, has now increased by &#36;900&#8212;the &#36;900 now held by Maya.</caption>
</figure>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p129" block_type="txt">This initial transaction has no effect on the money supply. Currency in circulation, part of the money supply, falls by &#36;1,000; checkable bank deposits, also part of the money supply, rise by the same amount.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p130" block_type="txt">But this is not the end of the story because First Street Bank can now lend out part of Silas&#8217;s deposit. Assume that it holds 10&#37; of Silas&#8217;s deposit&#8212;&#36;100&#8212;in reserves and lends the rest out in cash to Silas&#8217;s neighbor, Maya. The effect of this second stage is shown in panel (b). First Street&#8217;s deposits remain unchanged, and so does the value of its assets. But the composition of its assets changes: by making the loan, it reduces its reserves by &#36;900, so that they are only &#36;100 larger than they were before Silas made his deposit. In the place of the &#36;900 reduction in reserves, the bank has acquired an IOU, its &#36;900 cash loan to Maya.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_518" block_type="page_start">518</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p131" block_type="txt">So by putting &#36;900 of Silas&#8217;s cash back into circulation by lending it to Maya, First Street Bank has, in fact, increased the money supply. That is, the sum of currency in circulation and checkable bank deposits has risen by &#36;900 compared to what it had been when Silas&#8217;s cash was still under his bed. Although Silas is still the owner of &#36;1,000, now in the form of a checkable deposit, Maya has the use of &#36;900 in cash from her borrowings.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p132" block_type="txt">And this may not be the end of the story. Suppose that Maya uses her cash to buy a television from Acme Merchandise. What does Anne Acme, the store&#8217;s owner, do with the cash? If she holds on to it, the money supply doesn&#8217;t increase any further. But suppose she deposits the &#36;900 into a checkable bank deposit&#8212;say, at Second Street Bank. Second Street Bank, in turn, will keep only part of that deposit in reserves, lending out the rest, creating still more money.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p133" block_type="txt">Assume that Second Street Bank, like First Street Bank, keeps 10&#37; of any bank deposit in reserves and lends out the rest. Then it will keep &#36;90 in reserves and lend out &#36;810 of Anne&#8217;s deposit to another borrower, further increasing the money supply.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p134" block_type="txt"><link href="asset/ch18/table_18_1.html">Table 18-1</link> shows the process of money creation we have described so far. At first the money supply consists only of Silas&#8217;s &#36;1,000. After he deposits the cash into a checkable bank deposit and the bank makes a loan, the money supply rises to &#36;1,900. After the second deposit and the second loan, the money supply rises to &#36;2,710. And the process will, of course, continue from there. (Although we have considered the case in which Silas places his cash in a checkable bank deposit, the results would be the same if he put it into any type of near-money.)</p>
<table id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-tab-1" block_type="table" numbered="false" caption-placement="Top" data-href="asset/ch18/table_18_1.html" data-target="_pop">
<table_caption><strong><phrase block_type="tbl">TABLE</phrase> <phrase block_type="tbl_num">18-1</phrase></strong> <phrase block_type="tbl_title">How Banks Create Money</phrase></table_caption>
<tbody>
<tr class="tbl-hdr-bg">
<td></td>
<td><strong>Currency in circulation</strong></td>
<td> <strong>Checkable bank deposits</strong> </td>
<td><strong>Money supply</strong></td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tabl-rborder"><strong>First stage:</strong> Silas keeps his cash under his bed.</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">&#36;1,000</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">&#36;0</td>
<td>&#36;1,000</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-dark">
<td class="tabl-rborder"><strong>Second stage:</strong> Silas deposits cash in First Street Bank, which lends out &#36;900 to Maya, who then pays it to Anne Acme.</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">900</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">1,000</td>
<td>1,900</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tabl-rborder"><strong>Third stage:</strong> Anne Acme deposits &#36;900 in Second Street Bank, which lends out &#36;810 to another borrower.</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">810</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">1,900</td>
<td>2,710</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p135" block_type="txt">This process of money creation may sound familiar. In <link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e_ch17_1.html">Chapter 17</link> we described the <em>multiplier process:</em> an initial increase in real GDP leads to a rise in consumer spending, which leads to a further rise in real GDP, which leads to a further rise in consumer spending, and so on. What we have here is another kind of multiplier&#8212;the <em>money multiplier.</em> Next, we&#8217;ll learn what determines the size of this multiplier.</p>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-sec2-9" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="18" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="518">
<section-metadata><section-title>Reserves, Bank Deposits, and the Money Multiplier</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p136" block_type="txt-ni">In tracing out the effect of Silas&#8217;s deposit in <link href="asset/ch18/table_18_1.html">Table 18-1</link>, we assumed that the funds a bank lends out always end up being deposited either in the same bank or in another bank&#8212;so funds disbursed as loans come back to the banking system, even if not to the lending bank itself.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p137" block_type="txt">In reality, some of these loaned funds may be held by borrowers in their wallets and not deposited in a bank, meaning that some of the loaned amount &#8220;leaks&#8221; out of the banking system. Such leaks reduce the size of the money multiplier, just as leaks of real income into savings reduce the size of the real GDP multiplier. (Bear in mind, however, that the leak here comes from the fact that borrowers keep some of their funds in currency, rather than the fact that consumers save some of their income.)</p>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-exp3-21" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p138" block_type="mn-gl-def"><strong>Excess reserves</strong> are a bank&#8217;s reserves over and above its required reserves.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p139" block_type="txt">But let&#8217;s set that complication aside for a moment and consider how the money supply is determined in a &#8220;checkable-deposits-only&#8221; monetary system, where funds are always deposited in bank accounts and none are held in wallets as currency. That is, in our checkable-deposits-only monetary system, any and all funds borrowed from a bank are immediately deposited into a checkable bank account. We&#8217;ll assume that banks are required to satisfy a minimum reserve ratio of 10&#37; and that every bank lends out all of its <strong>excess reserves,</strong> reserves over and above the amount needed to satisfy the minimum reserve ratio.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_519" block_type="page_start">519</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-fig-13" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="right" width="medium" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-img-20" alt="image" src="asset/ch18/KrugESS4e_18UN07.jpg"/>
<asset_source>Frank Cotham, The New Yorker Collection/The CartoonBank</asset_source>
</figure>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p140" block_type="txt">Now suppose that for some reason a bank suddenly finds itself with &#36;1,000 in excess reserves. What happens? The answer is that the bank will lend out that &#36;1,000, which will end up as a checkable bank deposit somewhere in the banking system, launching a money multiplier process very similar to the process shown in <link href="asset/ch18/table_18_1.html">Table 18-1</link>.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p141" block_type="txt">In the first stage, the bank lends out its excess reserves of &#36;1,000, which becomes a checkable bank deposit somewhere. The bank that receives the &#36;1,000 deposit keeps 10&#37;, or &#36;100, as reserves and lends out the remaining 90&#37;, or &#36;900, which again becomes a checkable bank deposit somewhere. The bank receiving this &#36;900 deposit again keeps 10&#37;, which is &#36;90, as reserves and lends out the remaining &#36;810. The bank receiving this &#36;810 keeps &#36;81 in reserves and lends out the remaining &#36;729, and so on. As a result of this process, the total increase in checkable bank deposits is equal to a sum that looks like:</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p142" block_type="eq">&#36;1,000 &#43; &#36;900 &#43; &#36;810 &#43; &#36;729 &#43; . . . </p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p143" block_type="txt-ni">We&#8217;ll use the symbol <em>rr</em> for the reserve ratio. More generally, the total increase in checkable bank deposits that is generated when a bank lends out &#36;1,000 in excess reserves is:</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p144" block_type="eq"><strong>(18-1)</strong> Increase in checkable bank deposits from &#36;1,000 in excess reserves = &#36;1,000 &#43; (&#36;1,000 &#215; (1 &#8722; <em>rr</em>)) &#43; (&#36;1,000 &#215; (1 &#8722; <em>rr</em>)<sup>2</sup>) &#43; (&#36;1,000&#215; (1 &#8722; <em>rr</em>)<sup>3</sup>) &#43; . . .</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p145" block_type="txt-ni">An infinite series of this form can be simplified to:</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p146" block_type="eq"><strong>(18-2)</strong>Increase in checkable bank deposits from &#36;1,000 in excess reserves = &#36;1,000/<em>rr</em></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p147" block_type="txt-ni">Given a reserve ratio of 10&#37;, or 0.1, a &#36;1,000 increase in excess reserves will increase the total value of checkable bank deposits by &#36;1,000/0.1 = &#36;10,000. In fact, in a checkable-deposits-only monetary system, the total value of checkable bank deposits will be equal to the value of bank reserves divided by the reserve ratio. Or to put it a different way, if the reserve ratio is 10&#37;, each &#36;1 of reserves held by a bank supports &#36;1/<em>rr</em> = &#36;1/0.1 = &#36;10 of checkable bank deposits.</p>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-sec2-10" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="18" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="519">
<section-metadata><section-title>The Money Multiplier in Reality</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p148" block_type="txt-ni">In reality, the determination of the money supply is more complicated than our simple model suggests because it depends not only on the ratio of reserves to bank deposits but also on the fraction of the money supply that individuals choose to hold in the form of currency. In fact, we already saw this in our example of Silas depositing the cash under his bed: when he chose to hold a checkable bank deposit instead of currency, he set in motion an increase in the money supply.</p>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-exp3-22" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p149" block_type="mn-gl-def">The <strong>monetary base</strong> is the sum of currency in circulation and bank reserves.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p150" block_type="txt">To define the money multiplier in practice, it&#8217;s important to recognize that the Federal Reserve controls the <em>sum</em> of bank reserves and currency in circulation, called the <em>monetary base,</em> but it does not control the allocation of that sum between bank reserves and currency in circulation. Consider Silas and his deposit one more time: by taking the cash from under his bed and depositing it in a bank, he reduced the quantity of currency in circulation but increased bank reserves by an equal amount&#8212;leaving the <em>monetary base,</em> on net, unchanged. The <strong>monetary base,</strong> which is the quantity the monetary authorities control, is the sum of currency in circulation and reserves held by banks.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_520" block_type="page_start">520</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p151" block_type="txt">The monetary base is different from the money supply in two ways. First, bank reserves, which are part of the monetary base, aren&#8217;t considered part of the money supply. A &#36;1 bill in someone&#8217;s wallet is considered money because it&#8217;s available for an individual to spend, but a &#36;1 bill held as bank reserves in a bank vault or deposited at the Federal Reserve isn&#8217;t considered part of the money supply because it&#8217;s not available for spending. Second, checkable bank deposits, which are part of the money supply because they are available for spending, aren&#8217;t part of the monetary base.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p152" block_type="txt"><link href="asset/ch18/KrugESS4e_fig_18_05.html">Figure 18-5</link> shows the two concepts schematically. The circle on the left represents the monetary base, consisting of bank reserves plus currency in circulation. The circle on the right represents the money supply, consisting mainly of currency in circulation plus checkable or near-checkable bank deposits. As the figure indicates, currency in circulation is part of both the monetary base and the money supply. But bank reserves aren&#8217;t part of the money supply, and checkable or near-checkable bank deposits aren&#8217;t part of the monetary base. In practice, most of the monetary base actually consists of currency in circulation, which also makes up about half of the money supply.</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-fig-14" block_type="figure" numbered="true" number="18-5" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<caption><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-fig-14"><phrase block_type="fig-lable"><phrase block_type="fig"><strong>FIGURE</strong></phrase></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_num"><strong>18-5</strong></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_title">The Monetary Base and the Money Supply</phrase></link></caption>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-img-21" alt="image" src="asset/ch18/KrugESS4e_fig_18_05.jpg"/>
<caption>The monetary base is equal to bank reserves plus currency in circulation. It is different from the money supply, consisting mainly of checkable or near-checkable bank deposits plus currency in circulation. Each dollar of bank reserves backs several dollars of bank deposits, making the money supply larger than the monetary base.</caption>
</figure>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-exp3-23" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p153" block_type="mn-gl-def">The <strong>money multiplier</strong> is the ratio of the money supply to the monetary base.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p154" block_type="txt">Now we can formally define the <strong>money multiplier:</strong> it&#8217;s the ratio of the money supply to the monetary base. Before the financial crisis of 2008, the money multiplier was about 1.6; after the crisis it fell to about 0.7. Even before the crisis it was a lot smaller than 1/0.1 = 10, the money multiplier in a checkable-deposits-only system with a reserve ratio of 10&#37; (the minimum required ratio for most checkable deposits in the United States).</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p155" block_type="txt">The reason the actual money multiplier was so small arises from the fact that people hold significant amounts of cash, and a dollar of currency in circulation, unlike a dollar in reserves, doesn&#8217;t support multiple dollars of the money supply. In fact, before the crisis currency in circulation accounted for more than 90&#37; of the monetary base. At the end of 2013, however, currency in circulation was less than a third of the monetary base. What had happened?</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p156" block_type="txt">The answer is that the financial crisis created an abnormal situation. As explained later in this chapter, a very abnormal situation developed after Lehman Brothers, a key financial institution, failed in September 2008. Banks, seeing few opportunities for safe, profitable lending, began parking large sums at the Federal Reserve in the form of deposits&#8212;deposits that counted as part of the monetary base. As a result, currency in circulation no longer dominated the monetary base, and thanks to all those deposits at the Fed the monetary base was actually larger than M1, with the money multiplier therefore less than 1.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_521" block_type="page_start">521</p>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-bx2-3" block_type="bx-2-h">
<box-metadata><box-title><phrase block_type="title">ECONOMICS</phrase> <phrase block_type="number"><em>in Action</em> </phrase></box-title></box-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p157" block_type="bx-2-t"><strong>Multiplying Money Down</strong></p>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-exp2-4" block_type="mn2">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p158" block_type="fg1-t"><image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-img-22" alt="image" src="asset/images/launchpad_logo_cmyk.jpg"/> &#124; interactive activity</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p159" block_type="bx2-first"><phrase block_type="dropcap">I</phrase>n our hypothetical example illustrating how banks create money, we described Silas the miser taking the currency from under his bed and turning it into a checkable bank deposit. This led to an increase in the money supply, as banks engaged in successive waves of lending backed by Silas&#8217;s funds. It follows that if something happened to make Silas revert to old habits, taking his money out of the bank and putting it back under his bed, the result would be less lending and, ultimately, a decline in the money supply. That&#8217;s exactly what happened as a result of the bank runs of the 1930s.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p160" block_type="bx2-txt"><link href="asset/ch18/table_18_2.html">Table 18-2</link> shows what happened between 1929 and 1933, as bank failures shook the public&#8217;s confidence in the banking system. The second column shows the public&#8217;s holdings of currency. This increased sharply, as many Americans decided that money under the bed was safer than money in the bank after all. The third column shows the value of checkable bank deposits. This fell sharply, through the multiplier process we have just analyzed, when individuals pulled their cash out of banks. Loans also fell because banks that survived the waves of bank runs increased their excess reserves, just in case another wave began. The fourth column shows the value of M1, the first of the monetary aggregates we described earlier. It fell sharply because the total reduction in checkable or near-checkable bank deposits was much larger than the increase in currency in circulation.</p>
<table id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-tab-2" block_type="table" numbered="false" caption-placement="Top" data-href="asset/ch18/table_18_2.html" data-target="_pop">
<table_caption><strong><phrase block_type="tbl">TABLE</phrase> <phrase block_type="tbl_num">18-2</phrase></strong> <phrase block_type="tbl_title">The Effects of Bank Runs, 1929&#8211;1933</phrase></table_caption>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td><strong>Currency in<br/>circulation</strong></td>
<td><strong>Checkable<br/>bank deposits</strong></td>
<td><strong>M1</strong></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td colspan="3"><strong>(billions of dollars)</strong></td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tabl-rborder">1929</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">&#36;3.90</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">&#36;22.74</td>
<td>&#36;26.64</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-dark">
<td class="tabl-rborder">1933</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">5.09</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">14.82</td>
<td>19.91</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tabl-rborder">Percent change</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">&#43;31&#37;</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">&#8722;35&#37;</td>
<td>&#8722;25&#37;</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p161" block_type="tb-2-sc"><em>Data from:</em> U.S. Census Bureau (1975), <em>Historical Statistics of the United States.</em></p>
</box>
<box title="Quick Review" numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-bx5-3" block_type="sr-1-h">
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-list-5" type="unordered" block_type="redbullet">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p162" block_type="sr1-bl">Banks create money when they lend out <strong>excess reserves,</strong> generating a multiplier effect on the money supply.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p163" block_type="sr1-bl">In a checkable-deposits-only system, the money supply would be equal to bank reserves divided by the reserve ratio. In reality, however, the public holds some funds as cash rather than in checkable deposits, which reduces the size of the multiplier.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p164" block_type="sr1-bl">The <strong>monetary base,</strong> equal to bank reserves plus currency in circulation, overlaps but is not equal to the money supply. The <strong>money multiplier</strong> is equal to the money supply divided by the monetary base.</p></li>
</list>
</box>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-bx6-3" block_type="sr2-h">
<box-metadata><box-title><phrase block_type="title">Check Your Understanding</phrase> <phrase block_type="number">18-3</phrase></box-title></box-metadata>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-cyuquestion-6" block_type="q_cyu" number="1">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p165" block_type="sr2-nl-first"><phrase block_type="qnum">1.</phrase> Assume that total reserves are equal to &#36;200 and total checkable bank deposits are equal to &#36;1,000. Also assume that the public does not hold any currency. Now suppose that the required reserve ratio falls from 20&#37; to 10&#37;. Trace out how this leads to an expansion in bank deposits.</p>
</question>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-cyuquestion-7" block_type="q_cyu" number="2">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p166" block_type="sr2-nl-last"><phrase block_type="qnum">2.</phrase> Take the example of Silas depositing his &#36;1,000 in cash into First Street Bank and assume that the required reserve ratio is 10&#37;. But now assume that each time someone receives a bank loan, he or she keeps half the loan in cash. Trace out the resulting expansion in the money supply.</p>
</question>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p167" block_type="sr2-nl-fn">Solutions appear at back of book.</p>
</box>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-sec1-4" block_type="h1" title="" chapter="18" numbered="true" level="1" print_page="521">
<section-metadata><section-title>The Federal Reserve System</section-title></section-metadata>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-exp3-24" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p168" block_type="mn-gl-def">A <strong>central bank</strong> is an institution that oversees and regulates the banking system and controls the monetary base.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p169" block_type="txt-ni">Who&#8217;s in charge of ensuring that banks maintain enough reserves? Who decides how large the monetary base will be? The answer, in the United States, is an institution known as the Federal Reserve (or, informally, as <em>the Fed</em>). The Federal Reserve is a <strong>central bank</strong>&#8212;an institution that oversees and regulates the banking system and controls the monetary base. Other central banks include the Bank of England, the Bank of Japan, and the European Central Bank, or ECB. The ECB acts as a common central bank for 18 European countries: Austria, Belgium, Cyprus, Estonia, Finland, France, Germany, Greece, Ireland, Italy, Latvia, Luxembourg, Malta, the Netherlands, Portugal, Slovakia, Slovenia, and Spain. The world&#8217;s oldest central bank, by the way, is Sweden&#8217;s Sveriges Riksbank, which awards the Nobel Prize in economics.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_522" block_type="page_start">522</p>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-sec2-11" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="18" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="522">
<section-metadata><section-title>The Structure of the Fed</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p170" block_type="txt-ni">The legal status of the Fed, which was created in 1913, is unusual: it is not exactly part of the U.S. government, but it is not really a private institution either. Strictly speaking, the Federal Reserve system consists of two parts: the Board of Governors and the 12 regional Federal Reserve Banks.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p171" block_type="txt">The Board of Governors, which oversees the entire system from its offices in Washington, D.C., is constituted like a government agency: its seven members are appointed by the president and must be approved by the Senate. However, they are appointed for 14-year terms, to insulate them from political pressure in their conduct of monetary policy. Although the chair is appointed more frequently&#8212;every four years&#8212;it&#8217;s traditional for chairs to be reappointed and serve much longer terms. For example, William McChesney Martin was chair of the Fed from 1951 until 1970. Alan Greenspan, appointed in 1987, served as the Fed&#8217;s chair until 2006, and Ben Bernanke, Greenspan&#8217;s successor, served until 2014.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p172" block_type="txt">The 12 Federal Reserve Banks each serve a region of the country, providing various banking and supervisory services. One of their jobs, for example, is to audit the books of private-sector banks to ensure their financial health. Each regional bank is run by a board of directors chosen from the local banking and business community. The Federal Reserve Bank of New York plays a special role: it carries out <em>open-market operations,</em> usually the main tool of monetary policy. <link href="asset/ch18/KrugESS4e_fig_18_06.html">Figure 18-6</link> shows the 12 Federal Reserve districts and the city in which each regional Federal Reserve Bank is located.</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-fig-15" block_type="map" numbered="true" number="18-6" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<caption><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-fig-15"><phrase block_type="fig-lable"><phrase block_type="fig"><strong>FIGURE</strong></phrase></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_num"><strong>18-6</strong></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_title">The Federal Reserve System</phrase></link></caption>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-img-23" alt="image" src="asset/ch18/KrugESS4e_fig_18_06.jpg"/>
<caption>The Federal Reserve system consists of the Board of Governors in Washington, D.C., plus 12 regional Federal Reserve Banks. This map shows each of the 12 Federal Reserve districts.</caption>
<asset_source><em>Data from:</em> Board of Governors of the Federal Reserve System.</asset_source>
</figure>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p173" block_type="txt">Decisions about monetary policy are made by the Federal Open Market Committee, which consists of the Board of Governors plus five of the regional bank presidents. The president of the Federal Reserve Bank of New York is always on the committee, and the other four seats rotate among the 11 other regional bank presidents. The chairman of the Board of Governors normally also serves as the chairman of the Open Market Committee.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p174" block_type="txt">The effect of this complex structure is to create an institution that is ultimately accountable to the voting public because the Board of Governors is chosen by the president and confirmed by the Senate, all of whom are themselves elected officials. But the long terms served by board members, as well as the indirectness of their appointment process, largely insulate them from short-term political pressures.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_523" block_type="page_start">523</p>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-sec2-12" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="18" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="523">
<section-metadata><section-title>What the Fed Does: Reserve Requirements and the Discount Rate</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p175" block_type="txt-ni">The Fed has three main policy tools at its disposal: <em>reserve requirements,</em> the <em>discount rate,</em> and, most importantly, <em>open-market operations.</em></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p176" block_type="txt">In our discussion of bank runs, we noted that the Fed sets a minimum reserve ratio requirement, currently equal to 10&#37; for checkable bank deposits. Banks that fail to maintain at least the required reserve ratio on average over a two-week period face penalties.</p>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-exp3-25" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p177" block_type="mn-gl-def">The <strong>federal funds market</strong> allows banks that fall short of the reserve requirement to borrow funds from banks with excess reserves.</p>
</box>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-exp3-26" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p178" block_type="mn-gl-def">The <strong>federal funds rate</strong> is the interest rate determined in the federal funds market.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p179" block_type="txt">What does a bank do if it looks as if it has insufficient reserves to meet the Fed&#8217;s reserve requirement? Normally, it borrows additional reserves from other banks via the <strong>federal funds market,</strong> a financial market that allows banks that fall short of the reserve requirement to borrow reserves (usually just overnight) from banks that are holding excess reserves. The interest rate in this market is determined by supply and demand&#8212;but the supply and demand for bank reserves are both strongly affected by Federal Reserve actions. As we&#8217;ll see in the next chapter, the <strong>federal funds rate,</strong> the interest rate at which funds are borrowed and lent in the federal funds market, plays a key role in modern monetary policy.</p>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-exp3-27" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p180" block_type="mn-gl-def">The <strong>discount rate</strong> is the rate of interest the Fed charges on loans to banks.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p181" block_type="txt">Alternatively, banks in need of reserves can borrow from the Fed itself via the <em>discount window.</em> The <strong>discount rate</strong> is the rate of interest the Fed charges on those loans. Normally, the discount rate is set 1 percentage point above the federal funds rate in order to discourage banks from turning to the Fed when they are in need of reserves.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p182" block_type="txt">Beginning in the fall of 2007, however, the Fed reduced the spread between the federal funds rate and the discount rate as part of its response to an ongoing financial crisis, described in the upcoming Economics in Action. As a result, by the spring of 2008 the discount rate was only 0.25 percentage point above the federal funds rate. And in the summer of 2014 the discount rate was still only 0.65 percentage point above the federal funds rate.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p183" block_type="txt">In order to alter the money supply, the Fed can change reserve requirements, the discount rate, or both. If the Fed reduces reserve requirements, banks will lend a larger percentage of their deposits, leading to more loans and an increase in the money supply via the money multiplier. Alternatively, if the Fed increases reserve requirements, banks are forced to reduce their lending, leading to a fall in the money supply via the money multiplier. </p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p184" block_type="txt">If the Fed reduces the spread between the discount rate and the federal funds rate, the cost to banks of being short of reserves falls; banks respond by increasing their lending, and the money supply increases via the money multiplier. If the Fed increases the spread between the discount rate and the federal funds rate, bank lending falls&#8212;and so will the money supply via the money multiplier.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p185" block_type="txt">Under current practice, however, the Fed doesn&#8217;t use changes in reserve requirements to actively manage the money supply. The last significant change in reserve requirements was in 1992. The Fed normally doesn&#8217;t use the discount rate either, although, as we mentioned earlier, there was a temporary surge in lending through the discount window beginning in 2007 in response to a financial crisis. Ordinarily, monetary policy is conducted almost exclusively using the Fed&#8217;s third policy tool: open-market operations.</p>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-sec2-13" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="18" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="523">
<section-metadata><section-title>Open-Market Operations</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p186" block_type="txt-ni">Like the banks it oversees, the Federal Reserve has assets and liabilities. The Fed&#8217;s assets normally consist of holdings of debt issued by the U.S. government, mainly short-term U.S. government bonds with a maturity of less than one year, known as U.S. Treasury bills. Remember, the Fed isn&#8217;t exactly part of the U.S. government, so U.S. Treasury bills held by the Fed are a liability of the government but an asset of the Fed. The Fed&#8217;s liabilities consist of currency in circulation and bank reserves. <link href="asset/ch18/KrugESS4e_fig_18_07.html">Figure 18-7</link> summarizes the normal assets and liabilities of the Fed in the form of a T-account.</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-fig-16" block_type="figure" numbered="true" number="18-7" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="right" width="medium" border="true"/>
<caption><phrase block_type="fig-lable"><phrase block_type="fig"><strong>FIGURE</strong></phrase></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_num"><strong>18-7</strong></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_title">The Federal Reserve&#8217;s Assets And Liabilities</phrase></caption>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-img-24" alt="image" src="asset/ch18/KrugESS4e_fig_18_07.jpg"/>
<caption>The Federal Reserve holds its assets mostly in short-term government bonds called U.S. Treasury bills. Its liabilities are the monetary base&#8212;currency in circulation plus bank reserves.</caption>
</figure>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_524" block_type="page_start">524</p>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-exp3-28" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p187" block_type="mn-gl-def">An <strong>open-market operation</strong> is a purchase or sale of government debt by the Fed.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p188" block_type="txt">In an <strong>open-market operation</strong> the Federal Reserve buys or sells U.S. Treasury bills, normally through a transaction with <em>commercial banks&#8212;</em>banks that mainly make business loans, as opposed to home loans. The Fed never buys U.S. Treasury bills directly from the federal government. There&#8217;s a good reason for this: when a central bank buys government debt directly from the government, it is lending directly to the government&#8212;in effect, the central bank is printing money to finance the government&#8217;s budget deficit. This has historically been a formula for disastrously high levels of inflation.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p189" block_type="txt">The two panels of <link href="asset/ch18/KrugESS4e_fig_18_08.html">Figure 18-8</link> show the changes in the financial position of both the Fed and commercial banks that result from open-market operations. When the Fed buys U.S. Treasury bills from a commercial bank, it pays by crediting the bank&#8217;s reserve account by an amount equal to the value of the Treasury bills. This is illustrated in panel (a): the Fed buys &#36;100 million of U.S. Treasury bills from commercial banks, which increases the monetary base by &#36;100 million because it increases bank reserves by &#36;100 million. When the Fed sells U.S. Treasury bills to commercial banks, it debits the banks&#8217; accounts, reducing their reserves. This is shown in panel (b), where the Fed sells &#36;100 million of U.S. Treasury bills. Here, bank reserves and the monetary base decrease.</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-fig-17" block_type="figure" numbered="true" number="18-8a" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<caption><link href="asset/ch18/KrugESS4e_fig_18_08.html"><phrase block_type="fig-lable"><phrase block_type="fig"><strong>FIGURE</strong></phrase></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_num">18-8</phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_title">Open-Market Operations by the Federal Reserve</phrase></link></caption>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-img-25" alt="image" src="asset/ch18/KrugESS4e_fig_18_08a.jpg"/>
</figure>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-fig-18" block_type="figure" numbered="true" number="18-8b" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-img-26" alt="image" src="asset/ch18/KrugESS4e_fig_18_08b.jpg"/>
<caption>In panel (a), the Federal Reserve increases the monetary base by purchasing U.S. Treasury bills from private commercial banks in an open-market operation. Here, a &#36;100 million purchase of U.S. Treasury bills by the Federal Reserve is paid for by a &#36;100 million addition to private bank reserves, generating a &#36;100 million increase in the monetary base. This will ultimately lead to an increase in the money supply via the money multiplier as banks lend out some of these new reserves. In panel (b), the Federal Reserve reduces the monetary base by selling U.S. Treasury bills to private commercial banks in an open-market operation. Here, a &#36;100 million sale of U.S. Treasury bills leads to a &#36;100 million reduction in private bank reserves, resulting in a &#36;100 million decrease in the monetary base. This will ultimately lead to a fall in the money supply via the money multiplier as banks reduce their loans in response to a fall in their reserves.</caption>
</figure>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_525" block_type="page_start">525</p>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-bx3-3" block_type="bx3-h">
<box-metadata><box-title><phrase block_type="title">FOR INQUIRING MINDS</phrase> &#124; <strong>Who Gets the Interest on the Fed&#8217;s Assets?</strong> <image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-img-27" alt="image" src="asset/images/world_view_icon.jpg"/></box-title></box-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p190" block_type="bx3-txt-ni">As we&#8217;ve just learned, the Fed owns a lot of assets&#8212;Treasury bills&#8212;that it bought from commercial banks in exchange for monetary base in the form of credits to banks&#8217; reserve accounts. These assets pay interest. Yet the Fed&#8217;s liabilities consist mainly of the monetary base, liabilities on which the Fed normally <em>doesn&#8217;t</em> pay interest. So the Fed is, in effect, an institution that has the privilege of borrowing funds at a zero interest rate and lending them out at a positive interest rate. That sounds like a pretty profitable business. Who gets the profits?</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p191" block_type="bx3-txt">The answer is, you do&#8212;or rather, U.S. taxpayers do. The Fed keeps some of the interest it receives to finance its operations but turns most of it over to the U.S. Treasury. For example, in 2015 the total income of the Federal Reserve system was &#36;100.2 billion, almost all in the form of interest on its assets, of which &#36;97.7 billion was returned to the Treasury. </p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p192" block_type="bx3-txt">We can now finish the chapter&#8217;s opening story&#8212;the impact of those forged dollars printed in Peru. When, say, a fake &#36;20 bill enters circulation, it has the same economic effect as a real &#36;20 bill printed by the U.S. government. That is, as long as nobody catches the forgery, the fake bill serves, for all practical purposes, as part of the monetary base.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p193" block_type="bx3-txt">Meanwhile, the Fed decides on the size of the monetary base based on economic considerations&#8212;in particular, the Fed normally doesn&#8217;t let the monetary base get too large because that can cause higher inflation. So every fake &#36;20 bill that enters circulation means that the Fed prints one less real &#36;20 bill. When the Fed prints a &#36;20 bill legally, however, it gets Treasury bills in return&#8212;and the interest on those bills helps pay for the U.S. government&#8217;s expenses.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p194" block_type="bx3-txt">So a counterfeit &#36;20 bill reduces the amount of Treasury bills the Fed can acquire and thereby reduces the interest payments going to the Fed and the U.S. Treasury. Taxpayers, then, bear the real cost of counterfeiting.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p195" block_type="txt">You might wonder where the Fed gets the funds to purchase U.S. Treasury bills from banks. The answer is that it simply creates them with a stroke of the pen&#8212;or, more likely, a click of the mouse&#8212;that credits the banks&#8217; accounts with extra reserves. (The Fed prints money to pay for Treasury bills only when banks want the additional reserves in the form of currency.) Remember, the modern dollar is fiat money, which isn&#8217;t backed by anything. So the Fed can create additional monetary base at its own discretion.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p196" block_type="txt">The change in bank reserves caused by an open-market operation doesn&#8217;t directly affect the money supply. Instead, it starts the money multiplier in motion. After the &#36;100 million increase in reserves shown in panel (a) of <link href="asset/ch18/KrugESS4e_fig_18_08.html">Figure 18-8</link>, commercial banks would lend out their additional reserves, immediately increasing the money supply by &#36;100 million. Some of those loans would be deposited back into the banking system, increasing reserves again and permitting a further round of loans, and so on, leading to a rise in the money supply. An open-market sale has the reverse effect: bank reserves fall, requiring banks to reduce their loans, leading to a fall in the money supply.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p197" block_type="txt">Economists often say, loosely, that the Fed controls the money supply&#8212;checkable deposits plus currency in circulation. In fact, it controls only the monetary base&#8212;bank reserves plus currency in circulation. But by increasing or reducing the monetary base, the Fed can exert a powerful influence on both the money supply and interest rates. This influence is the basis of monetary policy, the subject of our next chapter.</p>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-sec2-14" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="18" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="525">
<section-metadata><section-title>The European Central Bank</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p198" block_type="txt-ni">The Fed is only one of a number of central banks around the world, and it&#8217;s much younger than Sweden&#8217;s Sveriges Riksbank and Britain&#8217;s Bank of England. In general, other central banks operate in much the same way as the Fed. That&#8217;s especially true of the only other central bank that rivals the Fed in terms of importance to the world economy: the European Central Bank.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_526" block_type="page_start">526</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p199" block_type="txt">The European Central Bank, known as the ECB, was created in January 1999 when 11 European nations abandoned their national currencies and adopted the euro as their common currency and placed their joint monetary policy in the ECB&#8217;s hands. (Eight more countries have joined since 1999.)</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p200" block_type="txt">The ECB instantly became an extremely important institution: although no single European nation has an economy anywhere near as large as that of the United States, the combined economies of the eurozone, the group of countries that have adopted the euro as their currency, are roughly as big as the U.S. economy. As a result, the ECB and the Fed are the two giants of the monetary world.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p201" block_type="txt">Like the Fed, the ECB has a special status: it&#8217;s not a private institution, but it&#8217;s not exactly a government agency either. In fact, it can&#8217;t be a government agency because there is no pan-European government! Luckily for puzzled Americans, there are strong analogies between European central banking and the Federal Reserve system.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p202" block_type="txt">First of all, the ECB, which is located in the German city of Frankfurt, isn&#8217;t really the counterpart of the whole Federal Reserve system: it&#8217;s the equivalent of the Board of Governors in Washington. The European counterparts of the regional Federal Reserve Banks are Europe&#8217;s national central banks: the Bank of France, the Bank of Italy, and so on. Until 1999, each of these national banks was its country&#8217;s equivalent to the Fed. For example, the Bank of France controlled the French monetary base.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p203" block_type="txt">Today these national banks, like regional Feds, provide various financial services to local banks and businesses and conduct open-market operations, but the making of monetary policy has moved upstream to the ECB. Still, the various European national central banks aren&#8217;t small institutions: in total, they employ more than 50,000 people; in 2014, the ECB employed only around 2,000.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p204" block_type="txt">In the eurozone, each country chooses who runs its own national central bank. The ECB&#8217;s Executive Board is the counterpart of the Fed&#8217;s Board of Governors; its members are chosen by unanimous consent of the eurozone national governments. The counterpart of the Federal Open Market Committee is the ECB&#8217;s Governing Council. Just as the Fed&#8217;s Open Market Committee consists of the Board of Governors plus a rotating group of regional Fed presidents, the ECB&#8217;s Governing Council consists of the Executive Board plus the heads of the national central banks.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p205" block_type="txt">Like the Fed, the ECB is ultimately answerable to voters, but given the fragmentation of political forces across national boundaries, it appears to be even more insulated than the Fed from short-term political pressures.</p>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-bx2-4" block_type="bx-2-h">
<box-metadata><box-title><phrase block_type="title">ECONOMICS</phrase> <phrase block_type="number"><em>in Action</em></phrase></box-title></box-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p206" block_type="bx-2-t"><strong>The Fed&#8217;s Balance Sheet, Normal and Abnormal</strong></p>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-exp2-5" block_type="mn2">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p207" block_type="fg1-t"><image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-img-28" alt="image" src="asset/images/launchpad_logo_cmyk.jpg"/> &#124; interactive activity</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p208" block_type="bx2-first"><phrase block_type="dropcap">F</phrase>igure 18-7 showed a simplified version of the Fed&#8217;s balance sheet. Here, liabilities consisted entirely of the monetary base and assets consisted entirely of Treasury bills. This is an oversimplification because the Fed&#8217;s operations are more complicated in reality and its balance sheet contains a number of additional things. But, in normal times, <link href="asset/ch18/KrugESS4e_fig_18_07.html">Figure 18-7</link> is a reasonable approximation: the monetary base typically accounts for 90&#37; of the Fed&#8217;s liabilities, and 90&#37; of its assets are in the form of claims on the U.S. Treasury (as in Treasury bills).</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p209" block_type="bx2-txt">But in late 2007 it became painfully clear that we were no longer in normal times. The source of the turmoil was the bursting of a huge housing bubble, which led to massive losses for financial institutions that had made mortgage loans or held mortgage-related assets. This led to a widespread loss of confidence in the financial system.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_527" block_type="page_start">527</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p210" block_type="bx2-txt">As we&#8217;ll describe in more detail in the next section, not only standard deposit-taking banks were in trouble, but also nondepository financial institutions&#8212;financial institutions that did not accept customer deposits. Because they carried a lot of debt, faced huge losses from the collapse of the housing bubble, and held illiquid assets, panic hit these &#8220;nonbank banks.&#8221; Within hours the financial system was frozen as financial institutions experienced what were essentially bank runs. </p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p211" block_type="bx2-txt">For example, in 2008, many investors became worried about the health of Bear Stearns, a Wall Street nondepository financial institution that engaged in complex financial deals, buying and selling financial assets with borrowed funds. When confidence in Bear Stearns dried up, the firm found itself unable to raise the funds it needed to deliver on its end of these deals and it quickly spiraled into collapse.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p212" block_type="bx2-txt">The Fed sprang into action to contain what was becoming a meltdown across the entire financial sector. It greatly expanded its discount window&#8212;making huge loans to deposit-taking banks as well as nondepository financial institutions such as Wall Street financial firms. This gave financial institutions the liquidity that the financial market had now denied them. And as these firms took advantage of the ability to borrow cheaply from the Fed, they pledged their assets on hand as collateral&#8212;a motley collection of real estate loans, business loans, and so on.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p213" block_type="bx2-txt">Examining <link href="asset/ch18/KrugESS4e_fig_18_09.html">Figure 18-9</link>, we see that starting in mid-2008, the Fed sharply reduced its holdings of traditional securities like Treasury bills, as its lending to financial institutions skyrocketed. &#8220;Lending to financial institutions&#8221; refers to discount window lending, but also loans the Fed made directly to firms like Bear Stearns. &#8220;Liquidity to key credit markets&#8221; covers purchases by the Fed of assets like corporate bonds, which were necessary to keep interest rates on loans to firms from soaring. Finally, &#8220;Federal agency debt&#8221; is the debt of Fannie Mae and Freddie Mac, the government-sponsored home mortgage agencies, which the Fed was also compelled to buy in order to prevent collapse in the mortgage market.</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-fig-19" block_type="figure" numbered="true" number="18-9" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<caption><phrase block_type="fig-lable"><phrase block_type="fig"><strong>FIGURE</strong></phrase></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_num"><strong>18-9</strong></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_title">The Federal Reserve&#8217;s Assets</phrase></caption>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-img-29" alt="image" src="asset/ch18/KrugESS4e_fig_18_09.jpg"/>
<asset_source><em>Data from:</em> Federal Reserve Bank of Cleveland.</asset_source>
</figure>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p214" block_type="bx2-txt">As the crisis subsided in late 2009, the Fed didn&#8217;t return to its traditional asset holdings. Instead, it shifted into long-term Treasury bills and increased its purchases of Federal agency debt. The whole episode was very unusual&#8212;a major departure from the way in which the Fed normally conducts business, but one that it deemed necessary to stave off financial and economic collapse. It was also a graphic illustration of the fact that the Fed does much more than just determine the size of the monetary base.</p>
</box>
<box title="Quick Review" numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-bx5-4" block_type="sr-1-h">
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-list-6" type="unordered" block_type="redbullet">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p215" block_type="sr1-bl">The Federal Reserve is America&#8217;s <strong>central bank,</strong> overseeing banking and making monetary policy.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p216" block_type="sr1-bl">The Fed sets the required reserve ratio. Banks borrow and lend reserves in the <strong>federal funds market.</strong> The interest rate determined in this market is the <strong>federal funds rate.</strong> Banks can also borrow from the Fed at the <strong>discount rate.</strong></p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p217" block_type="sr1-bl">Although the Fed can change reserve requirements or the discount rate, in practice, monetary policy is conducted using <strong>open-market operations.</strong></p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p218" block_type="sr1-bl">An open-market purchase of Treasury bills increases the monetary base and therefore the money supply. An open-market sale reduces the monetary base and the money supply.</p></li>
</list>
</box>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-bx6-4" block_type="sr2-h">
<box-metadata><box-title><phrase block_type="title">Check Your Understanding</phrase> <phrase block_type="number">18-4</phrase></box-title></box-metadata>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-cyuquestion-8" block_type="q_cyu" number="1">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p219" block_type="sr2-nl-first"><phrase block_type="qnum">1.</phrase> Assume that any money lent by a bank is always deposited back in the banking system as a checkable deposit and that the reserve ratio is 10&#37;. Trace out the effects of a &#36;100 million open-market purchase of U.S. Treasury bills by the Fed on the value of checkable bank deposits. What is the size of the money multiplier?</p>
</question>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p220" block_type="sr2-nl-fn">Solution appears at back of book.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_528" block_type="page_start">528</p>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-sec1-5" block_type="h1" title="" chapter="18" numbered="true" level="1" print_page="528">
<section-metadata><section-title>The Evolution of the American Banking System</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p221" block_type="txt-ni">Up to this point, we have been describing the U.S. banking system and how it works. To fully understand that system, however, it is helpful to understand how and why it was created&#8212;a story that is closely intertwined with the story of how and when things went wrong. The key elements of twenty-first-century U.S. banking weren&#8217;t created out of thin air: efforts to change both the regulations that govern banking and the Federal Reserve system that began in 2008 have propelled financial reform to the forefront. This reform promises to continue reshaping the financial system well into future years.</p>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-sec2-15" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="18" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="528">
<section-metadata><section-title>The Crisis in American Banking in the Early Twentieth Century</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p222" block_type="txt-ni">The creation of the Federal Reserve system in 1913 marked the beginning of the modern era of American banking. From 1864 until 1913, American banking was dominated by a federally regulated system of national banks. They alone were allowed to issue currency, and the currency notes they issued were printed by the federal government with uniform size and design. How much currency a national bank could issue depended on its capital. Although this system was an improvement on the earlier period in which banks issued their own notes with no uniformity and virtually no regulation, the national banking regime still suffered numerous bank failures and major financial crises&#8212;at least one and often two per decade.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p223" block_type="txt">The main problem afflicting the system was that the money supply was not sufficiently responsive: it was difficult to shift currency around the country to respond quickly to local economic changes. (In particular, there was often a tug of war between New York City banks and rural banks for adequate amounts of currency.) Rumors that a bank had insufficient currency to satisfy demands for withdrawals would quickly lead to a bank run. A bank run would then spark a contagion, setting off runs at other nearby banks, sowing widespread panic and devastation in the local economy. In response, bankers in some locations pooled their resources to create local clearinghouses that would jointly guarantee a member&#8217;s liabilities in the event of a panic, and some state governments began offering deposit insurance on their banks&#8217; deposits.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p224" block_type="txt">However, the cause of the Panic of 1907 was different from those of previous crises; in fact, its cause was eerily similar to the roots of the 2008 crisis. Ground zero of the 1907 panic was New York City, but the consequences devastated the entire country, leading to a deep four-year recession.</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-fig-20" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="right" width="medium" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-img-30" alt="image" src="asset/ch18/KrugESS4e_18UN08.jpg"/>
<caption>In both the Panic of 1907 and the financial crisis of 2008, large losses from risky speculation destabilized the banking system.</caption>
<asset_source>The Pierpont Morgan Library/Art Resource, NY</asset_source>
</figure>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p225" block_type="txt">The crisis originated in institutions in New York known as trusts, bank-like institutions that accepted deposits but that were originally intended to manage only inheritances and estates for wealthy clients. Because these trusts were supposed to engage only in low-risk activities, they were less regulated, had lower reserve requirements, and had lower cash reserves than national banks.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p226" block_type="txt">However, as the American economy boomed during the first decade of the twentieth century, trusts began speculating in real estate and the stock market, areas of speculation forbidden to national banks. Less regulated than national banks, trusts were able to pay their depositors higher returns. Yet trusts took a free ride on national banks&#8217; reputation for soundness, with depositors considering them equally safe. As a result, trusts grew rapidly: by 1907, the total assets of trusts in New York City were as large as those of national banks. Meanwhile, the trusts declined to join the New York Clearinghouse, a consortium of New York City national banks that guaranteed one anothers&#8217; soundness; that would have required the trusts to hold higher cash reserves, reducing their profits.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_529" block_type="page_start">529</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p227" block_type="txt">The Panic of 1907 began with the failure of the Knickerbocker Trust, a large New York City trust that failed when it suffered massive losses in unsuccessful stock market speculation. Quickly, other New York trusts came under pressure, and frightened depositors began queuing in long lines to withdraw their funds. The New York Clearinghouse declined to step in and lend to the trusts, and even healthy trusts came under serious assault. Within two days, a dozen major trusts had gone under. Credit markets froze, and the stock market fell dramatically as stock traders were unable to get credit to finance their trades and business confidence evaporated.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p228" block_type="txt">Fortunately, New York City&#8217;s wealthiest man, the banker J. P. Morgan, quickly stepped in to stop the panic. Understanding that the crisis was spreading and would soon engulf healthy institutions, trusts and banks alike, he worked with other bankers, wealthy men such as John D. Rockefeller, and the U.S. Secretary of the Treasury to shore up the reserves of banks and trusts so they could withstand the onslaught of withdrawals. Once people were assured that they could withdraw their money, the panic ceased. Although the panic itself lasted little more than a week, it and the stock market collapse decimated the economy. A four-year recession ensued, with production falling 11&#37; and unemployment rising from 3&#37; to 8&#37;.</p>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-sec2-16" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="18" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="529">
<section-metadata><section-title>Responding to Banking Crises: The Creation of the Federal Reserve</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p229" block_type="txt-ni">Concerns over the frequency of banking crises and the unprecedented role of J. P. Morgan in saving the financial system prompted the federal government to initiate banking reform. In 1913 the national banking system was eliminated and the Federal Reserve system was created as a way to compel all deposit-taking institutions to hold adequate reserves and to open their accounts to inspection by regulators. The Panic of 1907 convinced many that the time for centralized control of bank reserves had come. In addition, the Federal Reserve was given the sole right to issue currency in order to make the money supply sufficiently responsive to satisfy economic conditions around the country.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p230" block_type="txt">Although the new regime standardized and centralized the holding of bank reserves, it did not eliminate the potential for bank runs because banks&#8217; reserves were still less than the total value of their deposits. The potential for more bank runs became a reality during the Great Depression. Plunging commodity prices hit American farmers particularly hard, precipitating a series of bank runs in 1930, 1931, and 1933, each of which started at midwestern banks and then spread throughout the country.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p231" block_type="txt">After the failure of a particularly large bank in 1930, federal officials realized that the economy-wide effects compelled them to take a less hands-off approach and to intervene more vigorously. In 1932, the Reconstruction Finance Corporation (RFC) was established and given the authority to make loans to banks in order to stabilize the banking sector. Also, the Glass-Steagall Act of 1933, which created federal deposit insurance and increased the ability of banks to borrow from the Federal Reserve system, was passed. However, the beast had not yet been tamed. Banks became fearful of borrowing from the RFC because doing so signaled weakness to the public. </p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p232" block_type="txt">As we noted earlier, during the catastrophic bank run of 1933, the new president, Franklin Delano Roosevelt, was inaugurated. He immediately declared a &#8220;bank holiday,&#8221; closing all banks until regulators could get a handle on the problem.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p233" block_type="txt">In March 1933, emergency measures were adopted that gave the RFC extraordinary powers to stabilize and restructure the banking industry by providing capital to banks through either loans or outright purchases of bank shares. With the new rules, regulators closed nonviable banks and recapitalized viable ones by allowing the RFC to buy preferred shares in banks (shares that gave the U.S. government more rights than regular shareholders) and by greatly expanding banks&#8217; ability to borrow from the Federal Reserve. By 1933, the RFC had invested over &#36;16.2 billion (2010 dollars) in bank capital&#8212;one-third of the total capital of all banks in the United States at that time&#8212;and purchased shares in almost one-half of all banks. The RFC loaned more than &#36;32.4 billion (2010 dollars) to banks during this period.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_530" block_type="page_start">530</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p234" block_type="txt">Economic historians uniformly agree that the banking crises of the early 1930s greatly exacerbated the severity of the Great Depression, rendering monetary policy ineffective as the banking sector broke down and currency, withdrawn from banks and stashed under beds, reduced the money supply.</p>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-exp3-29" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p235" block_type="mn-gl-def">A <strong>commercial bank</strong> accepts deposits and is covered by deposit insurance.</p>
</box>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-exp3-30" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p236" block_type="mn-gl-def">An <strong>investment bank</strong> trades in financial assets and is not covered by deposit insurance.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p237" block_type="txt">Although the powerful actions of the RFC stabilized the banking industry, new legislation was needed to prevent future banking crises. The Glass-Steagall Act of 1933 separated banks into two categories, <strong>commercial banks,</strong> depository banks that accepted deposits and were covered by deposit insurance, and <strong>investment banks,</strong> which engaged in creating and trading financial assets such as stocks and corporate bonds but were not covered by deposit insurance because their activities were considered more risky.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p238" block_type="txt"><em>Regulation Q</em> prevented commercial banks from paying interest on checking accounts in the belief that this would promote unhealthy competition between banks. In addition, investment banks were much more lightly regulated than commercial banks. The most important measure for the prevention of bank runs, however, was the adoption of federal deposit insurance (with an original limit of &#36;2,500 per deposit).</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p239" block_type="txt">These measures were clearly successful, and the United States enjoyed a long period of financial and banking stability. As memories of the bad old days dimmed, Depression-era bank regulations were lifted. In 1980, Regulation Q was eliminated; by 1999, the Glass-Steagall Act had been so weakened that offering services like trading financial assets was no longer off-limits to commercial banks.</p>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-sec2-17" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="18" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="530">
<section-metadata><section-title>The Savings and Loan Crisis of the 1980s</section-title></section-metadata>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-exp3-31" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p240" block_type="mn-gl-def">A <strong>savings and loan (thrift)</strong> is another type of deposit-taking bank, usually specialized in issuing home loans.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p241" block_type="txt-ni">Along with banks, the banking industry also included <strong>savings and loans</strong> (also called S&#38;Ls or <strong>thrifts</strong>), institutions designed to accept savings and turn them into long-term mortgages for home-buyers. S&#38;Ls were covered by federal deposit insurance and were tightly regulated for safety. However, trouble hit in the 1970s, as high inflation led savers to withdraw their funds from low-interest-paying S&#38;L accounts and put them into higher-interest-paying money market accounts. In addition, the high inflation rate severely eroded the value of the S&#38;Ls&#8217; assets, the long-term mortgages they held on their books.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p242" block_type="txt">In order to improve S&#38;Ls&#8217; competitive position vis-&#224;-vis banks, Congress eased regulations to allow S&#38;Ls to undertake much more risky investments in addition to long-term home mortgages. However, the new freedom did not bring with it increased oversight, leaving S&#38;Ls with less oversight than banks. Not surprisingly, during the real estate boom of the 1970s and 1980s, S&#38;Ls engaged in overly risky real estate lending. Also, corruption occurred as some S&#38;L executives used their institutions as private piggy banks.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p243" block_type="txt">Unfortunately, during the late 1970s and early 1980s, political interference from Congress kept insolvent S&#38;Ls open when a bank in a comparable situation would have been quickly shut down by bank regulators. By the early 1980s, a large number of S&#38;Ls had failed. Because accounts were covered by federal deposit insurance, the liabilities of a failed S&#38;L were now liabilities of the federal government, and depositors had to be paid from taxpayer funds. From 1986 through 1995, the federal government closed over 1,000 failed S&#38;Ls, costing U.S. taxpayers over &#36;124 billion.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_531" block_type="page_start">531</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p244" block_type="txt">In a classic case of shutting the barn door after the horse has escaped, in 1989 Congress put in place comprehensive oversight of S&#38;L activities. It also empowered Fannie Mae and Freddie Mac to take over much of the home mortgage lending previously done by S&#38;Ls. <em>Fannie Mae</em> and <em>Freddie Mac</em> are quasi-governmental agencies created during the Great Depression to make homeownership more affordable for low- and moderate-income households. It has been calculated that the S&#38;L crisis helped cause a steep slowdown in the finance and real estate industries, leading to the recession of the early 1990s.</p>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-sec2-18" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="18" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="531">
<section-metadata><section-title>Back to the Future: The Financial Crisis of 2008</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p245" block_type="txt-ni">The financial crisis of 2008 shared features of previous crises. Like the Panic of 1907 and the S&#38;L crisis, it involved institutions that were not as strictly regulated as deposit-taking banks, as well as excessive speculation. Like the crises of the early 1930s, it involved a U.S. government that was reluctant to take aggressive action until the scale of the devastation became clear. </p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p246" block_type="txt">In addition, by the late 1990s, advances in technology and financial innovation had created yet another systemic weakness that played a central role in 2008. The story of Long-Term Capital Management, or LTCM, highlights these problems.</p>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-exp3-32" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p247" block_type="mn-gl-def">A financial institution engages in <strong>leverage</strong> when it finances its investments with borrowed funds.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p248" block_type="txt-3"><phrase block_type="h3"><strong>Long-Term Capital (Mis)Management</strong> </phrase>Created in 1994, LTCM was a hedge fund, a private investment partnership open only to wealthy individuals and institutions. Hedge funds are virtually unregulated, allowing them to make much riskier investments than mutual funds, which are open to the average investor. Using vast amounts of <strong>leverage&#8212;</strong>that is, borrowed money&#8212;in order to increase its returns, LTCM used sophisticated computer models to make money by taking advantage of small differences in asset prices in global financial markets to buy at a lower price and sell at a higher price. In one year, LTCM made a return as high as 40&#37;.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p249" block_type="txt">LTCM was also heavily involved in derivatives, complex financial instruments that are constructed&#8212;derived&#8212;from the obligations of more basic financial assets. Derivatives are popular investment tools because they are cheaper to trade than basic financial assets and can be constructed to suit a buyer&#8217;s or seller&#8217;s particular needs. Yet their complexity can make it extremely hard to measure their value. LTCM believed that its computer models allowed it to accurately gauge the risk in the huge bets that it was undertaking in derivatives using borrowed money.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p250" block_type="txt">However, LTCM&#8217;s computer models hadn&#8217;t factored in a series of financial crises in Asia and in Russia during 1997 and 1998. Through its large borrowing, LTCM had become such a big player in global financial markets that attempts to sell its assets depressed the prices of what it was trying to sell. As the markets fell around the world and LTCM&#8217;s panic-stricken investors demanded the return of their funds, LTCM&#8217;s losses mounted as it tried to sell assets to satisfy those demands. Quickly, its operations collapsed because it could no longer borrow money and other parties refused to trade with it. Financial markets around the world froze in panic.</p>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-exp3-33" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p251" block_type="mn-gl-def">The <strong>balance sheet effect</strong> is the reduction in a firm&#8217;s net worth due to falling asset prices.</p>
</box>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-exp3-34" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p252" block_type="mn-gl-def">A <strong>vicious cycle of deleveraging</strong> takes place when asset sales to cover losses produce negative balance sheet effects on other firms and force creditors to call in their loans, forcing sales of more assets and causing further declines in asset prices.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p253" block_type="txt">The Federal Reserve realized that allowing LTCM&#8217;s remaining assets to be sold at panic-stricken prices presented a grave risk to the entire financial system through the <strong>balance sheet effect:</strong> as sales of assets by LTCM depressed asset prices all over the world, other firms would see the value of their balance sheets fall as assets held on these balance sheets declined in value. Moreover, falling asset prices meant the value of assets held by borrowers on their balance sheets would fall below a critical threshold, leading to a default on the terms of their credit contracts and forcing creditors to call in their loans. This in turn would lead to more sales of assets as borrowers tried to raise cash to repay their loans, more credit defaults, and more loans called in, creating a <strong>vicious cycle of deleveraging.</strong></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_532" block_type="page_start">532</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p254" block_type="txt">The Federal Reserve Bank of New York arranged a &#36;3.625 billion bailout of LTCM in 1998, in which other private institutions took on shares of LTCM&#8217;s assets and obligations, liquidated them in an orderly manner, and eventually turned a small profit. Quick action by the Federal Reserve Bank of New York prevented LTCM from sparking a contagion, yet virtually all of LTCM&#8217;s investors were wiped out.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p255" block_type="txt-3"><phrase block_type="h3"><strong>Subprime Lending and the Housing Bubble</strong> </phrase>After the LTCM crisis, U.S. financial markets stabilized. They remained more or less stable even as stock prices fell sharply from 2000 to 2002 and the U.S. economy went into recession. During the recovery from the 2001 recession, however, the seeds for another financial crisis were planted.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p256" block_type="txt">The story begins with low interest rates: by 2003, U.S. interest rates were at historically low levels, partly because of Federal Reserve policy and partly because of large inflows of capital from other countries, especially China. These low interest rates helped cause a boom in housing, which in turn led the U.S. economy out of recession. As housing boomed, however, financial institutions began taking on growing risks&#8212;risks that were not well understood.</p>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-exp3-35" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p257" block_type="mn-gl-def"><strong>Subprime lending</strong> is lending to home-buyers who don&#8217;t meet the usual criteria for being able to afford their payments.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p258" block_type="txt">Traditionally, people were only able to borrow money to buy homes if they could show that they had sufficient income to meet the mortgage payments. Home loans to people who don&#8217;t meet the usual criteria for borrowing, called <strong>subprime lending,</strong> were only a minor part of overall lending. But in the booming housing market of 2003&#8211;2006, subprime lending started to seem like a safe bet. Since housing prices kept rising, borrowers who couldn&#8217;t make their mortgage payments could always pay off their mortgages, if necessary, by selling their homes. As a result, subprime lending exploded.</p>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-exp3-36" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p259" block_type="mn-gl-def">In <strong>securitization,</strong> a pool of loans is assembled and shares of that pool are sold to investors.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p260" block_type="txt">Who was making these subprime loans? For the most part, it wasn&#8217;t traditional banks lending out depositors&#8217; money. Instead, most of the loans were made by &#8220;loan originators,&#8221; who quickly sold mortgages to other investors. These sales were made possible by a process known as <strong>securitization:</strong> financial institutions assembled pools of loans and sold shares in the income from these pools. These shares were considered relatively safe investments, since it was considered unlikely that large numbers of home-buyers would default on their payments at the same time.</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-fig-21" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="right" width="medium" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-img-31" alt="image" src="asset/ch18/KrugESS4e_18UN09.jpg"/>
<asset_source>The New Yorker Collection 2008 Leo Cullum from <link href="http://cartoonbank.com">cartoonbank.com</link>. All Rights Reserved.</asset_source>
</figure>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p261" block_type="txt">But that&#8217;s exactly what happened. The housing boom turned out to be a bubble, and when home prices started falling in late 2006, many subprime borrowers were unable either to meet their mortgage payments or sell their houses for enough to pay off their mortgages. As a result, investors in securities backed by subprime mortgages started taking heavy losses. Many of the mortgage-backed assets were held by financial institutions, including banks and other institutions playing bank-like roles. Like the trusts that played a key role in the Panic of 1907, these &#8220;nonbank banks&#8221; were less regulated than commercial banks, which allowed them to offer higher returns to investors but left them extremely vulnerable in a crisis. Mortgage-related losses, in turn, led to a collapse of trust in the financial system.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p262" block_type="txt"><link href="asset/ch18/KrugESS4e_fig_18_10.html">Figure 18-10</link> shows one measure of this loss of trust: the TED spread, which is the difference between the interest rate on three-month loans that banks make to each other and the interest rate the federal government pays on three-month bonds. Since government bonds are considered extremely safe, the TED spread shows how much risk banks think they&#8217;re taking on when lending to each other. Normally the spread is around a quarter of a percentage point, but it shot up in August 2007 and surged to an unprecedented 4.58 percentage points in October 2008, before returning to more normal levels in mid-2009. </p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-fig-22" block_type="figure" numbered="true" number="18-10" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<caption><phrase block_type="fig-lable"><phrase block_type="fig"><strong>FIGURE</strong></phrase></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_num"><strong>18-10</strong></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_title">The TED Spread</phrase></caption>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-img-32" alt="image" src="asset/ch18/KrugESS4e_fig_18_10.jpg"/>
<caption>The TED spread is the difference between the interest rate at which banks lend to each other and the interest rate on U.S. government debt. It&#8217;s widely used as a measure of financial stress. The TED spread soared as a result of the financial crisis of 2007&#8211;2008.</caption>
<asset_source><em>Data from:</em> British Bankers&#8217; Association; Federal Reserve Bank of St. Louis.</asset_source>
</figure>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p263" block_type="txt-3"><phrase block_type="h3"><strong>Crisis and Response</strong> </phrase>The collapse of trust in the financial system, combined with the large losses suffered by financial firms, led to a severe cycle of deleveraging and a credit crunch for the economy as a whole. Firms found it difficult to borrow, even for short-term operations; individuals found home loans unavailable and credit card limits reduced.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_533" block_type="page_start">533</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p264" block_type="txt">Overall, the negative economic effect of the financial crisis bore a distinct and troubling resemblance to the effects of the banking crisis of the early 1930s, which helped cause the Great Depression. Policy makers noticed the resemblance and tried to prevent a repeat performance. Beginning in August 2007, the Federal Reserve engaged in a series of efforts to provide cash to the financial system, lending funds to a widening range of institutions and buying private-sector debt. The Fed and the Treasury Department also stepped in to rescue individual firms that were deemed too crucial to be allowed to fail, such as the investment bank Bear Stearns and the insurance company AIG.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p265" block_type="txt">In September 2008, however, policy makers decided that one major investment bank, Lehman Brothers, could be allowed to fail. They quickly regretted the decision. Within days of Lehman&#8217;s failure, widespread panic gripped the financial markets, as illustrated by the surge in the TED spread shown in <link href="asset/ch18/KrugESS4e_fig_18_10.html">Figure 18-10</link>. In response to the intensified crisis, the U.S. government intervened further to support the financial system, as the U.S. Treasury began &#8220;injecting&#8221; capital into banks. Injecting capital, in practice, meant that the U.S. government would supply cash to banks in return for shares&#8212;in effect, partially nationalizing the financial system.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p266" block_type="txt">By the fall of 2010, the financial system appeared to be stabilized, and major institutions had repaid much of the money the federal government had injected during the crisis. It was generally expected that taxpayers would end up losing little if any money. However, the recovery of the banks was not matched by a successful turnaround for the overall economy: although the recession that began in December 2007 officially ended in June 2009, unemployment remained stubbornly high for several years.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p267" block_type="txt">The Federal Reserve responded to this troubled situation with novel forms of open-market operations. Conventional open-market operations are limited to short-term government debt, but the Fed believed that this was no longer enough. It provided massive liquidity through discount window lending, as well as buying large quantities of other assets, mainly long-term government debt and debt of Fannie Mae and Freddie Mac, government-sponsored agencies that support home lending. This explains the surge in Fed assets after September 2008 visible in <link href="asset/ch18/KrugESS4e_fig_18_09.html">Figure 18-9</link>.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p268" block_type="txt">Like earlier crises, the crisis of 2008 led to changes in banking regulation, most notably the Dodd-Frank financial regulatory reform bill enacted in 2010. We discuss that bill in the following Economics in Action.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_534" block_type="page_start">534</p>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-bx2-5" block_type="bx-2-h">
<box-metadata><box-title><phrase block_type="title">ECONOMICS</phrase> <phrase block_type="number"><em>in Action</em></phrase></box-title></box-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p269" block_type="bx-2-t"><strong>Regulation After the 2008 Crisis</strong></p>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-exp2-6" block_type="mn2">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p270" block_type="fg1-t"><image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-img-33" alt="image" src="asset/images/launchpad_logo_cmyk.jpg"/> &#124; interactive activity</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p271" block_type="bx2-first"><phrase block_type="dropcap">I</phrase>n July 2010, President Obama signed the Wall Street Reform and Consumer Protection Act&#8212;generally known as Dodd-Frank, after its sponsors in the Senate and House, respectively&#8212;into law. It was the biggest financial reform enacted since the 1930s&#8212;not surprising given that the nation had just gone through the worst financial crisis since the 1930s. How did it change regulation?</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-fig-23" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="right" width="medium" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-img-34" alt="image" src="asset/ch18/KrugESS4e_18UN10.jpg"/>
<caption>The Wall Street Reform and Consumer Protection Act of 2010 was an attempt to extend the spirit of old-fashioned bank regulation to today&#8217;s more complex financial system.</caption>
<asset_source>Thinkstock</asset_source>
</figure>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p272" block_type="bx2-txt">For the most part, it left regulation of traditional deposit-taking banks more or less as it was. The main change these banks would face was the creation of a new agency, the Bureau of Consumer Financial Protection, whose mission was to protect borrowers from being exploited through seemingly attractive financial deals they didn&#8217;t understand.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p273" block_type="bx2-txt">The major changes came in the regulation of financial institutions other than banks&#8212;institutions that, as the fall of Lehman Brothers showed, could trigger banking crises. The new law gave a special government committee, the Financial Stability Oversight Council, the right to designate certain institutions as &#8220;systemically important&#8221; even if they weren&#8217;t ordinary deposit-taking banks. </p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p274" block_type="bx2-txt">These systemically important institutions would be subjected to bank-style regulation, including relatively high capital requirements and limits on the kinds of risks they could take. In addition, the federal government would acquire &#8220;resolution authority,&#8221; meaning the right to seize troubled financial institutions in much the same way that it routinely takes over troubled banks.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p275" block_type="bx2-txt">Beyond this, the law established new rules on the trading of derivatives, those complex financial instruments that sank LTCM and played an important role in the 2008 crisis as well: most derivatives would henceforth have to be bought and sold on exchanges, where everyone could observe their prices and the volume of transactions. The idea was to make the risks taken by financial institutions more transparent.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p276" block_type="bx2-txt">Overall, Dodd-Frank is probably best seen as an attempt to extend the spirit of old-fashioned bank regulation to the more complex financial system of the twenty-first century. Will it succeed in heading off future banking crises? Stay tuned. </p>
</box>
<box title="Quick Review" numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-bx5-5" block_type="sr-1-h">
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-list-7" type="unordered" block_type="redbullet">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p277" block_type="sr1-bl">The Federal Reserve system was created in response to the Panic of 1907.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p278" block_type="sr1-bl">Widespread bank runs in the early 1930s resulted in greater bank regulation and the creation of federal deposit insurance. Banks were separated into two categories: <strong>commercial</strong> (covered by deposit insurance) and <strong>investment</strong> (not covered).</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p279" block_type="sr1-bl">In the <strong>savings and loan (thrift)</strong> crisis of the 1970s and 1980s, insufficiently regulated S&#38;Ls incurred huge losses from risky speculation.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p280" block_type="sr1-bl">During the mid-1990s, the hedge fund LTCM used huge amounts of <strong>leverage</strong> to speculate in global markets, incurred massive losses, and collapsed. In selling assets to cover its losses, LTCM caused <strong>balance sheet effects</strong> for firms around the world. To prevent a <strong>vicious cycle of deleveraging,</strong> the New York Fed coordinated a private bailout.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p281" block_type="sr1-bl">In the mid-2000s, loans from <strong>subprime lending</strong> spread through the financial system via <strong>securitization,</strong> leading to a financial crisis. The Fed responded by injecting cash into financial institutions and buying private debt.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p282" block_type="sr1-bl">In 2010, the Dodd-Frank bill revised financial regulation in an attempt to prevent repeats of the 2008 crisis.</p></li>
</list>
</box>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-bx6-5" block_type="sr2-h">
<box-metadata><box-title><phrase block_type="title">Check Your Understanding</phrase> <phrase block_type="number">18-5</phrase></box-title></box-metadata>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-cyuquestion-9" block_type="q_cyu" number="1">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p283" block_type="sr2-nl-first"><phrase block_type="qnum">1.</phrase> What are the similarities between the Panic of 1907, the S&#38;L crisis, and the crisis of 2008?</p>
</question>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-cyuquestion-10" block_type="q_cyu" number="2">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p284" block_type="sr2-nl-mid"><phrase block_type="qnum">2.</phrase> Why did the creation of the Federal Reserve fail to prevent the bank runs of the Great Depression? What measures stopped the bank runs?</p>
</question>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-cyuquestion-11" block_type="q_cyu" number="3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p285" block_type="sr2-nl-last"><phrase block_type="qnum">3.</phrase> Describe the balance sheet effect. Describe the vicious cycle of deleveraging. Why is it necessary for the government to step in to halt a vicious cycle of deleveraging?</p>
</question>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p286" block_type="sr2-nl-fn">Solutions appear at back of book.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_535" block_type="page_start">535</p>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-sec1-6" block_type="solved_problem" title="" chapter="18" numbered="true" level="1" print_page="535">
<section-metadata><section-title>Solved problem</section-title></section-metadata>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-bx7-1" block_type="sum-h">
<box-metadata><box-title><phrase block_type="gc1">SOLVED PROBLEM</phrase> <phrase block_type="gc2">Multiplying Money</phrase></box-title></box-metadata>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-exp2-7" block_type="mn2">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p287" block_type="fg1-t"><image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-img-35" alt="image" src="asset/images/launchpad_logo_cmyk.jpg"/> for interactive tutorials with step-by-step guidance on how to solve problems</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p288" block_type="wio-txt-ni">The Economic Stimulus Act of 2008, which we learned about in the previous chapter, was a &#36;787 billion package of spending, aid, and tax cuts intended to help the struggling U.S. economy and reverse a severe recession. It is the most recent example we have of fiscal stimulus in action. As part of this Act, the U.S. government issued tax rebate checks to eligible households. On average, rebate checks totaled &#36;950.00.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p289" block_type="wio-txt">Economists have estimated that each household initially spent about &#36;450.00 of the rebate. Since the public holds about 50&#37; of M1 in the form of currency, the average household deposited about &#36;250.00 of the remaining &#36;500.00 and held the other &#36;250.00 in cash. In light of this data, approximately how much will the money supply increase in response to the average household&#8217;s deposit? (<em>Hint:</em> Create a table that shows the change in the money supply for ten rounds.) Assume that banks lend out the full amount of any excess reserves.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p290" block_type="sp-stp-txt"><phrase block_type="step-green">STEP</phrase> &#124; <phrase block_type="step-green">1</phrase> <phrase block_type="step-title"><strong>Find the required reserve ratio in the United States.</strong>
<phrase block_type="step-subtext">Review pages 513&#8211;514 to find and understand the U.S. reserve ratio.</phrase></phrase></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p291" block_type="wio-txt-ni">The required reserve ratio in the United States is 10&#37;.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p292" block_type="sp-stp-txt"><phrase block_type="step-green">STEP</phrase> &#124; <phrase block_type="step-green">2</phrase> <phrase block_type="step-title"><strong>Make a table that shows on line 1 the initial deposit, the required reserves, the excess reserves, the loans that a bank makes, and the amount held in currency from the initial loans made by the bank.</strong>
<phrase block_type="step-subtext">Review pages 517&#8211;519 to help determine the required reserves, excess reserves, and the loans made.</phrase></phrase></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p293" block_type="wio-txt-ni">The amount held in currency from the initial loans made by the bank is the amount in the loan that &#8220;leaks&#8221; out of the banking system, which is also discussed in the section, &#8220;Reserves, Bank Deposits, and the Money Multiplier.&#8221;</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p294" block_type="wio-txt-ni">The first line of this table is shown here.</p>
<table id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-untab-3" block_type="un_table" data-href="asset/ch18/un_table_18_3.html" data-target="_pop">
<layout align="center" width="large"/>
<tbody>
<tr class="tbl-hdr-bg">
<td><strong>Round</strong></td>
<td><strong>Deposits</strong></td>
<td><strong>Required<br/> reserves</strong></td>
<td><strong>Excess<br/> reserves</strong></td>
<td><strong>Loans</strong></td>
<td><strong>Held as<br/> currency</strong></td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tabl-rborder">1</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">&#36;250.00</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">&#36;25.00</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">&#36;225.00</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">&#36;225.00</td>
<td>&#36;112.50</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p295" block_type="wio-txt-ni">The deposit amount is &#36;250.00. As determined in Step 1, the required reserves are 10&#37; of this deposit amount: 10&#37; &#215; &#36;250.00 = &#36;25.00. The excess reserves are therefore &#36;250.00 &#8722; &#36;25.00 = &#36;225.00. We have assumed that banks loan out all of their excess reserves, so they loan out &#36;225.00. Of this amount, the public will hold 50&#37; in currency: 50&#37; &#215; &#36;225.00 = &#36;112.50.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p296" block_type="sp-stp-txt"><phrase block_type="step-green">STEP</phrase> &#124; <phrase block_type="step-green">3</phrase> <phrase block_type="step-title"><strong>Extend this table for 10 rounds.</strong>
<phrase block_type="step-subtext">Review pages 517&#8211;519.</phrase></phrase></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p297" block_type="wio-txt-ni">If, after the first round, the public has held &#36;112.50 of &#36;225.00 in loans as currency, then the second round will begin with a deposit of &#36;112.50 = &#36;225.00 &#8722; &#36;112.50. Each round begins with the difference between the loan amount and the amount held in currency from the previous round.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_536" block_type="page_start">536</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p298" block_type="wio-txt-ni">The extended table is shown here.</p>
<table id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-untab-4" block_type="un_table" data-href="asset/ch18/un_table_18_4.html" data-target="_pop">
<layout align="center" width="large"/>
<tbody>
<tr class="tbl-hdr-bg">
<td><strong>Round</strong></td>
<td><strong>Deposits</strong></td>
<td><strong>Required<br/> reserves</strong></td>
<td><strong>Excess<br/> reserves</strong></td>
<td><strong>Loans</strong></td>
<td><strong>Held as<br/> currency</strong></td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tabl-rborder">1</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">&#36;250.00</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">&#36;25.00</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">&#36;225.00</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">&#36;225.00</td>
<td>&#36;112.50</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-dark">
<td class="tabl-rborder">2</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">112.50</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">11.25</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">101.50</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">101.25</td>
<td>50.63</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tabl-rborder">3</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">50.63</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">5.06</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">45.56</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">45.56</td>
<td>22.78</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-dark">
<td class="tabl-rborder">4</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">22.78</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">2.28</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">20.50</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">20.50</td>
<td>10.25</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tabl-rborder">5</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">10.25</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">1.03</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">9.23</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">9.23</td>
<td>4.61</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-dark">
<td class="tabl-rborder">6</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">4.61</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">0.46</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">4.15</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">4.15</td>
<td>2.08</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tabl-rborder">7</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">2.08</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">0.21</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">1.87</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">1.87</td>
<td>0.93</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-dark">
<td class="tabl-rborder">8</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">0.93</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">0.09</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">0.84</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">0.84</td>
<td>0.42</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tabl-rborder">9</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">0.42</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">0.04</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">0.38</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">0.38</td>
<td>0.19</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-dark">
<td class="tabl-rborder">10</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">0.19</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">0.02</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">0.17</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">0.17</td>
<td>0.09</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tabl-rborder">Total after<br/> 10 rounds</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">&#36;454.39</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">&#36;45.44</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">&#36;408.95</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">&#36;408.95</td>
<td>&#36;204.48</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p299" block_type="wio-txt-ni">Round 2 is constructed in the same manner as Round 1. The round begins with a deposit of &#36;112.50. The bank holds &#36;11.25 of this as reserves, and so the excess reserves and the amount loaned out is &#36;112.50 &#8722; &#36;11.25 = &#36;101.25. Of this, the public keeps &#36;50.63 in currency. </p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p300" block_type="sp-stp-txt"><phrase block_type="step-green">STEP</phrase> &#124; <phrase block_type="step-green">4</phrase> <phrase block_type="step-title"><strong>Determine the increase in the money supply that results from the average household deposit.</strong>
<phrase block_type="step-subtext">Review pages 518&#8211;519.</phrase></phrase></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p301" block_type="wio-txt-ni">The approximate increase in the money supply from the average household deposit is &#36;408.95.</p>
</box>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-sec1-7" block_type="cr-que-t" title="" chapter="18" numbered="true" level="1" print_page="536">
<section-metadata><section-title>SUMMARY</section-title></section-metadata>
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-list-8" type="ordered" block_type="numbered">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p302" block_type="sum-nl"><strong>Money</strong> is any asset that can easily be used to purchase goods and services. Money consists of cash, which is <strong>liquid</strong> by definition, as well as other highly liquid assets. <strong>Currency in circulation</strong> and <strong>checkable bank deposits</strong> are both considered part of the <strong>money supply.</strong> Money plays three roles: it is a <strong>medium of exchange</strong> used for transactions, a <strong>store of value</strong> that holds purchasing power over time, and a <strong>unit of account</strong> in which prices are stated.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p303" block_type="sum-nl">Over time, <strong>commodity money,</strong> which consists of goods possessing value aside from their role as money, such as gold and silver coins, was replaced by <strong>commodity-backed money,</strong> such as paper currency backed by gold. Today the dollar is pure <strong>fiat money,</strong> whose value derives solely from its official role.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p304" block_type="sum-nl">The Federal Reserve calculates two measures of the money supply. M1 is the narrowest <strong>monetary aggregate,</strong> containing only currency in circulation, traveler&#8217;s checks, and checkable bank deposits. M2 includes a wider range of assets called <strong>near-moneys,</strong> mainly other forms of bank deposits, that can easily be converted into checkable bank deposits.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p305" block_type="sum-nl">Banks allow depositors immediate access to their funds, but they also lend out most of the funds deposited in their care. To meet demands for cash, they maintain <strong>bank reserves</strong> composed of both currency held in vaults and deposits at the Federal Reserve. The <strong>reserve ratio</strong> is the ratio of bank reserves to bank deposits. A <strong>T-account</strong> summarizes a bank&#8217;s financial position, with loans and reserves counted as assets and deposits counted as liabilities.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p306" block_type="sum-nl">Banks have sometimes been subject to <strong>bank runs,</strong> most notably in the early 1930s. To avert this danger, depositors are now protected by <strong>deposit insurance,</strong> bank owners face capital requirements that reduce the incentive to make overly risky loans with depositors&#8217; funds, and banks must satisfy <strong>reserve requirements.</strong></p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p307" block_type="sum-nl">When currency is deposited in a bank, it starts a multiplier process in which banks lend out <strong>excess reserves,</strong> leading to an increase in the money supply&#8212;so banks create money. If the entire money supply consisted of checkable bank deposits, the money supply would be equal to the value of reserves divided by the reserve ratio. In reality, much of the <strong>monetary base</strong> consists of currency in circulation, and the <strong>money multiplier</strong> is the ratio of the money supply to the monetary base.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_537" block_type="page_start">537</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p308" block_type="sum-nl">The monetary base is controlled by the Federal Reserve, the <strong>central bank</strong> of the United States. The Fed regulates banks and sets reserve requirements. To meet those requirements, banks borrow and lend reserves in the <strong>federal funds market</strong> at the <strong>federal funds rate.</strong> Through the <strong>discount window</strong> facility, banks can borrow from the Fed at the <strong>discount rate.</strong></p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p309" block_type="sum-nl"><strong>Open-market operations</strong> by the Fed are the principal tool of monetary policy: the Fed can increase or reduce the monetary base by buying U.S. Treasury bills from banks or selling U.S. Treasury bills to banks.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p310" block_type="sum-nl">In response to the Panic of 1907, the Fed was created to centralize the holding of reserves, inspect banks&#8217; books, and make the money supply sufficiently responsive to varying economic conditions.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p311" block_type="sum-nl">The Great Depression sparked widespread bank runs in the early 1930s, which greatly worsened and lengthened it. Federal deposit insurance was created, and the government recapitalized banks by lending to them and by buying shares of banks. By 1933, banks had been separated into two categories: <strong>commercial banks</strong> (covered by deposit insurance) and <strong>investment banks</strong> (not covered). Public acceptance of deposit insurance finally stopped the bank runs of the Great Depression.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p312" block_type="sum-nl">The <strong>savings and loan (thrift)</strong> crisis of the 1980s arose because insufficiently regulated S&#38;Ls engaged in overly risky speculation and incurred huge losses. Depositors in failed S&#38;Ls were compensated with taxpayer funds because they were covered by deposit insurance. The crisis caused steep losses in the financial and real estate sectors, resulting in a recession in the early 1990s.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p313" block_type="sum-nl">During the mid-1990s, the hedge fund LTCM used huge amounts of <strong>leverage</strong> to speculate in global financial markets, incurred massive losses, and collapsed. LTCM was so large that, in selling assets to cover its losses, it caused <strong>balance sheet effects</strong> for firms around the world, leading to the prospect of a <strong>vicious cycle of deleveraging.</strong> As a result, credit markets around the world froze. The New York Fed coordinated a private bailout of LTCM and revived world credit markets.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p314" block_type="sum-nl"><strong>Subprime lending</strong> during the U.S. housing bubble of the mid-2000s spread through the financial system via <strong>securitization.</strong> When the bubble burst, massive losses by banks and nonbank financial institutions led to widespread collapse in the financial system. To prevent another Great Depression, the Fed and the U.S. Treasury expanded lending to bank and nonbank institutions, provided capital through the purchase of bank shares, and purchased private debt. Because much of the crisis originated in nontraditional bank institutions, the crisis of 2008 indicated that a wider safety net and broader regulation are needed in the financial sector. The 2010 Dodd-Frank bill, the biggest financial reform since the 1930s, is an attempt to prevent another crisis.</p></li>
</list>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-sec1-8" block_type="cr-kt-t" title="" chapter="18" numbered="true" level="1" print_page="536">
<section-metadata><section-title>KEY TERMS</section-title></section-metadata>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-exp2-8" block_type="mn2">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p315" block_type="fg1-t"><image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-img-36" alt="image" src="asset/images/launchpad_logo_cmyk.jpg"/> &#124; interactive activity</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p316" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p19">Money, p. 507</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p317" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p19">Liquid, p. 507</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p318" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p23">Currency in circulation, p. 507</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p319" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p23">Checkable bank deposits, p. 507</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p320" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p25">Money supply, p. 507</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p321" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p32">Medium of exchange, p. 508</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p322" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p36">Store of value, p. 508</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p323" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p42">Unit of account, p. 509</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p324" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p46">Commodity money, p. 509</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p325" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p47">Commodity-backed money, p. 509</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p326" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p51">Fiat money, p. 510</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p327" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p59">Monetary aggregate, p. 510</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p328" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p61">Near-moneys, p. 510</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p329" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p85">Bank reserves, p. 513</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p330" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p87">T-account, p. 513</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p331" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p93">Reserve ratio, p. 514</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p332" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p100">Bank run, p. 514</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p333" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p104">Deposit insurance, p. 515</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p334" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p109">Reserve requirements, p. 515</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p335" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p111">Discount window, p. 515</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p336" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p139">Excess reserves, p. 519</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p337" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p150">Monetary base, p. 519</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p338" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p154">Money multiplier, p. 520</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p339" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p169">Central bank, p. 521</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p340" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p179">Federal funds market, p. 523</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p341" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p179">Federal funds rate, p. 523</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p342" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p181">Discount rate, p. 523</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p343" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p188">Open-market operation, p. 524</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p344" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p237">Commercial bank, p. 530</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p345" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p237">Investment bank, p. 530</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p346" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p241">Savings and loan (thrift), p. 530</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p347" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p248">Leverage, p. 531</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p348" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p253">Balance sheet effect, p. 531</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p349" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p253">Vicious cycle of deleveraging, p. 531</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p350" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p258">Subprime lending, p. 532</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p351" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p260">Securitization, p. 532</link></p>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-sec1-9" block_type="cr-que-t" title="" chapter="18" numbered="true" level="1" print_page="536">
<section-metadata><section-title>PROBLEMS</section-title></section-metadata>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-question-1" block_type="q_prob" number="1">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p352" block_type="cr-que-nl-first"><phrase block_type="qnum">1.</phrase> For each of the following transactions, what is the initial effect (increase or decrease) on M1? On M2?</p>
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-list-9" type="ordered" block_type="loweralpha">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p353" block_type="cr-que-ans-first">You sell a few shares of stock and put the proceeds into your savings account.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p354" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">You sell a few shares of stock and put the proceeds into your checking account.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p355" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">You transfer money from your savings account to your checking account.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p356" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">You discover &#36;0.25 under the floor mat in your car and deposit it in your checking account.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p357" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">You discover &#36;0.25 under the floor mat in your car and deposit it in your savings account.</p></li>
</list>
</question>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_538" block_type="page_start">538</p>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-question-2" block_type="q_prob" number="2">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p358" block_type="cr-que-nl-mid"><phrase block_type="qnum">2.</phrase> There are three types of money: commodity money, commodity-backed money, and fiat money. Which type of money is used in each of the following situations?</p>
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-list-10" type="ordered" block_type="loweralpha">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p359" block_type="cr-que-ans-first">Bottles of rum were used to pay for goods in colonial Australia.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p360" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">Salt was used in many European countries as a medium of exchange.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p361" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">For a brief time, Germany used paper money (the &#8220;Rye Mark&#8221;) that could be redeemed for a certain amount of rye, a type of grain.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p362" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">The town of Ithaca, New York, prints its own currency, the Ithaca HOURS, which can be used to purchase local goods and services.</p></li>
</list>
</question>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-question-3" block_type="q_prob" number="3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p363" block_type="cr-que-nl-mid"><phrase block_type="qnum">3.</phrase> The following table below the components of M1 and M2 in billions of dollars for the month of December in the years 2003 to 2013 reported by the Federal Reserve Bank of St. Louis. Complete the table by calculating M1, M2, currency in circulation as a percentage of M1, and currency in circulation as a percentage of M2. What trends or patterns about M1, M2, currency in circulation as a percentage of M1, and currency in circulation as a percentage of M2 do you see? What might account for these trends?</p>
<table id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-untab-5" block_type="un_table" data-href="asset/ch18/un_table_18_5.html" data-target="_pop">
<layout align="center" width="large"/>
<tbody>
<tr class="tbl-hdr-bg">
<td><strong>Year</strong></td>
<td><strong>Currency<br/> in<br/> circulation</strong></td>
<td><strong>Traveler&#8217;s<br/> checks</strong></td>
<td><strong>Checkable<br/> deposits</strong></td>
<td><strong>Savings<br/> deposits</strong></td>
<td><strong>Time<br/> deposits</strong></td>
<td><strong>Money<br/> market<br/> funds</strong></td>
<td><strong>M1</strong></td>
<td><strong>M2</strong></td>
<td><strong>Currency<br/> in<br/> circulation<br/> as a<br/> percentage<br/> of M1</strong></td>
<td><strong>Currency<br/> in<br/> circulation<br/> as a<br/> percentage<br/> of M2</strong></td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tabl-rborder">2003</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">&#36;662.5</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">&#36;7.6</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">&#36;635.9</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">&#36;3,159.0</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">&#36;818.1</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">&#36;752.8</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">?</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">?</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">?</td>
<td>?</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-dark">
<td class="tabl-rborder">2004</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">697.8</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">7.5</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">670.6</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">3,506.5</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">828.4</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">677.6</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">?</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">?</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">?</td>
<td>?</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tabl-rborder">2005</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">724.6</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">7.2</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">643.0</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">3,601.6</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">993.7</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">682.4</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">?</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">?</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">?</td>
<td>?</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-dark">
<td class="tabl-rborder">2006</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">750.2</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">6.7</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">610.6</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">3,691.8</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">1,206.0</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">776.6</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">?</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">?</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">?</td>
<td>?</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tabl-rborder">2007</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">760.6</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">6.3</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">608.1</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">3,864.1</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">1,276.0</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">930.6</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">?</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">?</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">?</td>
<td>?</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-dark">
<td class="tabl-rborder">2008</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">816.2</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">5.5</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">782.0</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">4,085.6</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">1,457.6</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">1,021.6</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">?</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">?</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">?</td>
<td>?</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tabl-rborder">2009</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">863.7</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">5.1</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">825.3</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">4,809.3</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">1,183.1</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">781.2</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">?</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">?</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">?</td>
<td>?</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-dark">
<td class="tabl-rborder">2010</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">918.7</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">4.7</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">912.7</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">5,329.6</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">927.9</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">675.7</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">?</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">?</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">?</td>
<td>?</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tabl-rborder">2011</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">1,001.2</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">4.3</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">1,154.3</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">6,032.8</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">767.0</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">663.7</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">?</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">?</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">?</td>
<td>?</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-dark">
<td class="tabl-rborder">2012</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">1,090.0</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">3.8</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">1,353.5</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">6,687.5</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">633.0</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">642.0</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">?</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">?</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">?</td>
<td>?</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tabl-rborder">2013</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">1,159.5</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">3.5</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">1,475.8</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">7,133.0</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">555.6</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">640.9</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">?</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">?</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">?</td>
<td>?</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p364" block_type="cr-qu-tb-txt"><em>Data from:</em> Federal Reserve Bank of St. Louis.</p>
</question>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-question-4" block_type="q_prob" number="4">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p365" block_type="cr-que-nl-mid"><phrase block_type="qnum">4.</phrase> Indicate whether each of the following is part of M1, M2, or neither:</p>
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-list-11" type="ordered" block_type="loweralpha">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p366" block_type="cr-que-ans-first">&#36;95 on your campus meal card</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p367" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">&#36;0.55 in the change cup of your car</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p368" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">&#36;1,663 in your savings account</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p369" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">&#36;459 in your checking account</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p370" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">100 shares of stock worth &#36;4,000</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p371" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">A &#36;1,000 line of credit on your Sears credit card</p></li>
</list>
</question>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-question-5" block_type="q_prob" number="5">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p372" block_type="cr-que-nl-mid"><phrase block_type="qnum">5.</phrase> Tracy Williams deposits &#36;500 that was in her sock drawer into a checking account at the local bank.</p>
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-list-12" type="ordered" block_type="loweralpha">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p373" block_type="cr-que-ans-first">How does the deposit initially change the T-account of the local bank? How does it change the money supply?</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p374" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">If the bank maintains a reserve ratio of 10&#37;, how will it respond to the new deposit?</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p375" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">If every time the bank makes a loan, the loan results in a new checkable bank deposit in a different bank equal to the amount of the loan, by how much could the total money supply in the economy expand in response to Tracy&#8217;s initial cash deposit of &#36;500?</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p376" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">If every time the bank makes a loan, the loan results in a new checkable bank deposit in a different bank equal to the amount of the loan and the bank maintains a reserve ratio of 5&#37;, by how much could the money supply expand in response to Tracy&#8217;s initial cash deposit of &#36;500?</p></li>
</list>
</question>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-question-6" block_type="q_prob" number="6">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p377" block_type="cr-que-nl-mid"><phrase block_type="qnum">6.</phrase> Ryan Cozzens withdraws &#36;400 from his checking account at the local bank and keeps it in his wallet.</p>
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-list-13" type="ordered" block_type="loweralpha">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p378" block_type="cr-que-ans-first">How will the withdrawal change the T-account of the local bank and the money supply?</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p379" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">If the bank maintains a reserve ratio of 10&#37;, how will it respond to the withdrawal? Assume that the bank responds to insufficient reserves by reducing the amount of deposits it holds until its level of reserves satisfies its required reserve ratio. The bank reduces its deposits by calling in some of its loans, forcing borrowers to pay back these loans by taking cash from their checking deposits (at the same bank) to make repayment.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p380" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">If every time the bank decreases its loans, checkable bank deposits fall by the amount of the loan, by how much will the money supply in the economy contract in response to Ryan&#8217;s withdrawal of &#36;400?</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p381" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">If every time the bank decreases its loans, checkable bank deposits fall by the amount of the loan and the bank maintains a reserve ratio of 20&#37;, by how much will the money supply contract in response to a withdrawal of &#36;400?</p></li>
</list>
</question>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_539" block_type="page_start">539</p>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-question-7" block_type="q_prob" number="7">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p382" block_type="cr-que-nl-mid"><phrase block_type="qnum">7.</phrase> The government of Eastlandia uses measures of monetary aggregates similar to those used by the United States, and the central bank of Eastlandia imposes a required reserve ratio of 10&#37;. Given the following information, answer the questions below.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p383" block_type="cr-que-nl-mid">Bank deposits at the central bank = &#36;200 million</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p384" block_type="cr-que-nl-mid">Currency held by public = &#36;150 million</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p385" block_type="cr-que-nl-mid">Currency in bank vaults = &#36;100 million</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p386" block_type="cr-que-nl-mid">Checkable bank deposits = &#36;500 million</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p387" block_type="cr-que-nl-mid">Traveler&#8217;s checks = &#36;10 million</p>
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-list-14" type="ordered" block_type="loweralpha">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p388" block_type="cr-que-ans-first">What is M1?</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p389" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">What is the monetary base?</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p390" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">Are the commercial banks holding excess reserves?</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p391" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">Can the commercial banks increase checkable bank deposits? If yes, by how much can checkable bank deposits increase?</p></li>
</list>
</question>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-question-8" block_type="q_prob" number="8">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p392" block_type="cr-que-nl-mid"><phrase block_type="qnum">8.</phrase> In Westlandia, the public holds 50&#37; of M1 in the form of currency, and the required reserve ratio is 20&#37;. Estimate how much the money supply will increase in response to a new cash deposit of &#36;500 by completing the accompanying table. (<em>Hint:</em> The first row shows that the bank must hold &#36;100 in minimum reserves&#8212;20&#37; of the &#36;500 deposit&#8212;against this deposit, leaving &#36;400 in excess reserves that can be loaned out. However, since the public wants to hold 50&#37; of the loan in currency, only &#36;400 &#215; 0.5 = &#36;200 of the loan will be deposited in round 2 from the loan granted in round 1.) How does your answer compare to an economy in which the total amount of the loan is deposited in the banking system and the public doesn&#8217;t hold any of the loan in currency? What does this imply about the relationship between the public&#8217;s desire for holding currency and the money multiplier?</p>
<table id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-untab-6" block_type="un_table" data-href="asset/ch18/un_table_18_6.html" data-target="_pop">
<layout align="center" width="large"/>
<tbody>
<tr class="tbl-hdr-bg">
<td><strong>Round</strong></td>
<td><strong>Deposits</strong></td>
<td><strong>Required<br/> reserves</strong></td>
<td><strong>Excess<br/> reserves</strong></td>
<td><strong>Loans</strong></td>
<td><strong>Held as<br/> currency</strong></td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tabl-rborder">1</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">&#36;500.00</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">&#36;100.00</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">&#36;400.00</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">&#36;400.00</td>
<td>&#36;200.00</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-dark">
<td class="tabl-rborder">2</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">200.00</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">?</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">?</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">?</td>
<td>?</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tabl-rborder">3</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">?</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">?</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">?</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">?</td>
<td>?</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-dark">
<td class="tabl-rborder">4</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">?</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">?</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">?</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">?</td>
<td>?</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tabl-rborder">5</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">?</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">?</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">?</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">?</td>
<td>?</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-dark">
<td class="tabl-rborder">6</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">?</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">?</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">?</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">?</td>
<td>?</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tabl-rborder">7</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">?</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">?</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">?</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">?</td>
<td>?</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-dark">
<td class="tabl-rborder">8</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">?</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">?</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">?</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">?</td>
<td>?</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tabl-rborder">9</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">?</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">?</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">?</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">?</td>
<td>?</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-dark">
<td class="tabl-rborder">Total<br/> after 10<br/> rounds</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">?</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">?</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">?</td>
<td class="tabl-rborder">?</td>
<td>?</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</question>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-question-9" block_type="q_prob" number="9">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p393" block_type="cr-que-nl-mid"><phrase block_type="qnum">9.</phrase> What will happen to the money supply under the following circumstances in a checkable-deposits-only system?</p>
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-list-15" type="ordered" block_type="loweralpha">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p394" block_type="cr-que-ans-first">The required reserve ratio is 25&#37;, and a depositor withdraws &#36;700 from his checkable bank deposit.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p395" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">The required reserve ratio is 5&#37;, and a depositor withdraws &#36;700 from his checkable bank deposit.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p396" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">The required reserve ratio is 20&#37;, and a customer deposits &#36;750 to her checkable bank deposit.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p397" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">The required reserve ratio is 10&#37;, and a customer deposits &#36;600 to her checkable bank deposit.</p></li>
</list>
</question>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-question-10" block_type="q_prob" number="10">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p398" block_type="cr-que-nl-mid"><phrase block_type="qnum">10.</phrase> Although the U.S. Federal Reserve doesn&#8217;t use changes in reserve requirements to manage the money supply, the central bank of Albernia does. The commercial banks of Albernia have &#36;100 million in reserves and &#36;1,000 million in checkable deposits; the initial required reserve ratio is 10&#37;. The commercial banks follow a policy of holding no excess reserves. The public holds no currency, only checkable deposits in the banking system.</p>
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-list-16" type="ordered" block_type="loweralpha">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p399" block_type="cr-que-ans-first">How will the money supply change if the required reserve ratio falls to 5&#37;?</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p400" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">How will the money supply change if the required reserve ratio rises to 25&#37;?</p></li>
</list>
</question>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-question-11" block_type="q_prob" number="11">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p401" block_type="cr-que-nl-mid"><phrase block_type="qnum">11.</phrase> Using <link href="asset/ch18/KrugESS4e_fig_18_06.html">Figure 18-6</link>, find the Federal Reserve district in which you live. Go to <link href="http://www.federalreserve.gov/bios/pres.htm">www.federalreserve.gov/bios/pres.htm</link> and click on your district to identify the president of the Federal Reserve Bank in your district. Go to <link href="http://www.federalreserve.gov/fomc/">www.federalreserve.gov/fomc/</link> and determine if the president of the regional Federal Reserve bank in your district is currently a voting member of the Federal Open Market Committee (FOMC).</p>
</question>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-question-12" block_type="q_prob" number="12">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p402" block_type="cr-que-nl-mid"><phrase block_type="qnum">12.</phrase> Show the changes to the T-accounts for the Federal Reserve and for commercial banks when the Federal Reserve sells &#36;30 million in U.S. Treasury bills. If the public holds a fixed amount of currency (so that all new loans create an equal amount of checkable bank deposits in the banking system) and the minimum reserve ratio is 5&#37;, by how much will checkable bank deposits in the commercial banks change? By how much will the money supply change? Show the final changes to the T-account for the commercial banks when the money supply changes by this amount.</p>
</question>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-question-13" block_type="q_prob" number="13">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p403" block_type="cr-que-nl-mid"><phrase block_type="qnum">13.</phrase> The Congressional Research Service estimates that at least &#36;45 million of counterfeit U.S. &#36;100 notes produced by the North Korean government are in circulation.</p>
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-list-17" type="ordered" block_type="loweralpha">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p404" block_type="cr-que-ans-first">Why do U.S. taxpayers lose because of North Korea&#8217;s counterfeiting?</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p405" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">As of December 2014, the interest rate earned on one-year U.S. Treasury bills was 0.13&#37;. At a 0.13&#37; rate of interest, what is the amount of money U.S. taxpayers are losing per year because of these &#36;45 million in counterfeit notes? </p></li>
</list>
</question>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-question-14" block_type="q_prob" number="14">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p406" block_type="cr-que-nl-mid"><phrase block_type="qnum">14.</phrase> As shown in <link href="asset/ch18/KrugESS4e_fig_18_09.html">Figure 18-9</link>, the portion of the Federal Reserve&#8217;s assets made up of U.S. Treasury bills has declined since 2007. Go to <link href="http://www.federalreserve.gov.">www.federalreserve.gov.</link> Under &#8220;Select Statistical Releases,&#8221; click on &#8220;View All.&#8221; Under the heading &#8220;Money Stock and Reserve Balances,&#8221; click on &#8220;Factors Affecting Reserve Balances.&#8221; Click on the date of the current release.</p>
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-list-18" type="ordered" block_type="loweralpha">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p407" block_type="cr-que-ans-first">Under &#8220;Statement of Condition of Federal Reserve Bank,&#8221; look in the &#8220;Total&#8221; column. What is the amount displayed next to &#8220;Total assets&#8221;? What is the amount displayed next to &#8220;U.S. Treasury securities&#8221;? What percentage of the Federal Reserve&#8217;s total assets are currently made up of U.S. Treasury bills?</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_540" block_type="page_start">540</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p408" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">Do the Federal Reserve&#8217;s assets consist primarily of U.S. Treasury securities, as they did in January 2007, the beginning of the graph in <link href="asset/ch18/KrugESS4e_fig_18_09.html">Figure 18-9</link>, or does the Fed still own a large number of other assets, as it did in mid-2013, the end of the graph in <link href="asset/ch18/KrugESS4e_fig_18_09.html">Figure 18-9</link>? </p></li>
</list>
</question>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-question-15" block_type="q_prob" number="15">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p409" block_type="cr-que-nl-mid"><phrase block_type="qnum">15.</phrase> The accompanying figure shows new U.S. housing starts, in thousands of units per month, between January 1980 and January 2014. The graph shows a large drop in new housing starts in 1984&#8211;1991 and 2006&#8211;2009. New housing starts are related to the availability of mortgages.</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-fig-24" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="right" width="medium" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-img-37" alt="image" src="asset/ch18/KrugESS4e_18UN11.jpg"/>
</figure>
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-list-19" type="ordered" block_type="loweralpha">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p410" block_type="cr-que-ans-first">What caused the drop in new housing starts in 1984&#8211;1991?</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p411" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">What caused the drop in new housing starts in 2006&#8211;2009?</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p412" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">How could better regulation of financial institutions have prevented these two instances?</p></li>
</list>
</question>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-sec1-10" block_type="sum-h" title="" chapter="18" numbered="true" level="1" print_page="540">
<section-metadata><section-title>WORK IT OUT</section-title></section-metadata>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-exp2-9" block_type="mn2">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p413" block_type="fg1-t"><image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-img-38" alt="image" src="asset/images/launchpad_logo_cmyk.jpg"/> &#124; interactive activity</p>
</box>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-question-16" block_type="q_prob" number="16">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch18-p414" block_type="cr-wio-nl-first"><phrase block_type="qnum">16.</phrase> Show the changes to the T-accounts for the Federal Reserve and for commercial banks when the Federal Reserve buys &#36;50 million in U.S. Treasury bills. If the public holds a fixed amount of currency (so that all loans create an equal amount of deposits in the banking system), the minimum reserve ratio is 10&#37;, and banks hold no excess reserves, by how much will deposits in the commercial banks change? By how much will the money supply change? Show the final changes to the T-account for commercial banks when the money supply changes by this amount.</p>
</question>
</section>
</chapter>
