title="KRU_Chapter_05_SOL_DJHrev" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="../xsd/digfir_manuscript.xsd">
<chapter number="5" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-chapter-5" title="CHAPTER 5: Elasticity and Taxation" start-numbering-at="5" numbered="true">
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-sec1-001" block_type="h1" title="Chapter Introduction" chapter="5" numbered="false" level="1" print_page="137">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_137" block_type="page_start">137</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p2" block_type="chapter_title">Elasticity and Taxation</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p1" block_type="chapter_number"><phrase block_type="chap">CHAPTER</phrase> <phrase block_type="chapnum">5</phrase></p>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-bx3-001" block_type="bx3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch3-p48am" block_type="co-t"><strong>TAKEN FOR A RIDE</strong></p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-fig-001" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-img-002" alt="image" src="asset/ch5/KrugESS4e_CO05.jpg"/>
<caption>The demand for ambulance rides to the hospital is relatively unresponsive to the price.</caption>
<asset_source>Scott Kochsiek/iStockphoto/Getty Images</asset_source>
</figure>
</box>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-exp1-1" block_type="mn1">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p1" block_type="obj-h"><strong>What You Will Learn in This Chapter</strong></p>
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-list-1" type="unordered" block_type="greensquare">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p02" block_type="obj-bl">Why economists use <strong>elasticity</strong> to measure responsiveness to changes in prices or incomes</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p03" block_type="obj-bl">Why the <strong>price elasticity of demand,</strong> the i<strong>ncome elasticity of demand,</strong> and the <strong>cross-price elasticity of demand</strong> are important indicators of consumer behavior in response to changes in prices and income</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p04" block_type="obj-bl">Why the <strong>price elasticity of supply</strong> is an important indicator of producer behavior in response to changes in price</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p05" block_type="obj-bl">What factors influence the size of these various elasticities</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p06" block_type="obj-bl">How the price elasticities of supply and demand affect the costs and benefits of taxation</p></li>
</list>
</box>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-exp2-1" block_type="mn2">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p08" block_type="fg1-t"><image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-img-002" alt="image" src="asset/images/launchpad_ML_logo_black.jpg"/> &#124; interactive activity</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p09" block_type="co-txt-ni"><phrase block_type="dropcap">I</phrase>F YOU ARE EXPERIENCING A TRUE emergency, you aren&#8217;t likely to quibble about the price of an ambulance ride to the nearest emergency room. But what if it isn&#8217;t an emergency? Take the case of Kira Millas, who doesn&#8217;t even know who called an ambulance after she swam into the side of a swimming pool, breaking three teeth. Shaken, she accepted the ambulance ride to a local hospital, 15 minutes away. A week later, she received the bill: &#36;1,772.42. Stunned, she said: &#8220;We only drove nine miles and it was a non-life-threatening injury. I needed absolutely no emergency treatment.&#8221;</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p010" block_type="co-txt">Kira&#8217;s experience is by no means exceptional. Although ambulances are often requested by a bystander or by 911 dispatchers, it is the patient who receives the bill. Undoubtedly, in a true medical emergency, a patient feels fortunate that an ambulance is available. But even in nonemergency cases, like Kira&#8217;s, many patients often feel obliged to get into the ambulance once it arrives. And just like Kira, they are uninformed about the cost of the ride to the hospital. (With luck, they have recovered by the time they receive the bill!) And while many people have health insurance that will cover some or all of the cost of the ambulance service, the patient is ultimately responsible for paying the rest.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p011" block_type="co-txt">An estimated 40 million ambulance trips, at a cost of &#36;14 billion, are provided each year by nonprofit entities such as local fire departments and by for-profit companies each year in the United States. Sensing profit-making opportunities, in recent years for-profit companies have significantly expanded their operations, often taking over from nonprofit operators. And big investors are betting that ambulance services will generate significant profits: two private ambulance providers were recently bought by investors, one for &#36;3 billion and another for &#36;438 million.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p012" block_type="co-txt">Charges for an ambulance ride vary wildly across the country, from several hundred dollars to tens of thousands of dollars. The price may depend on many things other than the patient&#8217;s medical needs, from the level of skill of the ambulance team onboard to the distance traveled, or in some cases whether a friend or relative rides along (which can add hundreds of dollars to the cost). While it&#8217;s impossible to know the total amount that Americans are paying for ambulance services, Medicare, the federally administered health insurance program for Americans age 65 and older, has seen its spending on ambulance services explode, from &#36;2 billion a year in 2002 to nearly &#36;6 billion in 2013.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p013" block_type="co-txt">What accounts for the extreme variation in the cost of ambulance services? How are these services able to charge thousands of dollars, regardless of whether an ambulance is actually needed? Or to charge for an ambulance equipped with heart resuscitation capabilities when the patient has only a broken leg? The answer to these questions is <em>price unresponsiveness:</em> in the heat of the moment, many consumers&#8212;particularly those with true emergencies&#8212;are <em>unresponsive</em> to the price of an ambulance. Ambulance operators judge correctly that a significant number of patients won&#8217;t ask &#8220;How much is this ride to the emergency room going to cost?&#8221; before getting onboard. In other words, a large increase in the price of an ambulance ride leaves the quantity demanded by a significant number of consumers relatively unchanged.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_138" block_type="page_start">138</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p014" block_type="co-txt">Let&#8217;s consider a very different scenario. Suppose that the maker of a particular brand of breakfast cereal decided to charge 10 times the original price. It would be extremely difficult, if not impossible, to find consumers willing to pay the much higher price. In other words, consumers of breakfast cereal are much more responsive to price than the consumers of ambulance rides.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p015" block_type="co-txt">But how do we define <em>responsiveness</em>? Economists measure responsiveness of consumers to price with a particular number, called the <em>price elasticity of demand.</em> In this chapter we will show how the price elasticity of demand is calculated and why it is the best measure of how the quantity demanded responds to changes in price. We will then see that the price elasticity of demand is only one of a family of related concepts, including the <em>income elasticity of demand, cross-price elasticity of demand,</em> and the <em>price elasticity of supply.</em></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p016" block_type="co-txt">We will finish our discussion of elasticities by looking at how the price elasticities of supply and demand influence the costs and benefits of taxation.</p>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-sec1-001" block_type="h1" title="" chapter="5" numbered="true" level="1" print_page="138">
<section-metadata><section-title>Defining and Measuring Elasticity</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p017" block_type="txt-ni">In order for investors to know whether they can earn significant profits in the ambulance business, they need to know the <em>price elasticity of demand</em> for ambulance rides. With this information, investors can accurately predict whether or not a significant rise in the price of an ambulance ride results in an increase in revenue.</p>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-sec2-001" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="5" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="138">
<section-metadata><section-title>Calculating the Price Elasticity of Demand</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p018" block_type="txt-ni"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e_ch5-fig-002">Figure 5-1</link> shows a hypothetical demand curve for an ambulance ride. At a price of &#36;200 per ride, consumers would demand 10 million rides per year (point <em>A</em>); at a price of &#36;210 per ride, consumers would demand 9.9 million rides per year (point <em>B</em>).</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-fig-002" block_type="figure" numbered="true" number="5-1" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<caption><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-fig-002"><phrase block_type="fig-label"><strong><phrase block_type="fig">FIGURE</phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_num">5-1</phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_title">The Demand for Ambulance Rides</phrase></strong></phrase></link></caption>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-img-002" alt="image" src="asset/ch5/KrugESS4e_fig_5_01.jpg"/>
<caption>At a price of &#36;200 per ambulance ride, the quantity of ambulance rides demanded is 10&#160;million per year (point <em>A</em>). When price rises to &#36;210 per vaccination, the quantity demanded falls to 9.9 million ambulance rides per year (point <em>B</em>).</caption>
</figure>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p019" block_type="txt"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e_ch5-fig-002">Figure 5-1</link>, then, tells us the change in the quantity demanded for a particular change in the price. But how can we turn this into a measure of price responsiveness? The answer is to calculate the <em>price elasticity of demand.</em></p>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-exp3-1" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p020" block_type="mn-gl-def">The <strong>price elasticity of demand</strong> is the ratio of the percent change in the quantity demanded to the percent change in the price as we move along the demand curve.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p021" block_type="txt">The <strong>price elasticity of demand</strong> is the ratio of the <em>percent change in quantity demanded</em> to the <em>percent change in price</em> as we move along the demand curve. As we&#8217;ll see later in this chapter, the reason economists use percent changes is to obtain a measure that doesn&#8217;t depend on the units in which a good is measured (say, a 1-mile ambulance trip versus a 10-mile ambulance trip). But before we get to that, let&#8217;s look at how elasticity is calculated.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_139" block_type="page_start">139</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p022" block_type="txt">To calculate the price elasticity of demand, we first calculate the <em>percent change in the quantity demanded</em> and the corresponding <em>percent change in the price</em> as we move along the demand curve. These are defined as follows:</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p023" block_type="eq"><strong>(5-1)</strong> &#37; change in quantity demanded = <image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-img-003" alt="image" src="asset/ch5/KrugESS4e_5UN12.jpg"/> &#215; 100</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p024" block_type="eq-mid">and</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p025" block_type="eq"><strong>(5-2)</strong> &#37; change in price = <image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-img-004" alt="image" src="asset/ch5/KrugESS4e_5UN13.jpg"/> &#215; 100</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p026" block_type="txt-ni">In <link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e_ch5-fig-002">Figure 5-1</link>, we see that when the price rises from &#36;200 to &#36;210, the quantity demanded falls from 10 million to 9.9 million rides, yielding a change in the quantity demanded of 0.1 million rides. So the percent change in the quantity demanded is</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p027" block_type="eq">&#37; change in quantity demanded = <image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-img-005" alt="image" src="asset/ch5/KrugESS4e_5UN14.jpg"/> &#215; 100 = &#8722;1&#37;</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p029" block_type="txt">The initial price is &#36;200 and the change in the price is &#36;10, so the percent change in price is</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p030" block_type="eq">&#37; change in price = <image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-img-006" alt="image" src="asset/ch5/KrugESS4e_5UN15.jpg"/> &#215; 100 = 5&#37;</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p031" block_type="txt">To calculate the price elasticity of demand, we find the ratio of the percent change in the quantity demanded to the percent change in the price:</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p032" block_type="eq"><strong>(5-3)</strong> Price elasticity of demand = <image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-img-007" alt="image" src="asset/ch5/KrugESS4e_5UN16.jpg"/></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p033" block_type="txt">In <link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e_ch5-fig-002">Figure 5-1</link>, the price elasticity of demand is therefore</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p034" block_type="eq">Price elasticity of demand = <image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-img-008" alt="image" src="asset/ch5/KrugESS4e_5UN17.jpg"/> = 0.2</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p035" block_type="txt">Notice that the minus sign that appeared in the calculation of the percent change in the quantity demanded has been dropped when we calculate this last equation, the price elasticity of demand. Why have we done this? The <em>law of demand</em> says that demand curves are downward sloping, so price and quantity demanded always move in opposite directions. In other words, a positive percent change in price (a rise in price) leads to a negative percent change in the quantity demanded; a negative percent change in price (a fall in price) leads to a positive percent change in the quantity demanded. This means that the price elasticity of demand is, in strictly mathematical terms, a negative number.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p036" block_type="txt">However, it is inconvenient to repeatedly write a minus sign. So when economists talk about the price elasticity of demand, they usually drop the minus sign and report the <em>absolute value</em> of the price elasticity of demand. In this case, for example, economists would usually say &#8220;the price elasticity of demand is 0.2,&#8221; taking it for granted that you understand they mean <em>minus</em> 0.2. We follow this convention here.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p037" block_type="txt">The larger the price elasticity of demand, the more responsive the quantity demanded is to the price. When the price elasticity of demand is large&#8212;when consumers change their quantity demanded by a large percentage compared to the percent change in the price&#8212;economists say that demand is highly elastic.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p038" block_type="txt">As we&#8217;ll see shortly, a price elasticity of 0.2 indicates a small response of quantity demanded to price. That is, the quantity demanded will fall by a relatively small amount when price rises. This is what economists call <em>inelastic</em> demand. And inelastic demand is exactly what enables an ambulance operator to increase the total amount earned by raising the price of an ambulance ride.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_140" block_type="page_start">140</p>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-sec2-002" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="5" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="140">
<section-metadata><section-title>An Alternative Way to Calculate Elasticities: The Midpoint Method</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p039" block_type="txt-ni">Price elasticity of demand compares the <em>percent change in quantity demanded</em> with the <em>percent change in price.</em> When we look at some other elasticities, which we will do shortly, we&#8217;ll learn why it is important to focus on percent changes. But at this point we need to discuss a technical issue that arises when you calculate percent changes in variables.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p040" block_type="txt">The best way to understand the issue is with a real example. Suppose you were trying to estimate the price elasticity of demand for gasoline by comparing gasoline prices and consumption in different countries. Because of high taxes, gasoline usually costs about three times as much per gallon in Europe as it does in the United States. So what is the percent difference between American and European gas prices?</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p041" block_type="txt">Well, it depends on which way you measure it. Because the price of gasoline in Europe is approximately three times higher than in the United States, it is 200&#160;percent higher. Because the price of gasoline in the United States is one-third as high as in Europe, it is 66.7 percent lower.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p042" block_type="txt">This is a nuisance: we&#8217;d like to have a percent measure of the difference in prices that doesn&#8217;t depend on which way you measure it. To avoid computing different elasticities for rising and falling prices we use the <em>midpoint method.</em></p>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-exp3-2" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p043" block_type="mn-gl-def">The <strong>midpoint method</strong> is a technique for calculating the percent change. In this approach, we calculate changes in a variable compared with the average, or midpoint, of the starting and final values.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p044" block_type="txt">The <strong>midpoint method</strong> replaces the usual definition of the percent change in a variable, <em>X,</em> with a slightly different definition:</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p045" block_type="eq"><strong>(5-4)</strong> &#37; change in <em>X</em> = <image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-img-009" alt="image" src="asset/ch5/KrugESS4e_5UN18.jpg"/> &#215; 100</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p046" block_type="txt-ni">where the average value of <em>X</em> is defined as</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p047" block_type="eq">Average value of <em>X</em> = <image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-img-010" alt="image" src="asset/ch5/KrugESS4e_5UN19.jpg"/></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p048" block_type="txt">When calculating the price elasticity of demand using the midpoint method, both the percent change in the price and the percent change in the quantity demanded are found using this method. To see how this method works, suppose you have the following data for some good:</p>
<table id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-untab-1" block_type="un_table" data-href="asset/ch5/tables/untable_5_1.html" data-target="_pop">
<tbody>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td><strong>Price</strong></td>
<td><strong>Quantity demanded</strong></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>Situation A</strong></td>
<td>&#36;0.90</td>
<td>1,100</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>Situation B</strong></td>
<td>&#36;1.10</td>
<td>900</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p049" block_type="txt">To calculate the percent change in quantity going from situation A to situation&#160;<em>B</em>, we compare the change in the quantity demanded&#8212;a fall of 200 units&#8212;with the <em>average</em> of the quantity demanded in the two situations. So we calculate</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p050" block_type="eq">&#37; change in quantity demanded = <image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-img-011" alt="image" src="asset/ch5/KrugESS4e_5UN20.jpg"/> &#215; 100 = <image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-img-012" alt="image" src="asset/ch5/KrugESS4e_5UN21.jpg"/> &#215; 100 = &#8722;20&#37;</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p051" block_type="txt">In the same way, we calculate</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p052" block_type="eq">&#37; change in price = <image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-img-013" alt="image" src="asset/ch5/KrugESS4e_5UN22.jpg"/> &#215; 100 = <image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-img-014" alt="image" src="asset/ch5/KrugESS4e_5UN23.jpg"/> &#215; 100 = 20&#37;</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p053" block_type="txt">So in this case we would calculate the price elasticity of demand to be</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p054" block_type="eq">Price elasticity of demand = <image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-img-015" alt="image" src="asset/ch5/KrugESS4e_5UN24.jpg"/> = <image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-img-016" alt="image" src="asset/ch5/KrugESS4e_5UN25.jpg"/> = 1</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p054" block_type="txt">again dropping the minus sign.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_141" block_type="page_start">141</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p056" block_type="txt">The important point is that we would get the same result, a price elasticity of demand of 1, whether we go up the demand curve from situation A to situation B or down from situation B to situation A.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p057" block_type="txt">To arrive at a more general formula for price elasticity of demand, suppose that we have data for two points on a demand curve. At point 1 the quantity demanded and price are (<em>Q</em><sub>1</sub>, <em>P</em><sub>1</sub>); at point 2 they are (<em>Q</em><sub>2</sub>, <em>P</em><sub>2</sub>). Then the formula for calculating the price elasticity of demand is:</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p058" block_type="eq"><strong>(5-5)</strong> Price elasticity of demand = <image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-img-017" alt="image" src="asset/ch5/KrugESS4e_5UN26.jpg"/></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p059" block_type="txt">As before, when finding a price elasticity of demand calculated by the midpoint method, we drop the minus sign and use the absolute value.</p>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-bx2-2" block_type="bx2-h">
<box-metadata><box-title><phrase block_type="title">ECONOMICS</phrase> <phrase block_type="number"><em>in Action</em></phrase></box-title></box-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p060" block_type="bx2-t"><strong>Estimating Elasticities</strong></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p062" block_type="bx2-first"><phrase block_type="dropcap">Y</phrase>ou might think it&#8217;s easy to estimate price elasticities of demand from real-world data: just compare percent changes in prices with percent changes in quantities demanded. Unfortunately, it&#8217;s rarely that simple because changes in price aren&#8217;t the only thing affecting changes in the quantity demanded: other factors&#8212;such as changes in income, changes in tastes, and changes in the prices of other goods&#8212;shift the demand curve, thereby changing the quantity demanded at any given price.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p063" block_type="bx2-txt">To estimate price elasticities of demand, economists must use careful statistical analysis to separate the influence of the change in price, holding other things equal.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p064" block_type="bx2-txt">Economists have estimated price elasticities of demand for a number of goods and services. <link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-tab-1">Table 5-1</link> summarizes some of these and shows a wide range of price elasticities. There are some goods, like gasoline, for which demand hardly responds at all to changes in the price. There are other goods, such as airline travel for leisure, or Coke and Pepsi, for which the quantity demanded is very sensitive to the price.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p065" block_type="bx2-txt">Notice that <link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-tab-1">Table 5-1</link> is divided into two parts: inelastic and elastic demand. We&#8217;ll explain the significance of that division in the next section.</p>
</box>
<table id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-tab-2" block_type="table" numbered="false" caption-placement="Top" data-href="asset/ch5/tables/table_5_2.html" data-target="_pop">
<table_caption><strong><phrase block_type="tbl">TABLE</phrase> <phrase block_type="tbl_num">5-1</phrase></strong> <phrase block_type="tbl_title">Some Estimated Price Elasticities of Demand</phrase></table_caption>
<tbody>
<tr class="tbl-hdr-bg">
<td class="tbl-ljust"><strong>Good</strong></td>
<td class="tbl-lborder"><strong>Price elasticity of demand</strong></td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-dark">
<td class="tbl-ljust"><strong>Inelastic demand</strong></td>
<td class="tbl-lborder"></td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tbl-ljust">Gasoline (short-run)</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">0.09</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-dark">
<td class="tbl-ljust">Gasonline (long-run)</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">0.24</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tbl-ljust">Airline travel (business)</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">0.80</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-dark">
<td class="tbl-ljust">Soda</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">0.80</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tbl-ljust">College (in-state tuition)</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">0.87</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-dark">
<td class="tbl-ljust"><strong>Elastic demand</strong></td>
<td class="tbl-lborder"></td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tbl-ljust">Housing</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">1.2</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-dark">
<td class="tbl-ljust">College (out-of-state tuition)</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">1.2</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tbl-ljust">Airline travel (leisure)</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">1.5</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-dark">
<td class="tbl-ljust">Coke/Pepsi</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">3.3</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-bx6-1" block_type="sr2-h">
<box-metadata><box-title><phrase block_type="title">Check Your Understanding</phrase> <phrase block_type="number">5-1</phrase></box-title></box-metadata>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-cyuquestion-1" block_type="q_cyu" number="1">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p001" block_type="sr2-nl-first"><phrase block_type="qnum">1.</phrase> The price of strawberries falls from &#36;1.50 to &#36;1.00 per carton and the quantity demanded goes from 100,000 to 200,000 cartons. Use the midpoint method to find the price elasticity of demand.</p>
</question>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-cyuquestion-2" block_type="q_cyu" number="2">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p001" block_type="sr2-nl-first"><phrase block_type="qnum">2.</phrase> At the present level of consumption, 4,000 movie tickets, and at the current price, &#36;5 per ticket, the price elasticity of demand for movie tickets is 1. Using the midpoint method, calculate the percentage by which the owners of movie theaters must reduce price in order to sell 5,000 tickets.</p>
</question>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-cyuquestion-3" block_type="q_cyu" number="3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p001" block_type="sr2-nl-first"><phrase block_type="qnum">3.</phrase> The price elasticity of demand for ice-cream sandwiches is 1.2 at the current price of &#36;0.50 per sandwich and the current consumption level of 100,000 sandwiches. Calculate the change in the quantity demanded when price rises by &#36;0.05. Use Equations 5-1 and 5-2 to calculate percent changes and Equation 5-3 to relate price elasticity of demand to the percent changes.</p>
</question>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_142" block_type="page_start">142</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p004" block_type="sr2-nl-fn">Solutions appear at back of book.</p>
</box>
<box title="Quick Review" numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-bx5-3" block_type="sr-1-h">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p005" block_type="sr1-txt">The <strong>price elasticity of demand</strong> is equal to the percent change in the quantity demanded divided by the percent change in the price as you move along the demand curve, and dropping any minus sign.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p007" block_type="sr1-txt">In practice, percent changes are best measured using the <strong>midpoint method,</strong> in which the percent changes are calculated using the average of starting and final values.</p>
</box>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-sec1-002" block_type="h1" title="" chapter="5" numbered="true" level="1" print_page="142">
<section-metadata><section-title>Interpreting the Price Elasticity of Demand</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p074" block_type="txt-ni">In a true emergency, a patient is unlikely to question the price of the ambulance ride to the hospital. But even in a non-emergency, like Kira&#8217;s broken teeth, patients are often unlikely to respond to an increase in the price of an ambulance by reducing their demand, because they are unaware of the cost. As a result, investors in private ambulance companies see profit-making opportunities in delivering ambulance services, because the price elasticity of demand is small. But what does that mean? How low does a price elasticity have to be for us to classify it as low? How big does it have to be for us to consider it high? And what determines whether the price elasticity of demand is high or low anyway?</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p075" block_type="txt">To answer these questions, we need to look more deeply at the price elasticity of demand.</p>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-sec2-003" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="5" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="142">
<section-metadata><section-title>How Elastic Is Elastic?</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p076" block_type="txt-ni">As a first step toward classifying price elasticities of demand, let&#8217;s look at the extreme cases.</p>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-exp3-3" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p079" block_type="mn-gl-def">Demand is <strong>perfectly inelastic</strong> when the quantity demanded does not respond at all to changes in the price. When demand is perfectly inelastic, the demand curve is a vertical line.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p077" block_type="txt">First, consider the demand for a good when people pay no attention to the price&#8212;say, snake anti-venom. Suppose that consumers will buy 1,000 doses of anti-venom per year regardless of the price. In this case, the demand curve for anti-venom would look like the curve shown in panel (a) of <link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e_ch5-fig-003">Figure 5-2</link>: it would be a vertical line at 1,000 doses of anti-venom. Since the percent change in the quantity demanded is zero for <em>any</em> change in the price, the price elasticity of demand in this case is zero. The case of a zero price elasticity of demand is known as <strong>perfectly inelastic demand.</strong></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_143" block_type="page_start">143</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-fig-3" block_type="figure" numbered="true" number="5-2" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<caption><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-fig-3"><phrase block_type="fig-label"><strong><phrase block_type="fig">FIGURE</phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_num">5-2</phrase></strong></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_title">Two Extreme Cases of Price Elasticity of Demand</phrase></link></caption>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-img-003" alt="image" src="asset/ch5/KrugESS4e_fig_5_02.jpg"/>
<caption>Panel (a) shows a perfectly inelastic demand curve, which is a vertical line. The quantity of snake anti-venom demanded is always 1,000 doses, regardless of price. As a result, the price elasticity of demand is zero&#8212;the quantity demanded is unaffected by the price. Panel (b) shows a perfectly elastic demand curve, which is a horizontal line. At a price of &#36;5, consumers will buy any quantity of pink tennis balls, but they will buy none at a price above &#36;5. If the price falls below &#36;5, they will buy an extremely large number of pink tennis balls and none of any other color.
</caption>
</figure>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p078" block_type="txt">The opposite extreme occurs when even a tiny rise in the price will cause the quantity demanded to drop to zero or even a tiny fall in the price will cause the quantity demanded to get extremely large.</p>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-exp3-4" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p081" block_type="mn-gl-def">Demand is <strong>perfectly elastic</strong> when any price increase will cause the quantity demanded to drop to zero. When demand is perfectly elastic, the demand curve is a horizontal line.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p080" block_type="txt">Panel (b) of <link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e_ch5-fig-003">Figure 5-2</link> shows the case of pink tennis balls; we suppose that tennis players really don&#8217;t care what color their balls are and that other colors, such as neon green and vivid yellow, are available at &#36;5 per dozen balls. In this case, consumers will buy no pink balls if they cost more than &#36;5 per dozen but will buy only pink balls if they cost less than &#36;5. The demand curve will therefore be a horizontal line at a price of &#36;5 per dozen balls. As you move back and forth along this line, there is a change in the quantity demanded but no change in the price. Roughly speaking, when you divide a number by zero, you get infinity, denoted by the symbol &#8734;. So a horizontal demand curve implies an infinite price elasticity of demand. When the price elasticity of demand is infinite, economists say that demand is <strong>perfectly elastic.</strong></p>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-exp3-5" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p082" block_type="mn-gl-def">Demand is <strong>elastic</strong> if the price elasticity of demand is greater than 1, <strong>inelastic</strong> if the price elasticity of demand is less than 1, and <strong>unit-elastic</strong> if the price elasticity of demand is exactly 1.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p084" block_type="txt">The price elasticity of demand for the vast majority of goods is somewhere between these two extreme cases. Economists use one main criterion for classifying these intermediate cases: they ask whether the price elasticity of demand is greater or less than 1. When the price elasticity of demand is greater than 1, economists say that demand is <strong>elastic.</strong> When the price elasticity of demand is less than 1, they say that demand is <strong>inelastic.</strong> The borderline case is <strong>unit-elastic demand,</strong> where the price elasticity of demand is&#8212;surprise&#8212;exactly 1.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p085" block_type="txt">To see why a price elasticity of demand equal to 1 is a useful dividing line, let&#8217;s consider a hypothetical example: a toll bridge operated by the state highway department. Other things equal, the number of drivers who use the bridge depends on the toll, the price the highway department charges for crossing the bridge: the higher the toll, the fewer the drivers who use the bridge.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p086" block_type="txt"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e_ch5-fig-005">Figure 5-3</link> shows three hypothetical demand curves&#8212;one in which demand is unit-elastic, one in which it is inelastic, and one in which it is elastic. In each case, point <em>A</em> shows the quantity demanded if the toll is &#36;0.90 and point <em>B</em> shows the quantity demanded if the toll is &#36;1.10. An increase in the toll from &#36;0.90 to &#36;1.10 is an increase of 20&#37; if we use the midpoint method to calculate percent changes.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p087" block_type="txt">Panel (a) shows what happens when the toll is raised from &#36;0.90 to &#36;1.10 and the demand curve is unit-elastic. Here the 20&#37; price rise leads to a fall in the quantity of cars using the bridge each day from 1,100 to 900, which is a 20&#37; decline (again using the midpoint method). So the price elasticity of demand is 20&#37;/20&#37; = 1.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p088" block_type="txt">Panel (b) shows a case of inelastic demand when the toll is raised from &#36;0.90 to &#36;1.10. The same 20&#37; price rise reduces the quantity demanded from 1,050 to 950. That&#8217;s only a 10&#37; decline, so in this case the price elasticity of demand is 10&#37;/20&#37; = 0.5.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p089" block_type="txt">Panel (c) shows a case of elastic demand when the toll is raised from &#36;0.90 to &#36;1.10. The 20&#37; price increase causes the quantity demanded to fall from 1,200 to 800&#8212;a 40&#37; decline, so the price elasticity of demand is 40&#37;/20&#37; = 2.</p>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-exp3-6" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p082a" block_type="mn-gl-def">The <strong>total revenue</strong> is the total value of sales of a good or service. It is equal to the price multiplied by the quantity sold.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p090" block_type="txt">Why does it matter whether demand is unit-elastic, inelastic, or elastic? Because this classification predicts how changes in the price of a good will affect the <em>total revenue</em> earned by producers from the sale of that good. In many real-life situations, it is crucial to know how price changes affect total revenue. <strong>Total revenue</strong> is defined as the total value of sales of a good or service, equal to the price multiplied by the quantity sold.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p091" block_type="eq"><strong>(5-6)</strong> Total revenue = Price &#215; Quantity sold</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_144" block_type="page_start">144</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p092" block_type="txt">Total revenue has a useful graphical representation that can help us understand why knowing the price elasticity of demand is crucial when we ask whether a price rise will increase or reduce total revenue. Panel (a) of <link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e_ch5-fig-006">Figure 5-4</link> shows the same demand curve as panel (a) of <link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e_ch5-fig-005">Figure 5-3</link>. We see that 1,100 drivers will use the bridge if the toll is &#36;0.90. So the total revenue at a price of &#36;0.90 is &#36;0.90 &#215; 1,100 = &#36;990. This value is equal to the area of the green rectangle, which is drawn with the bottom left corner at the point (0, 0) and the top right corner at (1,100, 0.90). In general, the total revenue at any given price is equal to the area of a rectangle whose height is the price and whose width is the quantity demanded at that price.</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-fig-5" block_type="figure" numbered="true" number="5-3" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<caption><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-fig-5"><phrase block_type="fig-label"><strong><phrase block_type="fig">FIGURE</phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_num">5-3</phrase></strong></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_title">Unit-Elastic Demand, Inelastic Demand, and Elastic Demand</phrase></link></caption>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-img-005" alt="image" src="asset/ch5/KrugESS4e_fig_5_03.jpg"/>
<caption>Panel (a) shows a case of unit-elastic demand: a 20&#37; increase in price generates a 20&#37; decline in quantity demanded, implying a price elasticity of demand of 1. Panel (b) shows a case of inelastic demand: a 20&#37; increase in price generates a 10&#37; decline in quantity demanded, implying a price elasticity of demand of 0.5. A case of elastic demand is shown in panel&#160;(c): a 20&#37; increase in price causes a 40&#37; decline in quantity demanded, implying a price elasticity of demand of 2. All percentages are calculated using the midpoint method.</caption>
</figure>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p093" block_type="txt">To get an idea of why total revenue is important, consider the following scenario. Suppose that the toll on the bridge is currently &#36;0.90 but that the highway department must raise extra money for road repairs. One way to do this is to raise the toll on the bridge. But this plan might backfire, since a higher toll will reduce the number of drivers who use the bridge. And if traffic on the bridge dropped a lot, a higher toll would actually reduce total revenue instead of increasing it. So it&#8217;s important for the highway department to know how drivers will respond to a toll increase.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_145" block_type="page_start">145</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p094" block_type="txt">We can see graphically how the toll increase affects total bridge revenue by examining panel (b) of <link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e_ch5-fig-006">Figure 5-4</link>. At a toll of &#36;0.90, total revenue is given by the sum of the areas <em>A</em> and <em>B.</em> After the toll is raised to &#36;1.10, total revenue is given by the sum of areas <em>B</em> and <em>C.</em> So when the toll is raised, revenue represented by area <em>A</em> is lost but revenue represented by area <em>C</em> is gained.</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-fig-006" block_type="figure" numbered="true" number="5-4" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<caption><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-fig-006"><phrase block_type="fig-label"><strong><phrase block_type="fig">FIGURE</phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_num">5-4</phrase></strong></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_title">Total Revenue</phrase></link></caption>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-img-006" alt="image" src="asset/ch5/KrugESS4e_fig_5_04.jpg"/>
<caption>The green rectangle in panel (a) shows the total revenue generated from 1,100 drivers who each pay a toll of &#36;0.90. Panel (b) shows how total revenue is affected when the price increases from &#36;0.90 to &#36;1.10. Due to the quantity effect, total revenue falls by area <em>A</em>. Due to the price effect, total revenue increases by the area <em>C</em>. In general, the overall effect can go either way, depending on the price elasticity of demand.</caption>
</figure>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p096" block_type="txt">These two areas have important interpretations. Area <em>C</em> represents the revenue gain that comes from the additional &#36;0.20 paid by drivers who continue to use the bridge. That is, the 900 who continue to use the bridge contribute an additional &#36;0.20 &#215; 900 = &#36;180 per day to total revenue, represented by area <em>C.</em> But 200 drivers who would have used the bridge at a price of &#36;0.90 no longer do so, generating a loss to total revenue of &#36;0.90 &#215; 200 = &#36;180 per day, represented by area <em>A.</em> (In this particular example, because demand is unit-elastic&#8212;the same as in panel (a) of <link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e_ch5-fig-005">Figure 5-3</link>&#8212;the rise in the toll has no effect on total revenue; areas <em>A</em> and <em>C</em> are the same size.)</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p097" block_type="txt">Except in the rare case of a good with perfectly elastic or perfectly inelastic demand, when a seller raises the price of a good, two countervailing effects are present:</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-fig-007" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-img-007" alt="image" src="asset/ch5/KrugESS4e_5UN01.jpg"/>
<caption>The highway department uses the price elasticity of demand to calculate the change in revenue from higher tolls.</caption>
</figure>
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-list-2" type="unordered" block_type="bullet">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p008" block_type="bl-first"><em>A price effect:</em> After a price increase, each unit sold sells at a higher price, which tends to raise revenue.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p009" block_type="bl-last"><em>A quantity effect:</em> After a price increase, fewer units are sold, which tends to lower revenue.</p></li>
</list>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_146" block_type="page_start">146</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0100" block_type="txt">But then, you may ask, what is the ultimate net effect on total revenue: does it go up or down? The answer is that, in general, the effect on total revenue can go either way&#8212;a price rise may either increase total revenue or lower it. If the price effect, which tends to raise total revenue, is the stronger of the two effects, then total revenue goes up. If the quantity effect, which tends to reduce total revenue, is the stronger, then total revenue goes down. And if the strengths of the two effects are exactly equal&#8212;as in our toll bridge example, where a &#36;180 gain offsets a &#36;180 loss&#8212;total revenue is unchanged by the price increase.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0101" block_type="txt">The price elasticity of demand tells us what happens to total revenue when price changes: its size determines which effect&#8212;the price effect or the quantity effect&#8212;is stronger. Specifically:</p>
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-list-3" type="unordered" block_type="bullet">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p010" block_type="bl-first">If demand for a good is <em>unit-elastic</em> (the price elasticity of demand is 1), an increase in price does not change total revenue. In this case, the quantity effect and the price effect exactly offset each other.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p011" block_type="bl-mid">If demand for a good is <em>inelastic</em> (the price elasticity of demand is less than 1), a higher price increases total revenue. In this case, the quantity effect is weaker than the price effect.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p012" block_type="bl-last">If demand for a good is <em>elastic</em> (the price elasticity of demand is greater than 1), an increase in price reduces total revenue. In this case, the quantity effect is stronger than the price effect.</p></li>
</list>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0105" block_type="txt"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-tab-2">Table 5-2</link> shows how the effect of a price increase on total revenue depends on the price elasticity of demand, using the same data as in <link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e_ch5-fig-005">Figure 5-3</link>. An increase in the price from &#36;0.90 to &#36;1.10 leaves total revenue unchanged at &#36;990 when demand is unit-elastic. When demand is inelastic, the quantity effect is dominated by the price effect; the same price increase leads to an increase in total revenue from &#36;945 to &#36;1,045. And when demand is elastic, the quantity effect dominates the price effect; the price increase leads to a decline in total revenue from &#36;1,080 to &#36;880.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0106" block_type="txt">The price elasticity of demand also predicts the effect of a <em>fall</em> in price on total revenue. When the price falls, the same two countervailing effects are present, but they work in the opposite directions as compared to the case of a price rise. There is the price effect of a lower price per unit sold, which tends to lower revenue. This is countered by the quantity effect of more units sold, which tends to raise revenue. Which effect dominates depends on the price elasticity. Here is a quick summary:</p>
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-list-4" type="unordered" block_type="bullet">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p013" block_type="bl-first">When demand is <em>unit-elastic,</em> the two effects exactly balance; so a fall in price has no effect on total revenue.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p014" block_type="bl-mid">When demand is <em>inelastic,</em> the quantity effect is dominated by the price effect; so a fall in price reduces total revenue.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_147" block_type="page_start">147</p>
</li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p015" block_type="bl-last">When demand is <em>elastic,</em> the quantity effect dominates the price effect; so a fall in price increases total revenue.</p></li>
</list>
<table id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-tab-3" block_type="table" numbered="false" caption-placement="Top" data-href="asset/ch5/tables/table_5_3.html" data-target="_pop">
<table_caption><strong><phrase block_type="tbl">TABLE</phrase> <phrase block_type="tbl_num">5-2</phrase> <phrase block_type="tbl_title">Price Elasticity of Demand and Total Revenue</phrase></strong></table_caption>
<tbody>
<tr class="tbl-hdr-bg">
<td class="tbl-rborder"></td>
<td class="tbl-rborder"><strong>Price of toll = &#36;0.90</strong></td>
<td><strong>Price of toll = &#36;1.10</strong></td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-dark">
<td class="tbl-rborder"><strong>Unit-elastic demand</strong><br/>(price elasticity of demand = 1)</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder"></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tbl-rborder">Quantity demanded</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder">1,100</td>
<td>900</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tbl-rborder">Total revenue</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder">&#36;990</td>
<td>&#36;990</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-dark">
<td class="tbl-rborder"><strong>Inelastic demand</strong><br/>(price elasticity of demand = 0.5)</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder"></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tbl-rborder">Quantity demanded</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder">1,050</td>
<td>950</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tbl-rborder">Total revenue</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder">&#36;945</td>
<td>&#36;1,045</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-dark">
<td class="tbl-rborder"><strong>Elastic demand</strong><br/>(price elasticity of demand = 2)</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder"></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tbl-rborder">Quantity demanded</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder">1,200</td>
<td>800</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tbl-rborder">Total revenue</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder">&#36;1,080</td>
<td>&#36;880</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-sec2-004" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="5" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="147">
<section-metadata><section-title>Price Elasticity Along the Demand Curve</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0111" block_type="txt-ni">Suppose an economist says that &#8220;the price elasticity of demand for coffee is 0.25.&#8221; What he or she means is that <em>at the current price</em> the elasticity is 0.25. In the previous discussion of the toll bridge, what we were really describing was the elasticity <em>at the price</em> of &#36;0.90. Why this qualification? Because for the vast majority of demand curves, the price elasticity of demand at one point along the curve is different from the price elasticity of demand at other points along the same curve.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0112" block_type="txt">To see this, consider the table in <link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e_ch5-fig-008">Figure 5-5</link>, which shows a hypothetical demand schedule. It also shows in the last column the total revenue generated at each price and quantity combination in the demand schedule. The upper panel of the graph in <link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e_ch5-fig-008">Figure 5-5</link> shows the corresponding demand curve. The lower panel illustrates the same data on total revenue: the height of a bar at each quantity demanded&#8212;which corresponds to a particular price&#8212;measures the total revenue generated at that price.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_148" block_type="page_start">148</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0113" block_type="txt">In <link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e_ch5-fig-008">Figure 5-5</link>, you can see that when the price is low, raising the price increases total revenue: starting at a price of &#36;1, raising the price to &#36;2 increases total revenue from &#36;9 to &#36;16. This means that when the price is low, demand is inelastic. Moreover, you can see that demand is inelastic on the entire section of the demand curve from a price of &#36;0 to a price of &#36;5.</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-fig-008" block_type="figure" numbered="true" number="5-5" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<caption><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-fig-008"><phrase block_type="fig-label"><strong><phrase block_type="fig">FIGURE</phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_num">5-5</phrase></strong></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_title">The Price Elasticity of Demand Changes Along the Demand Curve</phrase></link></caption>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-img-008" alt="image" src="asset/ch5/KrugESS4e_fig_5_05.jpg"/>
<caption>The upper panel shows a demand curve corresponding to the demand schedule in the table. The lower panel shows how total revenue changes along that demand curve: at each price and quantity combination, the height of the bar represents the total revenue generated. You can see that at a low price, raising the price increases total revenue. So demand is inelastic at low prices. At a high price, however, a rise in price reduces total revenue. So demand is elastic at high prices.</caption>
</figure>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0114" block_type="txt">When the price is high, however, raising it further reduces total revenue: starting at a price of &#36;8, raising the price to &#36;9 reduces total revenue, from &#36;16 to &#36;9. This means that when the price is high, demand is elastic. Furthermore, you can see that demand is elastic over the section of the demand curve from a price of &#36;5 to &#36;10.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0115" block_type="txt">For the vast majority of goods, the price elasticity of demand changes along the demand curve. So whenever you measure a good&#8217;s elasticity, you are really measuring it at a particular point or section of the good&#8217;s demand curve.</p>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-sec2-005" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="5" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="148">
<section-metadata><section-title>What Factors Determine the Price Elasticity of Demand?</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0116" block_type="txt-ni">Investors in private ambulance companies believe that the price elasticity of demand for an ambulance ride is low for two important reasons. First, in many if not most cases, an ambulance ride is a medical necessity. Second, in an emergency there really is no substitute for the standard of care that an ambulance provides. And even among ambulances there are typically no substitutes because in any given geographical area there is usually only one ambulance provider. (The&#160;exceptions are very densely populated areas, but even in those locations an ambulance dispatcher is unlikely to give you a choice of ambulance providers with an accompanying price list.)</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0117" block_type="txt">In general there are four main factors that determine elasticity: whether a good is a necessity or luxury, the availability of close substitutes, the share of income a consumer spends on the good, and how much time has elapsed since a change in price. We&#8217;ll briefly examine each of these factors.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0118" block_type="txt-3"><strong>Whether the Good Is a Necessity or a Luxury</strong> As our opening story illustrates, the price elasticity of demand tends to be low if a good is something you must have, like a life-saving ambulance ride to the hospital. The price elasticity of demand tends to be high if the good is a luxury&#8212;something you can easily live without. For example, most people would consider a 110-inch high-definition TV a luxury&#8212;nice to have, but something they can live without. Therefore, the price elasticity of demand for it will be much higher than for a life-saving ambulance ride to the hospital.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0119" block_type="txt-3"><strong>The Availability of Close Substitutes</strong> As we just noted, the price elasticity of demand tends to be low if there are no close substitutes or if they are very difficult to obtain. In contrast, the price elasticity of demand tends to be high if there are other readily available goods that consumers regard as similar and would be willing to consume instead. For example, most consumers believe that there are&#160;fairly close substitutes to their favorite brand of breakfast cereal. As a result, if the maker of a particular brand of breakfast cereal raised the price significantly, that maker is likely to lose much&#8212;if not all&#8212;of its sales to other brands for which the price has not risen.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0120" block_type="txt-3"><strong>Share of Income Spent on the Good</strong> Consider a good that some people consume frequently, such as gasoline&#8212;say, for a long commute to and from work every day. For these consumers, spending on gasoline will typically absorb a significant share of their income. As a result, when the price of gasoline goes up, these consumers are likely to be very responsive to the price change and have a higher elasticity of demand. Why? Because when the good absorbs a significant share of these consumers&#8217; income, it is worth their time and effort to find a way to reduce their demand when the price goes up&#8212;such as switching to carpooling instead of driving alone. In contrast, people who consume gasoline infrequently&#8212;for example, people who walk to work or take the bus&#8212;will have a low share of income spent on gasoline and therefore a lower elasticity of demand.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_149" block_type="page_start">149</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0121" block_type="txt-3"><strong>Time Elapsed Since Price Change</strong> In general, the price elasticity of demand tends to increase as consumers have more time to adjust. This means that the long-run price elasticity of demand is often higher than the short-run elasticity.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0122" block_type="txt">A good illustration is the changes in Americans&#8217; behavior over the past decade in response to higher gasoline prices. In 1998, a gallon of gasoline was only about &#36;1. Over the years, however, gasoline prices steadily rose, by early 2013 a gallon of gas cost from &#36;3.50 to &#36;4.00 in much of the United States. Over time, however, people changed their habits and choices in ways that enabled them to gradually reduce their gasoline consumption. In a recent survey, 53&#37; of responders said they had made major life changes in order to cope with higher gas prices&#8212;changes such as driving less, getting a more fuel-efficient car, and using other modes of transportation like buses or bicycles. Some even moved to a more convenient location to save gas. These changes are reflected in the data on American gasoline consumption: the trend line of consumption fluctuated until about 2003, then took a nosedive. So by 2013, Americans were purchasing 30 million gallons of gasoline a day on average, less than half of the 64 million they purchased in 2003. This confirms that the long-run price elasticity of demand for gasoline was indeed much larger than the short-run elasticity.</p>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-bx2-4" block_type="bx2-h">
<box-metadata><box-title><phrase block_type="title">ECONOMICS</phrase> <phrase block_type="number"><em>in Action</em></phrase></box-title></box-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0123" block_type="bx2-t"><strong>Responding to Your Tuition Bill</strong></p>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-exp2-2" block_type="mn2">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0124" block_type="fg1-t"><image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-img-018" alt="image" src="asset/images/launchpad_logo_cmyk.jpg"/> &#124; interactive activity</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0125" block_type="bx2-first"><phrase block_type="dropcap">C</phrase>ollege costs more than ever&#8212;and not just because of inflation. Tuition has been rising faster than the overall cost of living for years. But does rising tuition keep people from going to college? Two studies found that the answer depends on the type of college. Both studies assessed how responsive the decision to go to college is to a change in tuition.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0126" block_type="bx2-txt">A 1988 study found that a 3&#37; increase in tuition led to an approximately 2&#37; fall in the number of students enrolled at four-year institutions, giving a price elasticity of demand of 0.67 (2&#37;/3&#37;). In the case of two-year institutions, the study found a significantly higher response: a 3&#37; increase in tuition led to a 2.7&#37; fall in enrollments, giving a price elasticity of demand of 0.9. In other words, the enrollment decision for students at two-year colleges was significantly more responsive to price than for students at four-year colleges. The result: students at two-year colleges are more likely to forgo getting a degree because of tuition costs than students at four-year colleges.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0127" block_type="bx2-txt">A 1999 study confirmed this pattern. In comparison to four-year colleges, it found that two-year college enrollment rates were significantly more responsive to changes in state financial aid (a&#160;decline in aid leading to a decline in enrollments), a predictable effect given these students&#8217; greater sensitivity to the cost of tuition. Another piece of evidence suggests that students at two-year colleges are more likely to be paying their own way and making a trade-off between attending college versus working: the study found that enrollments at two-year colleges are much more responsive to changes in the unemployment rate (an increase in the unemployment rate leading to an increase in enrollments) than enrollments at four-year colleges. So is the cost of tuition a barrier to getting a college degree in the United States? Yes, but more so for students at two-year colleges than for students at four-year colleges.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_150" block_type="page_start">150</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0128" block_type="bx2-txt">In response to decreased state funding, many public colleges and universities have been experimenting with changes to their tuition schedule in order to increase revenue. A 2012 study found that in-state college freshmen were significantly more responsive to the cost of tuition than freshmen from out-of-state. In-state freshmen were found to have a measured elasticity of demand of 1.8; the elasticity of demand for out-of state freshmen was statistically insignificant (that is, virtually zero). Perhaps out-of-state applicants are less price sensitive because they have higher incomes.</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-fig-009" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-img-009" alt="image" src="asset/ch5/KrugESS4e_5UN02.jpg"/>
<caption>Students at two-year schools are more responsive to the price of tuition than students at four-year schools.</caption>
<asset_source>Wavebreakmedia/Shutterstock</asset_source>
</figure>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0129" block_type="bx2-txt">Not surprisingly, many public colleges and universities have found that raising the tuition for enrollments of out-of-state students has boosted revenues.</p>
</box>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-bx6-1" block_type="sr2-h">
<box-metadata><box-title><phrase block_type="title">Check Your Understanding</phrase> <phrase block_type="number">5-2</phrase></box-title></box-metadata>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-cyuquestion-4" block_type="q_cyu" number="1">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p016" block_type="sr2-nl-first"><phrase block_type="qnum">1.</phrase> For each case, choose the condition that characterizes demand: elastic demand, inelastic demand, or unit-elastic demand.</p>
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-list-2" type="ordered" block_type="loweralpha">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p017" block_type="sr2-nl-lvl2">Total revenue decreases when price increases.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p018" block_type="sr2-nl-lvl2">The additional revenue generated by an increase in quantity sold is exactly offset by revenue lost from the fall in price received per unit.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p019" block_type="sr2-nl-lvl2">Total revenue falls when output increases.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p020" block_type="sr2-nl-lvl2">Producers in an industry find they can increase their total revenues by coordinating a reduction in industry output.</p></li>
</list>
</question>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-cyuquestion-5" block_type="q_cyu" number="2">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0135" block_type="sr2-nl-last"><phrase block_type="qnum">2.</phrase> For the following goods, what is the elasticity of demand? Explain. What is the shape of the demand curve?</p>
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-list-3" type="ordered" block_type="loweralpha">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p021" block_type="sr2-nl-lvl2">Demand for a blood transfusion by an accident victim</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p022" block_type="sr2-nl-lvl2">Demand by students for green erasers</p></li>
</list>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0138" block_type="sr2-nl-fn">Solutions appear at back of book.</p>
</question>
</box>
<box title="Quick Review" numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-bx5-5" block_type="sr-1-h">
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-list-5" type="unordered" block_type="redbullet">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p023" block_type="sr1-bl">Demand is <strong>perfectly inelastic</strong> if it is completely unresponsive to price. It is <strong>perfectly elastic</strong> if it is infinitely responsive to price.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p024" block_type="sr1-bl">Demand is <strong>elastic</strong> if the price elasticity of demand is greater than 1. It is <strong>inelastic</strong> if the price elasticity of demand is less than 1. It is <strong>unit-elastic</strong> if the price elasticity of demand is exactly 1.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p026" block_type="sr1-bl">When demand is elastic, the quantity effect of a price increase dominates the price effect and <strong>total revenue</strong> falls. When demand is inelastic, the price effect of a price increase dominates the quantity effect and total revenue rises.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p028" block_type="sr1-bl">Because the price elasticity of demand can change along the demand curve, economists refer to a particular point on the demand curve when speaking of &#8220;the&#8221; price elasticity of demand.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p030" block_type="sr1-bl">Ready availability of close substitutes makes demand for a good more elastic, as does a longer length of time elapsed since the price change. Demand for a necessity is less elastic, and demand for a luxury good is more elastic. Demand tends to be inelastic for goods that absorb a small share of a consumer&#8217;s income and elastic for goods that absorb a large share of income.</p></li>
</list>
</box>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-sec1-003" block_type="h1" title="" chapter="5" numbered="true" level="1" print_page="150">
<section-metadata><section-title>Other Demand Elasticities</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0148" block_type="txt-ni">The quantity of a good demanded depends not only on the price of that good but also on other variables. In particular, demand curves shift because of changes in the prices of related goods and changes in consumers&#8217; incomes. It is often important to have a measure of these other effects, and the best measures are&#8212;you guessed it&#8212;elasticities. Specifically, we can best measure how the demand for a good is affected by prices of other goods using a measure called the <em>cross-price elasticity of demand,</em> and we can best measure how demand is affected by changes in income using the <em>income elasticity of demand.</em></p>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-sec2-006" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="5" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="150">
<section-metadata><section-title>The Cross-Price Elasticity of Demand</section-title></section-metadata>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-exp3-7" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0149" block_type="mn-gl-def">The <strong>cross-price elasticity of demand</strong> between two goods measures the effect of the change in one good&#8217;s price on the quantity demanded of the other good. It is equal to the percent change in the quantity demanded of one good divided by the percent change in the other good&#8217;s price.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0150" block_type="txt-ni">In <link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e_ch3_1.html">Chapter 3</link> you learned that the demand for a good is often affected by the prices of other, related goods&#8212;goods that are substitutes or complements. There you saw that a change in the price of a related good shifts the demand curve of the original good, reflecting a change in the quantity demanded at any given price. The strength of such a &#8220;cross&#8221; effect on demand can be measured by the <strong>cross-price elasticity of demand,</strong> defined as the ratio of the percent change in the quantity demanded of one good to the percent change in the price of the other.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0151" block_type="eq-first"><strong>(5-7)</strong> Cross-price elasticity of demand between goods A and B = <image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-img-019" alt="image" src="asset/ch5/KrugESS4e_5UN27.jpg"/></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0153" block_type="txt">When two goods are substitutes, like hot dogs and hamburgers, the cross-price elasticity of demand is positive: a rise in the price of hot dogs increases the demand for hamburgers&#8212;that is, it causes a rightward shift of the demand curve for hamburgers. If the goods are close substitutes, the cross-price elasticity will be positive and large; if they are not close substitutes, the cross-price elasticity will be positive and small. So when the cross-price elasticity of demand is positive, its size is a measure of how closely substitutable the two goods are, with a higher number meaning the goods are closer substitutes.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_151" block_type="page_start">151</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0154" block_type="txt">When two goods are complements, like hot dogs and hot dog buns, the cross-price elasticity is negative: a rise in the price of hot dogs decreases the demand for hot dog buns&#8212;that is, it causes a leftward shift of the demand curve for hot dog buns. As with substitutes, the size of the cross-price elasticity of demand between two complements tells us how strongly complementary they are: if the cross-price elasticity is only slightly below zero, they are weak complements; if it is very negative, they are strong complements.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0155" block_type="txt">Note that in the case of the cross-price elasticity of demand, the sign (plus or minus) is very important: it tells us whether the two goods are complements or substitutes. So we cannot drop the minus sign as we did for the price elasticity of demand.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0156" block_type="txt">Our discussion of the cross-price elasticity of demand is a useful place to return to a point we made earlier: elasticity is a <em>unit-free</em> measure&#8212;that is, it doesn&#8217;t depend on the units in which goods are measured.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0157" block_type="txt">To see the potential problem, suppose someone told you that &#8220;if the price of hot dog buns rises by &#36;0.30, Americans will buy 10 million fewer hot dogs this year.&#8221; If you&#8217;ve ever bought hot dog buns, you&#8217;ll immediately wonder: is that a &#36;0.30 increase in the price <em>per bun,</em> or is it a &#36;0.30 increase in the price <em>per package</em> (buns are usually sold in packages of eight). It makes a big difference what units we are talking about! However, if someone says that the crossprice elasticity of demand between buns and hot dogs is &#8722;0.3, it doesn&#8217;t matter whether buns are sold individually or by the package. So elasticity is defined as a ratio&#160;of percent changes, as a way of making sure that confusion over units doesn&#8217;t arise.</p>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-sec2-007" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="5" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="151">
<section-metadata><section-title>The Income Elasticity of Demand</section-title></section-metadata>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-exp3-8" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0163" block_type="mn-gl-def">The <strong>income elasticity of demand</strong> is the percent change in the quantity of a good demanded when a consumer&#8217;s income changes divided by the percent change in the consumer&#8217;s income.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0158" block_type="txt-ni">The <strong>income elasticity of demand</strong> is a measure of how much the demand for a good is affected by changes in consumers&#8217; incomes. It allows us to determine whether a good is a normal or inferior good as well as to measure how intensely the demand for the good responds to changes in income.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0159" block_type="eq-first"><strong>(5-8)</strong> Income elasticity of demand = <image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-img-020" alt="image" src="asset/ch5/KrugESS4e_5UN28.jpg"/></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0160" block_type="txt">Just as the cross-price elasticity of demand between two goods can be either positive or negative, depending on whether the goods are substitutes or complements, the income elasticity of demand for a good can also be either positive or negative. Recall from <link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e_ch3_1.html">Chapter 3</link> that goods can be either <em>normal goods,</em> for which demand increases when income rises, or <em>inferior goods,</em> for which demand decreases when income rises. These definitions relate directly to the sign of the income elasticity of demand:</p>
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-list-6" type="unordered" block_type="bullet">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p031" block_type="bl-first">When the income elasticity of demand is positive, the good is a normal good. In this case, the quantity demanded at any given price increases as income increases.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p032" block_type="bl-last">When the income elasticity of demand is negative, the good is an inferior good. In this case, the quantity demanded at any given price decreases as income increases.</p></li>
</list>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-exp3-9" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0164" block_type="mn-gl-def">The demand for a good is <strong>income-elastic</strong> if the income elasticity of demand for that good is greater than 1.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0165" block_type="mn-gl-def">The demand for a good is <strong>income-inelastic</strong> if the income elasticity of demand for that good is positive but less than 1.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0166" block_type="txt">The demand for a good is <strong>income-elastic</strong> if the income elasticity of demand for that good is greater than 1. When income rises, the demand for income-elastic goods rises <em>faster</em> than income. Luxury goods such as second homes and international travel tend to be income-elastic. The demand for a good is <strong>income-inelastic</strong> if the income elasticity of demand for that good is positive but less than 1. When income rises, the demand for income-inelastic goods rises, but more slowly than income. Necessities such as food and clothing tend to be income-inelastic.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_152" block_type="page_start">152</p>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-bx4-6" block_type="bx4-h">
<box-metadata><box-title><image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-img-7a" alt="image" src="asset/images/World_icon_no_type.jpg"/> <phrase block_type="gc1">GLOBAL</phrase> <phrase block_type="gc2">COMPARISON</phrase></box-title></box-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0168" block_type="bx4-t"><strong>Food&#8217;s Bite in World Budgets</strong></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0169" block_type="bx4-txt-ni"><phrase block_type="dropcap">I</phrase>f the income elasticity of demand for food is less than 1, we would expect to find that people in poor countries spend a larger share of their income on food than people in rich countries. And that&#8217;s exactly what the data show. In this graph, we compare per capita income&#8212;a country&#8217;s total income, divided by the population&#8212;with the share of income that is spent on food. (To make the graph a manageable size, per capita income is measured as a percentage of U.S. per capita income.)</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0170" block_type="bx4-txt">In very poor countries, like Pakistan, people spend a large percent of their income on food. In middle-income countries, like Israel and Mexico, the share of spending that goes to food is much lower. And it&#8217;s even lower in rich countries like the United States.</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-fig-010" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-img-0010" alt="image" src="asset/ch5/KrugESS4e_5UN03.jpg"/>
<asset_source><em>Data from:</em> U.S. Department of Agriculture and IMF <em>World Economic Outlook.</em></asset_source>
</figure>
</box>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-bx2-7" block_type="bx2-h">
<box-metadata><box-title><phrase block_type="title">ECONOMICS</phrase> <phrase block_type="number"><em>in Action</em></phrase><image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-img-171a" alt="image" src="asset/images/world_view_icon.jpg"/></box-title></box-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0172"><phrase block_type="bx2-t"><strong>Spending It</strong></phrase></p>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-exp2-3" block_type="mn2">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p08" block_type="fg1-t"><image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-img-002" alt="image" src="asset/images/launchpad_logo_cmyk.jpg"/> &#124; interactive activity</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0172" block_type="bx2-first"><phrase block_type="dropcap">T</phrase>he U.S. Bureau of Labor Statistics carries out extensive surveys of how families spend their incomes. This is not just a matter of intellectual curiosity. Quite a few government benefit programs involve some adjustment for changes in the cost of living; to estimate those changes, the government must know how people spend their money. But an additional payoff to these surveys is data on the income elasticity of demand for various goods.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0173" block_type="bx2-txt">What stands out from these studies? The classic result is that the income elasticity of demand for &#8220;food eaten at home&#8221; is considerably less than 1: as a family&#8217;s income rises, the share of its income spent on food consumed at home falls. Correspondingly, the lower a family&#8217;s income, the higher the share of income spent on food consumed at home.</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-fig-011" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-img-0011" alt="image" src="asset/ch5/KrugESS4e_5UN04.jpg"/>
<caption>Judging by the activity at this busy McDonald&#8217;s, incomes are rising in Vietnam.</caption>
<asset_source>Paula Bronstein/Getty Images</asset_source>
</figure>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0174" block_type="bx2-txt">In poor countries, many families spend more than half their income on food consumed at home. Although the income elasticity of demand for &#8220;food eaten at home&#8221; is estimated at less than 0.5 in the United States, the income elasticity of demand for &#8220;food eaten away from home&#8221; (restaurant meals) is estimated to be much higher&#8212;close to 1.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0175" block_type="bx2-txt">Families with higher incomes eat out more often and at fancier places. In 1950, about 19&#37; of U.S. income was spent on food consumed at home, a number that has dropped to 6.1&#37; in 2012. But over the same time period, the share of U.S. income spent on food consumed away from home has stayed constant at 5&#37;. In fact, a sure sign of rising income levels in developing countries is the arrival of fast-food restaurants that cater to newly affluent customers. For example, McDonald&#8217;s can now be found in Hanoi, Jakarta, and Mumbai.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0176" block_type="bx2-txt">There is one clear example of an inferior good found in the surveys: rental housing. Families with higher income actually spend less on rent than families with lower income, because they are much more likely to own their own homes. And the category identified as &#8220;other housing&#8221;&#8212;which basically means second homes&#8212;is highly income-elastic. Only higher-income families can afford a luxury like a vacation home, so &#8220;other housing&#8221; has an income elasticity of demand greater than 1.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_153" block_type="page_start">153</p>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-bx6-1" block_type="sr2-h">
<box-metadata><box-title><phrase block_type="title">Check Your Understanding</phrase> <phrase block_type="number">5-3</phrase></box-title></box-metadata>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-cyuquestion-6" block_type="q_cyu" number="1">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p033" block_type="sr2-nl-first"><phrase block_type="qnum">1.</phrase> After Chelsea&#8217;s income increased from &#36;12,000 to &#36;18,000 a year, her purchases of music downloads increased from 10 to 40 album downloads per year. Calculate Chelsea&#8217;s income elasticity of demand for albums using the midpoint method.</p>
</question>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-cyuquestion-7" block_type="q_cyu" number="2">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p034" block_type="sr2-nl-mid"><phrase block_type="qnum">2.</phrase> Expensive restaurant meals are income-elastic goods for most people, including Sanjay. Suppose his income falls by 10&#37; this year. What can you predict about the change in Sanjay&#8217;s consumption of expensive restaurant meals?</p>
</question>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-cyuquestion-8" block_type="q_cyu" number="3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p035" block_type="sr2-nl-mid"><phrase block_type="qnum">3.</phrase> As the price of margarine rises by 20&#37;, a manufacturer of baked goods increases its quantity of butter demanded by 5&#37;. Calculate the cross-price elasticity of demand between butter and margarine. Are butter and margarine substitutes or complements for this manufacturer?</p>
</question>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p036" block_type="sr2-nl-fn">Solutions appear at back of book.</p>
</box>
<box title="Quick Review" numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-bx5-8" block_type="sr-1-h">
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-list-7" type="unordered" block_type="redbullet">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p037" block_type="sr1-bl">Goods are substitutes when the <strong>cross-price elasticity of demand</strong> is positive. Goods are complements when the cross-price elasticity of demand is negative.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p039" block_type="sr1-bl">Inferior goods have a negative <strong>income elasticity of demand.</strong> Most goods are normal goods, which have a positive income elasticity of demand.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p040" block_type="sr1-bl">Normal goods may be either <strong>income-elastic,</strong> with an income elasticity of demand greater than 1, or <strong>income-inelastic,</strong> with an income elasticity of demand that is positive but less than 1.</p></li>
</list>
</box>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-sec1-004" block_type="h1" title="" chapter="5" numbered="true" level="1" print_page="153">
<section-metadata><section-title>The Price Elasticity of Supply</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0186" block_type="txt-ni">A fundamental characteristic of any market for ambulance services, no matter where it is located, is limited supply. For example, it would have been much harder to charge Kira Mills &#36;1,772.42 for a 15-minute ride to the hospital if there had been many ambulance providers cruising nearby and offering a lower price. But there are good economic reasons why there are not: who among those experiencing a true health emergency would trust their health and safety to a &#8220;low-price&#8221; ambulance? And who would want to be a supplier, paying the expense of providing quality ambulance services, without being able to charge high prices to recoup costs? Not surprisingly, then, in most locations there is only one ambulance provider available, as we have seen.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0187" block_type="txt">In sum, a critical element in the ability of ambulance providers to charge high prices is limited supply: a low responsiveness in the quantity of output supplied to the higher prices charged for an ambulance ride. To measure the response of ambulance providers to price changes, we need a measure parallel to the price elasticity of demand&#8212;the <em>price elasticity of supply,</em> as we&#8217;ll see next.</p>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-sec2-008" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="5" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="153">
<section-metadata><section-title>Measuring the Price Elasticity of Supply</section-title></section-metadata>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-exp3-10" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0188" block_type="mn-gl-def">The <strong>price elasticity of supply</strong> is a measure of the responsiveness of the quantity of a good supplied to the price of that good. It is the ratio of the percent change in the quantity supplied to the percent change in the price as we move along the supply curve.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0189" block_type="txt-ni">The <strong>price elasticity of supply</strong> is defined the same way as the price elasticity of demand (although there is no minus sign to be eliminated here):</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0190" block_type="eq-first"><strong>(5-9)</strong> Price elasticity of supply = <image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-img-021" alt="image" src="asset/ch5/KrugESS4e_5UN29.jpg"/></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0191" block_type="txt-ni">The only difference is that now we consider movements along the supply curve rather than movements along the demand curve.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0192" block_type="txt">Suppose that the price of tomatoes rises by 10&#37;. If the quantity of tomatoes supplied also increases by 10&#37; in response, the price elasticity of supply of tomatoes is 1 (10&#37;/10&#37;) and supply is unit-elastic. If the quantity supplied increases by 5&#37;, the price elasticity of supply is 0.5 and supply is inelastic; if the quantity increases by 20&#37;, the price elasticity of supply is 2 and supply is elastic.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0193" block_type="txt">As in the case of demand, the extreme values of the price elasticity of supply have a simple graphical representation. Panel (a) of <link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e_ch5-fig-012">Figure 5-6</link> shows the supply of cell phone frequencies, the portion of the radio spectrum that is suitable for sending and receiving cell phone signals. Governments own the right to sell the use of this part of the radio spectrum to cell phone operators inside their borders. But governments can&#8217;t increase or decrease the number of cell phone frequencies that they have to offer&#8212;for technical reasons, the quantity of frequencies suitable for cell phone operation is a fixed quantity.</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-fig-012" block_type="figure" numbered="true" number="5-6" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<caption><phrase block_type="fig-label"><strong><phrase block_type="fig">FIGURE</phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_num">5-6</phrase></strong></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_title">Two Extreme Cases of Price Elasticity of Supply</phrase></caption>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-img-0012" alt="image" src="asset/ch5/KrugESS4e_fig_5_06.jpg"/>
<caption>Panel (a) shows a perfectly inelastic supply curve, which is a vertical line. The price elasticity of supply is zero: the quantity supplied is always the same, regardless of price. Panel (b) shows a perfectly elastic supply curve, which is a horizontal line. At a price of &#36;12, producers will supply any quantity, but they will supply none at a price below &#36;12. If price rises above &#36;12, they will supply an extremely large quantity.</caption>
</figure>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-exp3-11" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0195" block_type="mn-gl-def">There is <strong>perfectly inelastic supply</strong> when the price elasticity of supply is zero, so that changes in the price of the good have no effect on the quantity supplied. A perfectly inelastic supply curve is a vertical line.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_154" block_type="page_start">154</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0196" block_type="txt">So the supply curve for cell phone frequencies is a vertical line, which we have assumed is set at the quantity of 100 frequencies. As you move up and down that curve, the change in the quantity supplied by the government is zero, whatever the change in price. So panel (a) illustrates a case in which the price elasticity of supply is zero. This is a case of <strong>perfectly inelastic supply.</strong></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0197" block_type="txt">Panel (b) shows the supply curve for pizza. We suppose that it costs &#36;12 to produce a pizza, including all opportunity costs. At any price below &#36;12, it would be unprofitable to produce pizza and all the pizza parlors in America would go out of business. Alternatively, there are many producers who could operate pizza parlors if they were profitable. The ingredients&#8212;flour, tomatoes, cheese&#8212;are plentiful. And if necessary, more tomatoes could be grown, more milk could be produced to make mozzarella, and so on. So any price above &#36;12 would elicit an extremely large quantity of pizzas supplied. The implied supply curve is therefore a horizontal line at &#36;12.</p>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-exp3-12" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0198" block_type="mn-gl-def">There is <strong>perfectly elastic supply</strong> when even a tiny increase or reduction in the price will lead to very large changes in the quantity supplied, so that the price elasticity of supply is infinite. A perfectly elastic supply curve is a horizontal line.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0199" block_type="txt">Since even a tiny increase in the price would lead to a huge increase in the quantity supplied, the price elasticity of supply would be more or less infinite. This is a case of <strong>perfectly elastic supply.</strong></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0200" block_type="txt">As our cell phone frequencies and pizza examples suggest, real-world instances of both perfectly inelastic and perfectly elastic supply are easy to find&#8212;much easier than their counterparts in demand.</p>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-sec2-009" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="5" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="154">
<section-metadata><section-title>What Factors Determine the Price Elasticity of Supply?</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0201" block_type="txt-ni">Our examples tell us the main determinant of the price elasticity of supply: the availability of inputs. In addition, as with the price elasticity of demand, time may also play a role in the price elasticity of supply. Here we briefly summarize the two factors.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0202" block_type="txt-3"><strong>The Availability of Inputs</strong> The price elasticity of supply tends to be large when inputs are readily available and can be shifted into and out of production at a relatively low cost. It tends to be small when inputs are difficult to obtain&#8212;and can be shifted into and out of production only at a relatively high cost. In the case of ambulance services, the high cost of providing quality ambulance services is the crucial element in keeping the elasticity of supply very low.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_155" block_type="page_start">155</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0203" block_type="txt-3"><strong>Time</strong> The price elasticity of supply tends to grow larger as producers have more time to respond to a price change. This means that the long-run price elasticity of supply is often higher than the short-run elasticity.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0204" block_type="txt">The price elasticity of the supply of pizza is very high because the inputs needed to expand the industry are readily available. The price elasticity of cell phone frequencies is zero because an essential input&#8212;the radio spectrum&#8212;cannot be increased at all.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0205" block_type="txt">Many industries are like pizza production and have large price elasticities of supply: they can be readily expanded because they don&#8217;t require any special or unique resources. In contrast, the price elasticity of supply is usually substantially less than perfectly elastic for goods that involve limited natural resources: minerals like gold or copper, agricultural products like coffee that flourish only on certain types of land, and renewable resources like ocean fish that can only be exploited up to a point without destroying the resource.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0206" block_type="txt">But given enough time, producers are often able to significantly change the amount they produce in response to a price change, even when production involves a limited natural resource or a very costly input. Agricultural markets provide a good example. When American farmers receive much higher prices for a given commodity, like wheat (because of a drought in a big wheat-producing country like Australia), in the next planting season they are likely to switch their acreage planted from other crops to wheat.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0207" block_type="txt">For this reason, economists often make a distinction between the short-run elasticity of supply, usually referring to a few weeks or months, and the long-run elasticity of supply, usually referring to several years. In most industries, the long-run elasticity of supply is larger than the short-run elasticity.</p>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-bx2-9" block_type="bx2-h">
<box-metadata><box-title><phrase block_type="title">ECONOMICS</phrase> <phrase block_type="number"><em>in Action</em></phrase><image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-img-208a" alt="image" src="asset/images/world_view_icon.jpg"/></box-title></box-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0208" block_type="bx2-t"><strong>European Farm Surpluses</strong></p>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-exp2-4" block_type="mn2">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0273" block_type="fg1-t"><image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-img-026" alt="image" src="asset/images/launchpad_logo_cmyk.jpg"/> &#124; interactive activity</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0210" block_type="bx2-first"><phrase block_type="dropcap">O</phrase>ne of the policies we analyzed in <link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e_ch4_1.html">Chapter 4</link> was the imposition of a <em>price floor,</em> a lower limit below which price of a good could not fall. We saw that price floors are often used by governments to support the incomes of farmers but create large unwanted surpluses of farm products. The most dramatic example of this is found in the European Union, where price floors have created a &#8220;butter mountain,&#8221; a &#8220;wine lake,&#8221; and so on.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0211" block_type="bx2-txt">Were European politicians unaware that their price floors would create huge surpluses? They probably knew that surpluses would arise but underestimated the price elasticity of agricultural supply. In fact, when the agricultural price supports were put in place, many analysts thought they were unlikely to lead to big increases in production. After all, European countries are densely populated and there is little new land available for cultivation.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0212" block_type="bx2-txt">What the analysts failed to realize, however, was how much farm production could expand by adding other resources, especially fertilizer and pesticides, which were readily available. So although European farm acreage didn&#8217;t increase much in response to the imposition of price floors, European farm production did!</p>
</box>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-bx6-1" block_type="sr2-h">
<box-metadata><box-title><phrase block_type="title">Check Your Understanding</phrase> <phrase block_type="number">5-4</phrase></box-title></box-metadata>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-cyuquestion-9" block_type="q_cyu" number="1">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p041" block_type="sr2-nl-first"><phrase block_type="qnum">1.</phrase> Using the midpoint method, calculate the price elasticity of supply for web-design services when the price per hour rises from &#36;100 to &#36;150 and the number of hours transacted increases from 300,000 to 500,000. Is supply elastic, inelastic, or unit-elastic?</p>
</question>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-cyuquestion-10" block_type="q_cyu" number="2">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p042" block_type="sr2-nl-mid"><phrase block_type="qnum">2.</phrase> True or false? If the demand for milk rose, then, in the long run, milk-drinkers would be better off if supply were elastic rather than inelastic.</p>
</question>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_156" block_type="page_start">156</p>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-cyuquestion-11" block_type="q_cyu" number="3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p043" block_type="sr2-nl-mid"><phrase block_type="qnum">3.</phrase> True or false? Long-run price elasticities of supply are generally larger than short-run price elasticities of supply. As a result, the short-run supply curves are generally flatter than the long-run supply curves.</p>
</question>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-cyuquestion-12" block_type="q_cyu" number="4">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p044" block_type="sr2-nl-mid"><phrase block_type="qnum">4.</phrase> True or false? When supply is perfectly elastic, changes in demand have no effect on price.</p>
</question>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p045" block_type="sr2-nl-fn">Solutions appear at back of book.</p>
</box>
<box title="Quick Review" numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-bx5-10" block_type="sr-1-h">
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-list-6" type="unordered" block_type="redbullet">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0219" block_type="sr1-bl">The <strong>price elasticity of supply</strong> is the percent change in the quantity supplied divided by the percent change in the price.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0220" block_type="sr1-bl">Under <strong>perfectly inelastic supply,</strong> the quantity supplied is completely unresponsive to price and the supply curve is a vertical line. Under <strong>perfectly elastic supply,</strong> the supply curve is horizontal at some specific price. If the price falls below that level, the quantity supplied is zero. If the price rises above that level, the quantity supplied is extremely large.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0222" block_type="sr1-bl">The price elasticity of supply depends on the availability of inputs, the ease of shifting inputs into and out of alternative uses, and the period of time that has elapsed since the price change.</p></li>
</list>
</box>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-sec1-005" block_type="h1" title="" chapter="5" numbered="true" level="1" print_page="156">
<section-metadata><section-title>An Elasticity Menagerie</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0223" block_type="txt-ni">We&#8217;ve just run through quite a few different elasticities. Keeping them all straight can be a challenge. So in <link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-tab-3">Table 5-3</link> we provide a summary of all the elasticities we have discussed and their implications.</p>
<table id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-tab-4" block_type="table" numbered="false" caption-placement="Top" data-href="asset/ch5/tables/table_5_4.html" data-target="_pop">
<table_caption><strong><phrase block_type="tbl">TABLE</phrase> <phrase block_type="tbl_num">5-3</phrase> <phrase block_type="tbl_title">An Elasticity Menagerie</phrase></strong></table_caption>
<tbody>
<tr class="tbl-td-dark">
<td colspan="2"><strong>Price elasticity of demand = <image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-img-022" alt="image" src="asset/ch5/KrugESS4e_5UN30.jpg"/> (dropping the minus sign)</strong></td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td>0</td>
<td><strong>Perfectly inelastic:</strong> price has no effect on quantity demanded (vertical demand curve).</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td>Between 0 and 1</td>
<td><strong>Inelastic:</strong> a rise in price increases total revenue.</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td>Exactly 1</td>
<td><strong>Unit-elastic:</strong> changes in price have no effect on total revenue.</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td>Greater than 1, less than &#8734;</td>
<td><strong>Elastic:</strong> a rise in price reduces total revenue.</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td>&#8734;</td>
<td><strong>Perfectly elastic:</strong> any rise in price causes quantity demanded to fall to 0. Any fall in price leads to an infinite quantity demanded (horizontal demand curve).</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-dark">
<td colspan="2"><strong>Cross-price elasticity of demand = <image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-img-023" alt="image" src="asset/ch5/KrugESS4e_5UN31.jpg"/></strong></td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td>Negative</td>
<td><strong>Complements:</strong> quantity demanded of one good falls when the price of another rises.</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td>Positive</td>
<td><strong>Substitutes:</strong> quantity demanded of one good rises when the price of another rises.</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-dark">
<td colspan="2"><strong>Income elasticity of demand = <image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-img-024" alt="image" src="asset/ch5/KrugESS4e_5UN32.jpg"/></strong></td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td>Negative</td>
<td><strong>Inferior good:</strong> quantity demanded falls when income rises.</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td>Positive, less than 1</td>
<td><strong>Normal good, income-inelastic:</strong> quantity demanded rises when income rises, but not as rapidly as income.</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td>Greater than 1</td>
<td><strong>Normal good, income-elastic:</strong> quantity demanded rises when income rises, and more rapidly than income.</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-dark">
<td colspan="2"><strong>Price elasticity of supply = <image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-img-025" alt="image" src="asset/ch5/KrugESS4e_5UN33.jpg"/></strong></td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td>0</td>
<td><strong>Perfectly inelastic:</strong> price has no effect on quantity supplied (vertical supply curve).</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td>Greater than 0, less than &#8734;</td>
<td>ordinary upward-sloping supply curve.</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td>&#8734;</td>
<td><strong>Perfectly elastic:</strong> any fall in price causes quantity supplied to fall to 0. Any rise in price elicits an infinite quantity supplied (horizontal supply curve).</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-sec1-006" block_type="h1" title="" chapter="5" numbered="true" level="1" print_page="157">
<section-metadata><section-title>The Benefits and Costs of Taxation</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_157" block_type="page_start">157</p>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-exp3-13" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0224" block_type="mn-gl-def">An <strong>excise tax</strong> is a tax on sales of a good or service.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0225" block_type="txt-ni">When a government is considering whether to impose a tax or how to design a tax system, it has to weigh the benefits of a tax against its costs. We don&#8217;t usually think of a tax as something that provides benefits, but governments need money to provide things people want, such as national defense and health care for those unable to afford it. The benefit of a tax is the revenue it raises for the government to pay for these services. Unfortunately, this benefit comes at a cost&#8212;a cost that is normally greater than the amount consumers and producers pay. Let&#8217;s look first at what determines how much money a tax raises, then at the costs a tax imposes, both of which are dependent upon the elasticity of supply and demand. To understand the economics of taxes, it&#8217;s helpful to look at a simple type of tax known as an <strong>excise tax&#8212;</strong>a tax charged on each unit of a good or service that is sold.</p>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-sec2-010" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="5" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="157">
<section-metadata><section-title>The Revenue from an Excise Tax</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0226" block_type="txt-ni">Suppose that the supply and demand for hotel rooms in the city of Potterville are as shown in <link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e_ch5-fig-013">Figure 5-7</link>. For simplicity, assume that all hotel rooms offer the same features. In the absence of taxes, the equilibrium price of a room is &#36;80.00 per night and the equilibrium quantity of hotel rooms rented is 10,000 per night.</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-fig-013" block_type="figure" numbered="true" number="5-7" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<caption><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-fig-013"><phrase block_type="fig-label"><strong><phrase block_type="fig">FIGURE</phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_num">5-7</phrase></strong></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_title">The Revenue from an Excise Tax</phrase></link></caption>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-img-0013" alt="image" src="asset/ch5/KrugESS4e_fig_5_07.jpg"/>
<caption>The revenue from a &#36;40 excise tax on hotel rooms is &#36;200,000, equal to the tax rate, &#36;40&#8212;the size of the wedge that the tax drives between the supply price and the demand price&#8212;multiplied by the number of rooms rented, 5,000. This is equal to the area of the shaded rectangle.</caption>
</figure>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0227" block_type="txt">Now suppose that Potterville&#8217;s city council imposes an excise tax of &#36;40 per night on hotel rooms&#8212;that is, every time a room is rented for the night, the owner of the hotel must pay the city &#36;40. For example, if a customer pays &#36;80, &#36;40 is collected as a tax, leaving the hotel owner with only &#36;40.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0228" block_type="txt">How much revenue will the government collect from this excise tax? In this case, the revenue is equal to the area of the shaded rectangle in <link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e_ch5-fig-013">Figure 5-7</link>.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0229" block_type="txt">To see why this area represents the revenue collected by a &#36;40 tax on hotel rooms, notice that the height of the rectangle is &#36;40, equal to the tax per room. It is also, as we&#8217;ve seen, the size of the wedge that the tax drives between the supply price (the price received by producers) and the demand price (the price paid by consumers). Meanwhile, the width of the rectangle is 5,000 rooms, equal to the equilibrium quantity of rooms given the &#36;40 tax. With that information, we can make the following calculations.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0230" block_type="txt">The tax revenue collected is:</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0231" block_type="eq">Tax revenue = &#36;40 per room &#215; 5,000 rooms = &#36;200,000</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_158" block_type="page_start">158</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0232" block_type="txt-ni">The area of the shaded rectangle is:</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0233" block_type="eq">Area = Height &#215; Width = &#36;40 per room &#215; 5,000 rooms = &#36;200,000</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0234" block_type="txt-ni">or</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0235" block_type="eq">Tax revenue = Area of shaded rectangle</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0236" block_type="txt">This is a general principle: <em>The revenue collected by an excise tax is equal to the area of the rectangle whose height is the tax wedge between the supply and demand curves and whose width is the quantity transacted under the tax.</em></p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-fig-014" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-img-0014" alt="image" src="asset/ch5/KrugESS4e_5UN05.jpg"/>
<caption><em>&#8220;What taxes would you like to see imposed on other people?&#8221;</em></caption>
<asset_source>&#169; Jeremy Banx</asset_source>
</figure>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-sec2-011" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="5" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="158">
<section-metadata><section-title>Tax Rates and Revenue</section-title></section-metadata>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-exp3-14" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p020" block_type="mn-gl-def">A <strong>tax rate</strong> is the amount of tax people are required to pay per unit of whatever is being taxed.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0237" block_type="txt-ni">In <link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e_ch5-fig-013">Figure 5-7</link>, &#36;40 per room is the <em>tax rate</em> on hotel rooms. A <strong>tax rate</strong> is the amount of tax levied per unit of whatever is being taxed. Sometimes tax rates are defined in terms of dollar amounts per unit of a good or service; for example, &#36;2.46 per pack of cigarettes sold. In other cases, they are defined as a percentage of the price; for example, the payroll tax is 15.3&#37; of a worker&#8217;s earnings up to &#36;117,000.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0238" block_type="txt">There&#8217;s obviously a relationship between tax rates and revenue. That relationship is not, however, one-for-one. In general, doubling the excise tax rate on a good or service won&#8217;t double the amount of revenue collected, because the tax increase will reduce the quantity of the good or service transacted. And the relationship between the level of the tax and the amount of revenue collected may not even be positive: in some cases raising the tax rate actually <em>reduces</em> the amount of revenue the government collects.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0239" block_type="txt">We can illustrate these points using our hotel room example. <link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e_ch5-fig-013">Figure 5-7</link> showed the revenue the government collects from a &#36;40 tax on hotel rooms. <link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e_ch5-fig-015">Figure 5-8</link> shows the revenue the government would collect from two alternative tax rates&#8212;a lower tax of only &#36;20 per room and a higher tax of &#36;60 per room.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0240" block_type="txt">Panel (a) of <link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e_ch5-fig-015">Figure 5-8</link> shows the case of a &#36;20 tax, equal to half the tax rate illustrated in <link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e_ch5-fig-013">Figure 5-7</link>. At this lower tax rate, 7,500 rooms are rented, generating tax revenue of:</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0241" block_type="eq">Tax revenue = &#36;20 per room &#215; 7,500 rooms = &#36;150,000</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0242" block_type="txt">Recall that the tax revenue collected from a &#36;40 tax rate is &#36;200,000. So the revenue collected from a &#36;20 tax rate, &#36;150,000, is only 75&#37; of the amount collected when the tax rate is twice as high (&#36;150,000/&#36;200,000 &#215; 100 = 75&#37;). To put it another way, a 100&#37; increase in the tax rate from &#36;20 to &#36;40 per room leads to only a one-third, or 33.3&#37;, increase in revenue, from &#36;150,000 to &#36;200,000 ((&#36;200,000 &#8722; &#36;150,000)/&#36;150,000 &#215; 100 = 33.3&#37;).</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0243" block_type="txt">Panel (b) depicts what happens if the tax rate is raised from &#36;40 to &#36;60 per room, leading to a fall in the number of rooms rented from 5,000 to 2,500. The revenue collected at a &#36;60 per room tax rate is:</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0244" block_type="eq">Tax revenue = &#36;60 per room &#215; 2,500 rooms = &#36;150,000</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0245" block_type="txt">This is also <em>less</em> than the revenue collected by a &#36;40 per room tax. So raising the tax rate from &#36;40 to &#36;60 actually reduces revenue. More precisely, in this case raising the tax rate by 50&#37; ((&#36;60 &#8722; &#36;40)/&#36;40 &#215; 100 = 50&#37;) lowers the tax revenue by 25&#37; ((&#36;150,000 &#8722; &#36;200,000)/&#36;200,000 &#215; 100 = &#8722;25&#37;). Why did this happen? Because the fall in tax revenue caused by the reduction in the number of rooms rented more than offset the increase in the tax revenue caused by the rise in the tax rate. In other words, setting a tax rate so high that it deters a significant number of transactions will likely lead to a fall in tax revenue.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_159" block_type="page_start">159</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0246" block_type="txt">One way to think about the revenue effect of increasing an excise tax is that the tax increase affects tax revenue in two ways. On one side, the tax increase means that the government raises more revenue for each unit of the good sold, which other things equal would lead to a rise in tax revenue. On the other side, the tax increase reduces the quantity of sales, which other things equal would lead to a fall in tax revenue. The end result depends both on the price elasticities of supply and demand and on the initial level of the tax.</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-fig-015" block_type="figure" numbered="true" number="5-8" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<caption><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-fig-015"><phrase block_type="fig-label"><strong><phrase block_type="fig">FIGURE</phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_num">5-8</phrase></strong></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_title">Tax Rates and Revenue</phrase></link></caption>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-img-0015" alt="image" src="asset/ch5/KrugESS4e_fig_5_08.jpg"/>
<caption>In general, doubling the excise tax rate on a good or service won&#8217;t double the amount of revenue collected, because the tax increase will reduce the quantity of the good or service bought and sold. And the relationship between the level of the tax and the amount of revenue collected may not even be positive. Panel (a) shows the revenue raised by a tax rate of &#36;20 per room, only half the tax rate in <link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e_ch5-fig-013">Figure 5-7</link>. The tax revenue raised, equal to the area of the shaded rectangle, is &#36;150,000. That is 75&#37; of &#36;200,000, the revenue raised by a &#36;40 tax rate. Panel (b) shows that the revenue raised by a &#36;60 tax rate is also &#36;150,000. So raising the tax rate from &#36;40 to &#36;60 actually reduces tax revenue.</caption>
</figure>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0247" block_type="txt">If the price elasticities of both supply and demand are low, the tax increase won&#8217;t reduce the quantity of the good sold very much, so tax revenue will definitely rise. If the price elasticities are high, the result is less certain; if they are high enough, the tax reduces the quantity sold so much that tax revenue falls. Also, if the initial tax rate is low, the government doesn&#8217;t lose much revenue from the decline in the quantity of the good sold, so the tax increase will definitely increase tax revenue. If the initial tax rate is high, the result is again less certain. Tax revenue is likely to fall or rise very little from a tax increase only in cases where the price elasticities are high and there is already a high tax rate.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0248" block_type="txt">The possibility that a higher tax rate can reduce tax revenue, and the corresponding possibility that cutting taxes can increase tax revenue, is a basic principle of taxation that policy makers take into account when setting tax rates. That is, when considering a tax created for the purpose of raising revenue (in contrast to taxes created to discourage undesirable behavior, known as &#8220;sin taxes&#8221;), a well-informed policy maker won&#8217;t impose a tax rate so high that cutting the tax would increase revenue.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0249" block_type="txt">In the real world, however, policy makers aren&#8217;t always well informed, but they usually aren&#8217;t complete fools either. That&#8217;s why it&#8217;s very hard to find real-world examples in which raising a tax reduced revenue or cutting a tax increased revenue.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_160" block_type="page_start">160</p>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-sec2-012" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="5" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="160">
<section-metadata><section-title>The Costs of Taxation</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0250" block_type="txt-ni">What is the cost of a tax? You might be inclined to answer that it is the money taxpayers pay to the government. In other words, you might believe that the cost of a tax is the tax revenue collected. But suppose the government uses the tax revenue to provide services that taxpayers want. Or suppose that the government simply hands the tax revenue back to taxpayers. Would we say in those cases that the tax didn&#8217;t actually cost anything?</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0251" block_type="txt">No&#8212;because a tax, like a quota, prevents mutually beneficial transactions from occurring. Consider <link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e_ch5-fig-013">Figure 5-7</link> once more. Here, with a &#36;40 tax on hotel rooms, guests pay &#36;100 per room but hotel owners receive only &#36;60 per room. Because of the wedge created by the tax, we know that some transactions don&#8217;t occur that would have occurred without the tax.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0252" block_type="txt">For example, we know from the supply and demand curves that there are some potential guests who would be willing to pay up to &#36;90 per night and some hotel owners who would be willing to supply rooms if they received at least &#36;70&#160;per night. If these two sets of people were allowed to trade with each other without the tax, they would engage in mutually beneficial transactions&#8212;hotel rooms would be rented.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0253" block_type="txt">But such deals would be illegal, because the &#36;40 tax would not be paid. In our example, 5,000 potential hotel room rentals that would have occurred in the absence of the tax, to the mutual benefit of guests and hotel owners, do not take place because of the tax.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0254" block_type="txt">So an excise tax imposes costs over and above the tax revenue collected in the form of inefficiency, which occurs because the tax discourages mutually beneficial transactions. As we learned in <link href="krugmanwellsessentials4e_ch4_1.html">Chapter 4</link>, the cost to society of this kind of inefficiency&#8212;the value of the forgone mutually beneficial transactions&#8212;is called the deadweight loss. While all real-world taxes impose some deadweight loss, a badly designed tax imposes a larger deadweight loss than a well-designed one.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_161" block_type="page_start">161</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0255" block_type="txt">To measure the deadweight loss from a tax, we turn to the concepts of producer and consumer surplus. <link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e_ch5-fig-016">Figure 5-9</link> shows the effects of an excise tax on consumer and producer surplus. In the absence of the tax, the equilibrium is at <em>E</em> and the equilibrium price and quantity are <em>P<sub>E</sub></em> and <em>Q<sub>E</sub>,</em> respectively. An excise tax drives a wedge equal to the amount of the tax between the price received by producers and the price paid by consumers, reducing the quantity sold. In this case, where the tax is <em>T</em> dollars per unit, the quantity sold falls to <em>Q<sub>T</sub>.</em> The price paid by consumers rises to <em>P<sub>C</sub>,</em> the demand price of the reduced quantity, <em>Q<sub>T</sub>,</em> and the price received by producers falls to <em>P<sub>P</sub>,</em> the supply price of that quantity. The difference between these prices, <em>P<sub>C</sub></em> &#8722; <em>P<sub>P</sub>,</em> is equal to the excise tax, <em>T.</em></p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-fig-016" block_type="figure" numbered="true" number="5-9" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<caption><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-fig-016"><phrase block_type="fig-label"><strong><phrase block_type="fig">FIGURE</phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_num">5-9</phrase></strong></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_title">A Tax Reduces Consumer and Producer Surplus</phrase></link></caption>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-img-0016" alt="image" src="asset/ch5/KrugESS4e_fig_5_09.jpg"/>
<caption>Before the tax, the equilibrium price and quantity are <em>P<sub>E</sub></em> and <em>Q<sub>E</sub>,</em> respectively. After an excise tax of <em>T</em> per unit is imposed, the price to consumers rises to <em>P<sub>C</sub></em> and consumer surplus falls by the sum of the dark blue rectangle, labeled <em>A,</em> and the light blue triangle, labeled <em>B.</em> The tax also causes the price to producers to fall to <em>P<sub>P</sub>;</em> producer surplus falls by the sum of the red rectangle, labeled <em>C,</em> and the pink triangle, labeled <em>F.</em> The government receives revenue from the tax equal to <em>Q</em>(<em>T</em>) &#215; <em>T</em>, which is given by the sum of the areas <em>A</em> and <em>C</em>. Areas <em>B</em> and <em>F</em> represent the losses to consumer and producer surplus that are not collected by the government as revenue. They are the deadweight loss to society of the tax.</caption>
</figure>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0256" block_type="txt">The rise in the price paid by consumers causes a loss equal to the sum of the areas of a rectangle and a triangle: the dark blue rectangle labeled <em>A</em> and the area of the light blue triangle labeled <em>B</em> in <link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e_ch5-fig-016">Figure 5-9</link>.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0257" block_type="txt">Meanwhile, the fall in the price received by producers leads to a fall in producer surplus. This, too, is equal to the sum of the areas of a rectangle and a triangle. The loss in producer surplus is the sum of the areas of the red rectangle labeled <em>C</em> and the pink triangle labeled <em>F</em> in <link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e_ch5-fig-016">Figure 5-9</link>.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0258" block_type="txt">Of course, although consumers and producers are hurt by the tax, the government gains revenue. The revenue the government collects is equal to the tax per unit sold, <em>T</em>, multiplied by the quantity sold, <em>Q<sub>T</sub>.</em> This revenue is equal to the area of a rectangle <em>Q<sub>T</sub></em> wide and <em>T</em> high. And we already have that rectangle in the figure: it is the sum of rectangles <em>A</em> and <em>C</em>. So the government gains part of what consumers and producers lose from an excise tax.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0259" block_type="txt">But a portion of the loss to producers and consumers from the tax is not offset by a gain to the government&#8212;specifically, the two triangles <em>B</em> and <em>F</em>. The deadweight loss caused by the tax is equal to the combined area of these two triangles. It represents the total surplus lost to society because of the tax&#8212;that is, the amount of surplus that would have been generated by transactions that now do not take place because of the tax.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0260" block_type="txt"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e_ch5-fig-017">Figure 5-10</link> is a version of <link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e_ch5-fig-016">Figure 5-9</link> that leaves out rectangles <em>A</em> (the surplus shifted from consumers to the government) and <em>C</em> (the surplus shifted from producers to the government) and shows only the deadweight loss, here drawn as a triangle shaded yellow. The base of that triangle is equal to the tax wedge, <em>T;</em> the height of the triangle is equal to the reduction in the quantity transacted due to the tax, <em>Q<sub>E</sub> &#8722; Q<sub>T</sub>.</em> Clearly, the larger the tax wedge and the larger the reduction in the quantity transacted, the greater the inefficiency from the tax.</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-fig-017" block_type="figure" numbered="true" number="5-10" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<caption><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-fig-017"><phrase block_type="fig-label"><strong><phrase block_type="fig">FIGURE</phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_num">5-10</phrase></strong></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_title">The Deadweight Loss of a Tax</phrase></link></caption>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-img-0017" alt="image" src="asset/ch5/KrugESS4e_fig_5_10.jpg"/>
<caption>A tax leads to a deadweight loss because it creates inefficiency: some mutually beneficial transactions never take place because of the tax&#8212;namely, the transactions <em>Q<sub>E</sub></em>&#8211;<em>Q<sub>T</sub></em>. The yellow area here represents the value of the deadweight loss: it is the total surplus that would have been gained from the <em>Q<sub>E</sub></em>&#8211;<em>Q<sub>T</sub></em> transactions. If the tax had not discouraged transactions&#8212;had the number of transactions remained at <em>Q<sub>E</sub></em> because of either perfectly inelastic supply or perfectly inelastic demand&#8212;no deadweight loss would have been incurred.</caption>
</figure>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_162" block_type="page_start">162</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0261" block_type="txt">But also note an important, contrasting point: if the excise tax somehow <em>didn&#8217;t</em> reduce the quantity bought and sold in this market&#8212;if <em>Q<sub>T</sub></em> remained equal to <em>Q<sub>E</sub></em> after the tax was levied&#8212;the yellow triangle would disappear and the deadweight loss from the tax would be zero. This observation is simply the flip-side of the principle found earlier in the chapter: a tax causes inefficiency because it discourages mutually beneficial transactions between buyers and sellers. So if a tax does not discourage transactions, which would be true if either supply or demand were perfectly inelastic, it causes no deadweight loss. In this case, the tax simply shifts surplus straight from consumers and producers to the government.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0262" block_type="txt">Using a triangle to measure deadweight loss is a technique used in many economic applications. For example, triangles are used to measure the deadweight loss produced by types of taxes other than excise taxes. They are also used to measure the deadweight loss produced by monopoly, another kind of market distortion. And deadweight-loss triangles are often used to evaluate the benefits and costs of public policies besides taxation&#8212;such as whether to impose stricter safety standards on a product.</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-fig-018" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-img-0018" alt="image" src="asset/ch5/KrugESS4e_5UN06.jpg"/>
<caption>Society ultimately pays the administrative costs of taxes.</caption>
<asset_source>David Paul Morris/Bloomberg via Getty Images</asset_source>
</figure>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-exp3-22" block_type="mn3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p020a" block_type="mn-gl-def">The <strong>administrative costs</strong> of a tax are the resources used for its collection, for the method of payment, and for any attempts to evade the tax.</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0263" block_type="txt">In considering the total amount of inefficiency caused by a tax, we must also take into account something not shown in <link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e_ch5-fig-017">Figure 5-10</link>: the resources actually used by the government to collect the tax, and by taxpayers to pay it, over and above the amount of the tax. These lost resources are called the <strong>administrative costs</strong> of the tax. The most familiar administrative cost of the U.S. tax system is the time individuals spend filling out their income tax forms or the money they pay for tax return preparation services like those provided by H&#38;R Block and companies like it. (The latter is considered an inefficiency from the point of view of society because resources spent on return preparation could be used for other, non-tax-related purposes.)</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0264" block_type="txt">Included in the administrative costs that taxpayers incur are resources used to evade the tax, both legally and illegally. The costs of operating the Internal Revenue Service, the arm of the federal government tasked with collecting the federal income tax, are actually quite small in comparison to the administrative costs paid by taxpayers.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0265" block_type="txt">So the total inefficiency caused by a tax is the sum of its deadweight loss and its administrative costs. The general rule for economic policy is that, other things equal, a tax system should be designed to minimize the total inefficiency it imposes on society. In practice, other considerations also apply, but this principle nonetheless gives valuable guidance. Administrative costs are usually well known, more or less determined by the current technology of collecting taxes (for example, filing paper returns versus filing electronically). But how can we predict the size of the deadweight loss associated with a given tax? Not surprisingly, as in our analysis of the incidence of a tax, the price elasticities of supply and demand play crucial roles in making such a prediction.</p>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-sec2-013" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="5" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="162">
<section-metadata><section-title>Elasticities and the Deadweight Loss of a Tax</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0266" block_type="txt-ni">We know that the deadweight loss from an excise tax arises because it prevents some mutually beneficial transactions from occurring. In particular, the producer and consumer surplus that is forgone because of these missing transactions is equal to the size of the deadweight loss itself. This means that the larger the number of transactions that are prevented by the tax, the larger the deadweight loss.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0267" block_type="txt">This fact gives us an important clue in understanding the relationship between elasticity and the size of the deadweight loss from a tax. Recall that when demand or supply is elastic, the quantity demanded or the quantity supplied is relatively responsive to changes in the price. So a tax imposed on a good for which either demand or supply, or both, is elastic will cause a relatively large decrease in the quantity transacted and a relatively large deadweight loss. And when we say that demand or supply is inelastic, we mean that the quantity demanded or the quantity supplied is relatively unresponsive to changes in the price.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_163" block_type="page_start">163</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0268" block_type="txt">As a result, a tax imposed when demand or supply, or both, is inelastic will cause a relatively small decrease in the quantity transacted and a relatively small deadweight loss.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0269" block_type="txt">The four panels of <link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e_ch5-fig-019">Figure 5-11</link> illustrate the positive relationship between a good&#8217;s price elasticity of either demand or supply and the deadweight loss from taxing that good. Each panel represents the same amount of tax imposed but on a different good; the size of the deadweight loss is given by the area of the shaded triangle. In panel (a), the deadweight-loss triangle is large because demand for this good is relatively elastic&#8212;a large number of transactions fail to occur because of the tax. In panel (b), the same supply curve is drawn as in panel (a), but demand for this good is relatively inelastic; as a result, the triangle is small because only a small number of transactions are forgone. Likewise, panels (c) and (d) contain the same demand curve but different supply curves. In panel (c), an elastic supply curve gives rise to a large deadweight-loss triangle, but in panel (d) an inelastic supply curve gives rise to a small deadweight-loss triangle.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_164" block_type="page_start">164</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-fig-019" block_type="figure" numbered="true" number="5-11" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<caption><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-fig-019"><phrase block_type="fig-label"><strong><phrase block_type="fig">FIGURE</phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_num">5-11</phrase></strong></phrase> <phrase block_type="fig_title">Deadweight Loss and Elasticities</phrase></link></caption>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-img-0019" alt="image" src="asset/ch5/KrugESS4e_fig_5_11.jpg"/>
<caption>Demand is elastic in panel (a) and inelastic in panel (b), but the supply curves are the same. Supply is elastic in panel (c)&#160;and inelastic in panel (d), but the demand curves are the same. The deadweight losses are larger in panels (a) and (c) than in panels (b) and (d) because the greater the price elasticity of demand or supply, the greater the tax-induced fall in the quantity transacted. In contrast, the lower the price elasticity of demand or supply, the smaller the tax-induced fall in the quantity transacted and the smaller the deadweight loss.</caption>
</figure>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0270" block_type="txt">The implication of this result is clear: if you want to minimize the efficiency costs of taxation, you should choose to tax only those goods for which demand or supply, or both, is relatively inelastic. For such goods, a tax has little effect on behavior because behavior is relatively unresponsive to changes in the price. In the extreme case in which demand is perfectly inelastic (a vertical demand curve), the quantity demanded is unchanged by the imposition of the tax. As a result, the tax imposes no deadweight loss. Similarly, if supply is perfectly inelastic (a vertical supply curve), the quantity supplied is unchanged by the tax and there is also no deadweight loss.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0271" block_type="txt">So if the goal in choosing whom to tax is to minimize deadweight loss, then taxes should be imposed on goods and services that have the most inelastic response&#8212;that is, goods and services for which consumers or producers will change their behavior the least in response to the tax. (Unless they have a tendency to revolt, of course.) And this lesson carries a flip-side: using a tax to purposely decrease the amount of a harmful activity, such as underage drinking, will have the most impact when that activity is elastically demanded or supplied.</p>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-bx2-11" block_type="bx2-h">
<box-metadata><box-title><phrase block_type="title">ECONOMICS</phrase> <phrase block_type="number"><em>in Action</em></phrase></box-title></box-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0272" block_type="bx2-t"><strong>Taxing the Marlboro Man</strong></p>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-exp2-5" block_type="mn2">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0273" block_type="fg1-t"><image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-img-026" alt="image" src="asset/images/launchpad_logo_cmyk.jpg"/> &#124; interactive activity</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0274" block_type="bx2-first"><phrase block_type="dropcap">O</phrase>ne of the most important excise taxes in the United States is the tax on cigarettes. The federal government imposes a tax of &#36;1.01 a pack; state governments impose taxes that range from &#36;0.17 cents a pack in Missouri to &#36;4.35 a pack in New York; and many cities impose further taxes. In general, tax rates on cigarettes have increased over time, because more and more governments have seen them not just as a source of revenue but as a way to discourage smoking. But the rise in cigarette taxes has not been gradual. Usually, once a state government decides to raise cigarette taxes, it raises them a lot&#8212;which provides economists with useful data on what happens when there is a big tax increase.</p>
</box>
<table id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-tab-5" block_type="table" numbered="false" caption-placement="Top" data-href="asset/ch5/tables/table_5_5.html" data-target="_pop">
<table_caption><strong><phrase block_type="tbl">TABLE</phrase> <phrase block_type="tbl_num">5-4</phrase> <phrase block_type="tbl_title">Results of Increases in Cigarette Taxes</phrase></strong></table_caption>
<tbody>
<tr class="tbl-hdr-bg">
<td class="tbl-ljust"><strong>State</strong></td>
<td class="tbl-lborder"><strong>Year</strong></td>
<td class="tbl-lborder"><strong>Increase in tax<br/>(per pack)</strong></td>
<td class="tbl-lborder"><strong>New state tax<br/>(per pack)</strong></td>
<td class="tbl-lborder"><strong>Change in<br/>quantity<br/>transacted</strong></td>
<td class="tbl-lborder"><strong>Change in tax<br/>revenue</strong></td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-dark">
<td class="tbl-ljust">Mississippi</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">2009</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">&#36;0.50</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">&#36;0.68</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">&#8722;22.8&#37;</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">188.3&#37;</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tbl-ljust">Hawaii</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">2009</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">0.60</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">2.60</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">&#8722;1.3</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">&#8722;14.5</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-dark">
<td class="tbl-ljust">New Mexico</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">2010</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">0.75</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">1.66</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">&#8722;7.8</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">67.5</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tbl-ljust">Florida</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">2010</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">1.00</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">2.00</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">&#8722;27.8</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">193.2</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-dark">
<td class="tbl-ljust">Washington</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">2010</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">1.00</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">3.03</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">&#8722;20.5</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">17.0</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0276" block_type="tbn-not"><em>Data from:</em> Orzechowski &#38; Walker, Tax Burden on Tobacco. U.S. Alcohol and Tobacco Tax and Trade Bureau.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0277" block_type="txt"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-tab-4">Table 5-4</link> shows the results of big increases in cigarette taxes. In each case, sales fell, just as our analysis predicts. Although it&#8217;s theoretically possible for tax revenue to fall after such a large tax increase, in reality tax revenue rose in each case. That&#8217;s because cigarettes have a low price elasticity of demand.</p>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-bx6-1" block_type="sr2-h">
<box-metadata><box-title><phrase block_type="title">Check Your Understanding</phrase> <phrase block_type="number">5-5</phrase></box-title></box-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_165" block_type="page_start">165</p>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-cyuquestion-13" block_type="q_cyu" number="1">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p051" block_type="sr2-nl-first"><phrase block_type="qnum">1.</phrase> The accompanying table shows five consumers&#8217; willingness to pay for one can of diet soda each as well as five producers&#8217; costs of selling one can of diet soda each. Each consumer buys at most one can of soda; each producer sells at most one can of soda. The government asks your advice about the effects of an excise tax of &#36;0.40 per can of diet soda. Assume that there are no administrative costs from the tax.</p>
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-list-7" type="ordered" block_type="loweralpha">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p052" block_type="sr2-nl-lvl2">Without the excise tax, what is the equilibrium price and the equilibrium quantity of soda transacted?</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p053" block_type="sr2-nl-lvl2">The excise tax raises the price paid by consumers post-tax to &#36;0.60 and lowers the price received by producers post-tax to &#36;0.20. With the excise tax, what is the quantity of soda transacted?</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p054" block_type="sr2-nl-lvl2">Without the excise tax, how much individual consumer surplus does each of the consumers gain? How much with the tax? How much total consumer surplus is lost as a result of the tax?</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p055" block_type="sr2-nl-lvl2">Without the excise tax, how much individual producer surplus does each of the producers gain? How much with the tax? How much total producer surplus is lost as a result of the tax?</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p056" block_type="sr2-nl-lvl2">How much government revenue does the excise tax create?</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p057" block_type="sr2-nl-lvl2">What is the deadweight loss from the imposition of this excise tax?</p></li>
</list>
</question>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-cyuquestion-14" block_type="q_cyu" number="2">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0291" block_type="sr2-nl-last"><phrase block_type="qnum">2.</phrase> In each of the following cases, focus on the price elasticity of demand and use a diagram to illustrate the likely size&#8212;small or large&#8212;of the deadweight loss resulting from a tax. Explain your reasoning.</p>
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-list-8" type="ordered" block_type="loweralpha">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p058" block_type="sr2-nl-lvl2">Gasoline</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p059" block_type="sr2-nl-lvl2">Milk chocolate bars</p></li>
</list>
</question>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p060" block_type="sr2-nl-fn">Solutions appear at back of book.</p>
</box>
<box title="Quick Review" numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-bx5-12" block_type="sr-1-h">
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-list-6" type="unordered" block_type="redbullet">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p046" block_type="sr1-bl">An <strong>excise tax</strong> generates tax revenue equal to the <strong>tax rate</strong> times the number of units of the good or service transacted but reduces consumer and producer surplus.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p047" block_type="sr1-bl">The government tax revenue collected is less than the loss in total surplus because the tax creates inefficiency by discouraging some mutually beneficial transactions.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p048" block_type="sr1-bl">The difference between the tax revenue from an excise tax and the reduction in total surplus is the deadweight loss from the tax. The total amount of inefficiency resulting from a tax is equal to the deadweight loss plus the <strong>administrative costs</strong> of the tax.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p049" block_type="sr1-bl">The larger the number of transactions prevented by a tax, the larger the deadweight loss. As a result, taxes on goods with a greater price elasticity of supply or demand, or both, generate higher deadweight losses. There is no deadweight loss when the number of transactions is unchanged by the tax.</p></li>
</list>
</box>
<table id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-untab-6" block_type="un_table" data-href="asset/ch5/tables/untable_5_6.html" data-target="_pop">
<tbody>
<tr class="tbl-hdr-bg">
<td class="tbl-ljust"><strong>Consumer</strong></td>
<td class="tbl-lborder"><strong>Willingness<br/>to pay</strong></td>
<td class="tbl-lborder"><strong>Producer</strong></td>
<td class="tbl-lborder"><strong>Cost</strong></td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-dark">
<td class="tbl-ljust">Ana</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">&#36;0.70</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">Zhang</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">&#36;0.10</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tbl-ljust">Bernice</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">0.60</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">Yves</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">0.20</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-dark">
<td class="tbl-ljust">Chizuko</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">0.50</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">Xavier</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">0.30</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tbl-ljust">Dagmar</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">0.40</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">Walter</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">0.40</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-dark">
<td class="tbl-ljust">Ella</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">0.30</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">Vern</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">0.50</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-sec1-6a" block_type="solved_problem" title="" chapter="5" numbered="true" level="1" print_page="165">
<section-metadata><section-title>Solved Problem</section-title></section-metadata>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-bx7-13" block_type="sum-h">
<box-metadata><box-title><phrase block_type="gc1">SOLVED PROBLEM</phrase> <phrase block_type="gc2">Drive We Must</phrase></box-title></box-metadata>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-exp2-6" block_type="mn2">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0297" block_type="fg1-t"><strong><image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-img-027" alt="image" src="asset/images/launchpad_logo_cmyk.jpg"/></strong> for interactive tutorials with step-by-step guidance on how to solve problems</p>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0300" block_type="wio-txt-ni">In late 2013, U.S. gasoline prices started to drop from over &#36;4.00 a gallon to under &#36;2.50 by 2015. You&#8217;ve learned that when prices fall, quantity demanded rises. But, in the case of gasoline, it can take time for consumers to change their behavior. So despite the lower gas prices, in the short run, consumers didn&#8217;t run out to buy gas-guzzling sport-utility vehicles (SUVs) or change their driving behavior by taking long road trips. But with lower gas prices holding steady, consumer behavior did change in the long run. In 2015, the <em>New York Times</em> reported that consumers were buying fewer electric and hybrid cars while SUV sales were reaching record highs.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0301" block_type="wio-txt">Because consumers are slow to change their behavior in response to a change in gas prices, economists have to make different elasticity estimates of demand. Specifically, economists estimate the short-run elasticity for gasoline to be about 0.10, and the long-run elasticity of demand for gasoline to be about 0.30.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0302" block_type="wio-txt">As we&#8217;ve seen, gasoline prices decreased from about &#36;4.00 per gallon in 2013 to about &#36;2.50 per gallon where they have remained into 2016. Using the above long- and short-run elasticities, what is the predicted change in consumption of gasoline in the short and long runs? Draw and label a demand curve that reflects the long-run elasticity, assuming that at &#36;4.00 per gallon, motorists in the United States consume 10 million barrels per day of gasoline.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0303" block_type="sp-stp-txt"><phrase block_type="step"><phrase block_type="step-green">STEP</phrase> &#124; <phrase block_type="step-green">1</phrase></phrase> <phrase block_type="step-title"><strong>Find the percent change in the consumption of gasoline in the short run.</strong>
<phrase block_type="step-subtext">Review pages 138&#8211;140.</phrase></phrase></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0305" block_type="wio-txt-ni">It is the following:</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0306" block_type="wio-txt-ni">&#37; change in price = Change in price/Initial price &#215; 100.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0307" block_type="wio-txt-ni">Looking at Equation 5-3, we see that</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0308" block_type="wio-txt-ni">Price elasticity of demand = &#37; change in quantity demanded/&#37; change in price.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0309" block_type="wio-txt-ni">This equation can be rearranged as follows:</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0310" block_type="wio-txt-ni">&#37; change in quantity demanded = Price elasticity of demand &#215; &#37; change in price.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_166" block_type="page_start">166</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0311" block_type="wio-txt-ni">Using Equation 5-2, we can first find the percent change in price. Since price went from &#36;4.00 per gallon to &#36;2.50 per gallon, we divide the change in price, which is &#36;4.00 &#8722; &#36;2.50 = &#36;1.50, by the initial price, which is &#36;4.00. The percent change in price is therefore &#36;1.50/&#36;4.00 &#215; 100 = 37.5&#37;. By rearranging Equation 5-3 as above, we find that the percent change in quantity demanded is the short-run price elasticity of demand (0.10) multiplied by the percent change in price (37.5&#37;), so 0.10 &#215; 37.5&#37;&#160;=&#160;3.75&#37;.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0312" block_type="sp-stp-txt"><phrase block_type="step"><phrase block_type="step-green">STEP</phrase> &#124; <phrase block_type="step-green">2</phrase></phrase> <phrase block_type="step-title"><strong>Find the percent change in the consumption of gasoline in the long run.</strong></phrase></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0313" block_type="wio-txt-ni">Use the same method as above to find the long-run percent change, but substitute 0.30 (the long-run elasticity) for 0.10 (the short-run elasticity).</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0314" block_type="wio-txt">As we found above, the percent change in price was 37.5&#37;. We know that by rearranging Equation 5-3, we find that the percent change in quantity demanded is the long-run price elasticity of demand (0.30) multiplied by the percent change in price (37.5&#37;), so 0.30 &#215; 37.5&#37; = 11.25&#37;.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0315" block_type="sp-stp-txt"><phrase block_type="step"><phrase block_type="step-green">STEP</phrase> &#124; <phrase block_type="step-green">3</phrase></phrase> <phrase block_type="step-title"><strong>Draw and label a demand curve that reflects the long-run elasticity, assuming that at &#36;4.00 per gallon, motorists in the United States consume 10&#160;million barrels per day of gasoline.</strong>
<phrase block_type="step-subtext">Use the next two steps to devise this curve.</phrase></phrase></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0317" block_type="sp-stp-txt"><phrase block_type="step"><phrase block_type="step-green">STEP</phrase> &#124; <phrase block_type="step-green">4</phrase></phrase> <phrase block_type="step-title"><strong>Find the relevant numerical quantities for the horizontal axis by finding the amount demanded at &#36;2.50 per gallon.</strong>
<phrase block_type="step-subtext">Again, review pages 138&#8211;140.</phrase></phrase></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0319" block_type="wio-txt-ni">&#37; change in quantity demanded = Change in quantity demanded/Initial quantity demanded &#215; 100</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0320" block_type="wio-txt-ni">Rearranging, we find that the</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0321" block_type="wio-txt-ni">Change in quantity demanded = &#37; change in quantity demanded &#215; Initial quantity demanded/100.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0322" block_type="wio-txt-ni">From the question, we know that a price of &#36;4.00 corresponds to a quantity of 10&#160;million barrels per day. If the price were to fall to &#36;2.50 and the elasticity is 0.30, we know from Step 2 that the percent change in consumption is 11.25&#37;. Using the above rearranged equation, the change in quantity demanded = (11.25 &#215; 10 million barrels)/ 100 = 1.125 million barrels. Hence, the new quantity at a price of &#36;2.50 equals the initial quantity plus the change in quantity demanded: 10 million barrels + 1.125 million barrels = 11.125 million barrels.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0323" block_type="sp-stp-txt"><phrase block_type="step"><phrase block_type="step-green">STEP</phrase> &#124; <phrase block_type="step-green">5</phrase></phrase> <phrase block_type="step-title"><strong>Draw and label the demand curve.</strong>
<phrase block_type="step-subtext">Review pages 142&#8211;144.</phrase></phrase></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0325" block_type="wio-txt-ni">Carefully examine panel (b) of <link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e_ch5-fig-005">Figure 5-3</link> and consider how the figure would change if the elasticity were 0.30 rather than 0.5 as in the figure.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0326" block_type="wio-txt">An elasticity of demand of 0.30 is slightly more inelastic than an elasticity of demand of .50, so we would draw the curve to be slightly more vertical than that of the figure. That is, we would rotate the curve slightly to the right. As shown in the figure, point <em>A</em> now corresponds to a price of &#36;4.00 and a quantity of 10 million barrels per day, and point <em>B</em> now corresponds to a price of &#36;2.50 and a quantity of 11.125 million barrels, as calculated in Step 4.</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-fig-020" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-img-0020" alt="image" src="asset/ch5/KrugESS4e_5UN07.jpg"/>
</figure>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_167" block_type="page_start">167</p>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-sec1-007" block_type="cr-que-t" title="" chapter="5" numbered="true" level="1" print_page="167">
<section-metadata><section-title>SUMMARY</section-title></section-metadata>
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-list-9" type="ordered" block_type="numbered">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p061" block_type="sum-nl">Many economic questions depend on the size of consumer or producer responses to changes in prices or other variables. <em>Elasticity</em> is a general measure of responsiveness that can be used to answer such questions.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p062" block_type="sum-nl">The <strong>price elasticity of demand&#8212;</strong>the percent change in the quantity demanded divided by the percent change in the price (dropping the minus sign)&#8212;is a measure of the responsiveness of the quantity demanded to changes in the price. In practical calculations, it is usually best to use the <strong>midpoint method,</strong> which calculates percent changes in prices and quantities based on the average of starting and final values.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p063" block_type="sum-nl">The responsiveness of the quantity demanded to price can range from <strong>perfectly inelastic demand,</strong> where the quantity demanded is unaffected by the price, to <strong>perfectly elastic demand,</strong> where there is a unique price at which consumers will buy as much or as little as they are offered. When demand is perfectly inelastic, the demand curve is a vertical line; when it is perfectly elastic, the demand curve is a horizontal line.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p064" block_type="sum-nl">The price elasticity of demand is classified according to whether it is more or less than 1. If it is greater than 1, demand is <strong>elastic;</strong> if it is less than 1, demand is <strong>inelastic;</strong> if it is exactly 1, demand is <strong>unit-elastic</strong>. This classification determines how <strong>total revenue,</strong> the total value of sales, changes when the price changes. If demand is elastic, total revenue falls when the price increases and rises when the price decreases. If demand is inelastic, total revenue rises when the price increases and falls when the price decreases. If demand is unit-elastic, total revenue is unchanged by a change in price.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p065" block_type="sum-nl">The price elasticity of demand depends on whether there are close substitutes for the good in question, whether the good is a necessity or a luxury, the share of income spent on the good, and the length of time that has elapsed since the price change.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p066" block_type="sum-nl">The <strong>cross-price elasticity of demand</strong> measures the effect of a change in one good&#8217;s price on the quantity demanded of another good. The cross-price elasticity of demand can be positive, in which case the goods are substitutes, or negative, in which case they are complements.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p067" block_type="sum-nl">The <strong>income elasticity of demand</strong> is the percent change in the quantity demanded of a good when a consumer&#8217;s income changes divided by the percent change in income. The income elasticity of demand indicates how intensely the demand for a good responds to changes in income. It can be negative; in that case the good is an inferior good. Goods with positive income elasticities of demand are normal goods. If the income elasticity is greater than 1, a good is <strong>income-elastic;</strong> if it is positive and less than 1, the good is <strong>income-inelastic.</strong></p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p068" block_type="sum-nl">The <strong>price elasticity of supply</strong> is the percent change in the quantity of a good supplied divided by the percent change in the price. If the quantity supplied does not change at all, we have an instance of <strong>perfectly inelastic supply;</strong> the supply curve is a vertical line. If the quantity supplied is zero below some price but infinite above that price, we have an instance of <strong>perfectly elastic supply;</strong> the supply curve is a horizontal line.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p069" block_type="sum-nl">The price elasticity of supply depends on the availability of resources to expand production and on time. It is higher when inputs are available at relatively low cost and the longer the time elapsed since the price change.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p070" block_type="sum-nl">The tax revenue generated by a tax depends on the <strong>tax rate</strong> and on the number of units transacted with the tax. Excise taxes cause inefficiency in the form of deadweight loss because they discourage some mutually beneficial transactions. Taxes also impose <strong>administrative costs:</strong> resources used to collect the tax, to pay it (over and above the amount of the tax), and to evade it.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p071" block_type="sum-nl">An <strong>excise tax</strong> generates revenue for the government but lowers total surplus. The loss in total surplus exceeds the tax revenue, resulting in a deadweight loss to society. This deadweight loss is represented by a triangle, the area of which equals the value of the transactions discouraged by the tax. The greater the elasticity of demand or supply, or both, the larger the deadweight loss from a tax. If either demand or supply is perfectly inelastic, there is no deadweight loss from a tax.</p></li>
</list>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-exp2-7" block_type="mn2">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p08" block_type="fg1-t"><image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-img-002" alt="image" src="asset/images/launchpad_logo_cmyk.jpg"/> &#124; interactive activity</p>
</box>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-sec1-008" block_type="cr-kt-t" title="" chapter="5" numbered="true" level="1" print_page="167">
<section-metadata><section-title>KEY TERMS</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0339" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p015">Price elasticity of demand, p. 138</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0340" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p044">Midpoint method, p. 140</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0341" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p077">Perfectly inelastic demand, p. 143</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0342" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p063">Perfectly elastic demand, p. 143</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0343" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p084">Elastic demand, p. 143</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0344" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p084">Inelastic demand, p. 143</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0345" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p084">Unit-elastic demand, p. 143</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0346" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p090">Total revenue, p. 143</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0347" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0150">Cross-price elasticity of demand, p. 150</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0348" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0158">Income elasticity of demand, p. 151</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0349" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0166">Income-elastic demand, p. 151</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0350" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0166">Income-inelastic demand, p. 151</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0351" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0189">Price elasticity of supply, p. 153</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0352" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0196">Perfectly inelastic supply, p. 154</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0353" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0199">Perfectly elastic supply, p. 154</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0354" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0225">Excise tax, p. 157</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0355" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0237">Tax rate, p. 158</link></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0356" block_type="cr-kt-mcl"><link href="#krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0263">Administrative costs, p. 162</link></p>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-sec1-009" block_type="cr-que-t" title="" chapter="5" numbered="true" level="1" print_page="168">
<section-metadata><section-title>PROBLEMS</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_168" block_type="page_start">168</p>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-question-1" block_type="q_prob" number="1">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p072" block_type="cr-que-nl-first"><phrase block_type="qnum">1.</phrase> Do you think the price elasticity of demand for Ford SUVs will increase, decrease, or remain the same when each of the following events occurs? Explain your answer.</p>
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-list-10" type="ordered" block_type="loweralpha">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p073" block_type="cr-que-ans-first">Other car manufacturers, such as General Motors, decide to make and sell SUVs.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p074" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">SUVs produced in foreign countries are banned from the American market.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p075" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">Due to ad campaigns, Americans believe that SUVs are much safer than ordinary passenger cars.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p076" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">The time period over which you measure the elasticity lengthens. During that longer time, new models such as four-wheel-drive cargo vans appear.</p></li>
</list>
</question>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-question-2" block_type="q_prob" number="2">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0362" block_type="cr-que-nl-mid"><phrase block_type="qnum">2.</phrase> In the United States, 2013 was a bad year for growing wheat. And as wheat supply decreased, the price of wheat rose dramatically, leading to a lower quantity demanded (a movement along the demand curve). The accompanying table describes what happened to prices and the quantity of wheat demanded.</p>
<table id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-untab-7" block_type="un_table" data-href="asset/ch5/tables/untable_5_7.html" data-target="_pop">
<tbody>
<tr class="tbl-hdr-bg">
<td class="tbl-ljust"></td>
<td class="tbl-lborder"><strong>2012</strong></td>
<td class="tbl-lborder"><strong>2013</strong></td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tbl-ljust">Quantity demanded (bushels)</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">2.2 billion</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">2.0 billion</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-dark">
<td class="tbl-ljust">Average price (per bushel)</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">&#36;3.42</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">&#36;4.26</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-list-11" type="ordered" block_type="loweralpha">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p077" block_type="cr-que-ans-first">Using the midpoint method, calculate the price elasticity of demand for winter wheat.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p078" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">What is the total revenue for U.S. wheat farmers in 2012 and 2013?</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p079" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">Did the bad harvest increase or decrease the total revenue of U.S. wheat farmers? How could you have predicted this from your answer to part a?</p></li>
</list>
</question>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-question-3" block_type="q_prob" number="3">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0366" block_type="cr-que-nl-mid"><phrase block_type="qnum">3.</phrase> The accompanying table gives part of the supply schedule for personal computers in the United States.</p>
<table id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-untab-8" block_type="un_table" data-href="asset/ch5/tables/untable_5_8.html" data-target="_pop">
<tbody>
<tr class="tbl-hdr-bg">
<td class="tbl-rborder">Price of computer</td>
<td>Quantity of computers supplied</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tbl-rborder"><strong>&#36;1,100</strong></td>
<td><strong>12,000</strong></td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-dark">
<td class="tbl-rborder">900</td>
<td>8,000</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-list-13" type="ordered" block_type="loweralpha">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p083" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">Calculate the price elasticity of supply when the price increases from &#36;900 to &#36;1,100 using the midpoint method.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p084" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">Suppose firms produce 1,000 more computers at any given price due to improved technology. As price increases from &#36;900 to &#36;1,100, is the price elasticity of supply now greater than, less than, or the same as it was in part a?</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p085" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">Suppose a longer time period under consideration means that the quantity supplied at any given price is 20&#37; higher than the figures given in the table. As price increases from &#36;900 to &#36;1,100, is the price elasticity of supply now greater than, less than, or the same as it was in part a?</p></li>
</list>
</question>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-question-4" block_type="q_prob" number="4">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0373" block_type="cr-que-nl-mid"><phrase block_type="qnum">4.</phrase> What can you conclude about the price elasticity of demand in each of the following statements?</p>
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-list-14" type="ordered" block_type="loweralpha">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p086" block_type="cr-que-ans-first">&#8220;The pizza delivery business in this town is very competitive. I&#8217;d lose half my customers if I raised the price by as little as 10&#37;.&#8221;</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p087" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">&#8220;I owned both of the two Jerry Garcia autographed lithographs in existence. I sold one on eBay for a high price. But when I sold the second one, the price dropped by 80&#37;.&#8221;</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p088" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">&#8220;My economics professor has chosen to use the Krugman/Wells textbook for this class. I have no choice but to buy this book.&#8221;</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p089" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">&#8220;I always spend a total of exactly &#36;10 per week on coffee.&#8221;</p></li>
</list>
</question>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-question-5" block_type="q_prob" number="5">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0378" block_type="cr-que-nl-mid"><phrase block_type="qnum">5.</phrase> The accompanying table shows the price and yearly quantity sold of souvenir T-shirts in the town of Crystal Lake according to the average income of the tourists visiting.</p>
<table id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-untab-9" block_type="un_table" data-href="asset/ch5/tables/untable_5_9.html" data-target="_pop">
<tbody>
<tr class="tbl-hdr-bg">
<td class="tbl-rborder"><strong>Price of T-shirt</strong></td>
<td class="tbl-rborder"><strong>Quantity of T-shirts<br/>demanded when<br/>average tourist<br/>income is &#36;20,000</strong></td>
<td><strong>Quantity of T-shirts<br/>demanded when<br/>average tourist<br/>income is &#36;30,000</strong></td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tbl-rborder">&#36;4</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder">3,000</td>
<td>5,000</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-dark">
<td class="tbl-rborder">5</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder">2,400</td>
<td>4,200</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tbl-rborder">6</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder">1,600</td>
<td>3,000</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-dark">
<td class="tbl-rborder">7</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder">800</td>
<td>1,800</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-list-15" type="ordered" block_type="loweralpha">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p090" block_type="cr-que-ans-first">Using the midpoint method, calculate the price elasticity of demand when the price of a T-shirt rises from &#36;5 to &#36;6 and the average tourist income is &#36;20,000. Also calculate it when the average tourist income is &#36;30,000.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p091" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">Using the midpoint method, calculate the income elasticity of demand when the price of a T-shirt is &#36;4 and the average tourist income increases from &#36;20,000 to &#36;30,000. Also calculate it when the price&#160;is &#36;7.</p></li>
</list>
</question>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-question-6" block_type="q_prob" number="6">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0381" block_type="cr-que-nl-mid"><phrase block_type="qnum">6.</phrase> A recent study determined the following elasticities for Volkswagen Beetles:</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0382" block_type="cr-que-txt">Price elasticity of demand = 2</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0382" block_type="cr-que-txt">Income elasticity of demand = 1.5</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0383" block_type="cr-que-nl-mid">The supply of Beetles is elastic. Based on this information, are the following statements true or false? Explain your reasoning.</p>
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-list-16" type="ordered" block_type="loweralpha">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p092" block_type="cr-que-ans-first">A 10&#37; increase in the price of a Beetle will reduce the quantity demanded by 20&#37;.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p093" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">An increase in consumer income will increase the price and quantity of Beetles sold.</p></li>
</list>
</question>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-question-7" block_type="q_prob" number="7">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0386" block_type="cr-que-nl-mid"><phrase block_type="qnum">7.</phrase> In each of the following cases, do you think the price elasticity of supply is (i) perfectly elastic; (ii) perfectly inelastic; (iii) elastic, but not perfectly elastic; or (iv) inelastic, but not perfectly inelastic? Explain using a diagram.</p>
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-list-17" type="ordered" block_type="loweralpha">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p094" block_type="cr-que-ans-first">An increase in demand this summer for luxury cruises leads to a huge jump in the sales price of a cabin on the <em>Queen Mary 2.</em></p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p095" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">The price of a kilowatt of electricity is the same during periods of high electricity demand as during periods of low electricity demand.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_169" block_type="page_start">169</p>
</li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p096" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">Fewer people want to fly during February than during any other month. The airlines cancel about 10&#37; of their flights as ticket prices fall about 20&#37; during this month.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p097" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">Owners of vacation homes in Maine rent them out during the summer. Due to the soft economy this year, a 30&#37; decline in the price of a vacation rental leads more than half of homeowners to occupy their vacation homes themselves during the summer.</p></li>
</list>
</question>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-question-8" block_type="q_prob" number="8">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0391" block_type="cr-que-nl-mid"><phrase block_type="qnum">8.</phrase> Use an elasticity concept to explain each of the following observations.</p>
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-list-18" type="ordered" block_type="loweralpha">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p098" block_type="cr-que-ans-first">During economic booms, the number of new personal care businesses, such as gyms and tanning salons, is proportionately greater than the number of other new businesses, such as grocery stores.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p099" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">Cement is the primary building material in Mexico. After new technology makes cement cheaper to produce, the supply curve for the Mexican cement industry becomes relatively flatter.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p100" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">Some goods that were once considered luxuries, like a telephone, are now considered virtual necessities. As a result, the demand curve for telephone services has become steeper over time.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p101" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">Consumers in a less developed country like Guatemala spend proportionately more of their income on equipment for producing things at home, like sewing machines, than consumers in a more developed country like Canada.</p></li>
</list>
</question>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-question-9" block_type="q_prob" number="9">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0396" block_type="cr-que-nl-mid"><phrase block_type="qnum">9.</phrase> There is a debate about whether sterile hypodermic needles should be passed out free of charge in cities with high drug use. Proponents argue that doing so will reduce the incidence of diseases, such as HIV/AIDS, that are often spread by needle sharing among drug users. Opponents believe that doing so will encourage more drug use by reducing the risks of this behavior. As an economist asked to assess the policy, you must know the following: (i) how responsive the spread of diseases like HIV/AIDS is to the price of sterile needles and (ii) how responsive drug use is to the price of sterile needles. Assuming that you know these two things, use the concepts of price elasticity of demand for sterile needles and the cross-price elasticity between drugs and sterile needles to answer the following questions.</p>
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-list-19" type="ordered" block_type="loweralpha">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p102" block_type="cr-que-ans-first">In what circumstances do you believe this is a beneficial policy?</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p103" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">In what circumstances do you believe this is a bad policy?</p></li>
</list>
</question>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-question-10" block_type="q_prob" number="10">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0399" block_type="cr-que-nl-mid"><phrase block_type="qnum">10.</phrase> Worldwide, the average coffee grower has increased the amount of acreage under cultivation over the past few years. The result has been that the average coffee plantation produces significantly more coffee than it did 10 to 20 years ago. Unfortunately for the growers, however, this has also been a period in which their total revenues have plunged. In terms of an elasticity, what must be true for these events to have occurred? Illustrate these events with a diagram, indicating the quantity effect and the price effect that gave rise to these events.</p>
</question>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-question-11" block_type="q_prob" number="11">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0400" block_type="cr-que-nl-mid"><phrase block_type="qnum">11.</phrase> According to data from the U.S. Department of Energy, sales of the fuel-efficient Toyota Prius hybrid fell from 158,574 vehicles sold in 2008 to 139,682 in 2009. Over the same period, according to data from the U.S. Energy Information Administration, the average price of regular gasoline fell from &#36;3.27 to &#36;2.35 per gallon. Using the midpoint method, calculate the cross-price elasticity of demand between Toyota Prii (the official plural of &#8220;Prius&#8221; is &#8220;Prii&#8221;) and regular gasoline. According to your estimate of the cross-price elasticity, are the two goods complements or substitutes? Does your answer make sense?</p>
</question>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-question-12" block_type="q_prob" number="12">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0401" block_type="cr-que-nl-first"><phrase block_type="qnum">12.</phrase> The United States imposes an excise tax on the sale of domestic airline tickets. Let&#8217;s assume that in 2013 the total excise tax was &#36;6.10 per airline ticket (consisting of the &#36;3.60 flight segment tax plus the &#36;2.50 September 11 fee). According to data from the Bureau of Transportation Statistics, in 2013, 643 million passengers traveled on domestic airline trips at an average price of &#36;380.00 per trip. The following table shows the supply and demand schedules for airline trips. The quantity demanded at the average price of &#36;380.00 is actual data; the rest is hypothetical.</p>
<table id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-untab-10" block_type="un_table" data-href="asset/ch5/tables/untable_5_10.html" data-target="_pop">
<tbody>
<tr class="tbl-hdr-bg">
<td class="tbl-rborder"><strong>Price of trip</strong></td>
<td class="tbl-rborder"><strong>Quantity of trips demanded (millions)</strong></td>
<td><strong>Quantity of trips supplied (millions)</strong></td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tbl-rborder">&#36;380.02</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder">642</td>
<td>699</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-dark">
<td class="tbl-rborder">380.00</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder">643</td>
<td>698</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tbl-rborder">378.00</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder">693</td>
<td>693</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-dark">
<td class="tbl-rborder">373.90</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder">793</td>
<td>643</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tbl-rborder">373.82</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder">913</td>
<td>642</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-list-20" type="ordered" block_type="loweralpha">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p104" block_type="cr-que-ans-first">What is the government tax revenue in 2013 from the excise tax?</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p105" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">On January 1, 2014, the total excise tax increased to &#36;6.20 per ticket. What is the quantity of tickets transacted now? What is the average ticket price now? What is the 2014 government tax revenue?</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p106" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">Does this increase in the excise tax increase or decrease government tax revenue?</p></li>
</list>
</question>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-question-13" block_type="q_prob" number="13">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0405" block_type="cr-que-nl-mid"><phrase block_type="qnum">13.</phrase> In 1990, the United States began to levy a tax on sales of luxury cars. For simplicity, assume that the tax was an excise tax of &#36;6,000 per car. The accompanying figure shows hypothetical demand and supply curves for luxury cars.</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-fig-021" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-img-0021" alt="image" src="asset/ch5/KrugESS4e_5UN08.jpg"/>
</figure>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_170" block_type="page_start">170</p>
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-list-21" type="ordered" block_type="loweralpha">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p107" block_type="cr-que-ans-first">Under the tax, what is the price paid by consumers? What is the price received by producers? What is the government tax revenue from the excise tax?</p></li>
</list>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p108" block_type="cr-que-nl-mid">Over time, the tax on luxury automobiles was slowly phased out (and completely eliminated in 2002). Suppose that the excise tax falls from &#36;6,000 per car to &#36;4,500 per car.</p>
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-list-21a" type="ordered" block_type="loweralpha" start="2">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p109" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">After the reduction in the excise tax from &#36;6,000 to &#36;4,500 per car, what is the price paid by consumers? What is the price received by producers? What is tax revenue now?</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p110" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">Compare the tax revenue created by the taxes in parts a and b. What accounts for the change in tax revenue from the reduction in the excise tax?</p></li>
</list>
</question>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-question-14" block_type="q_prob" number="14">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0410" block_type="cr-que-nl-mid"><phrase block_type="qnum">14.</phrase> The following table lists the cross-price elasticities of demand for several goods, where the percent quantity change is measured for the first good of the pair, and the percent price change is measured for the second good.</p>
<table id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-untab-11" block_type="un_table" data-href="asset/ch5/tables/untable_5_11.html" data-target="_pop">
<tbody>
<tr class="tbl-hdr-bg">
<td class="tbl-rborder"><strong>Good</strong></td>
<td><strong>Cross-price elasticities of demand</strong></td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tbl-ljust">Air-conditioning units and kilowatts of electricity</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">&#8722;0.34</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-dark">
<td class="tbl-ljust">Coke and Pepsi</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">&#8722;0.63</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tbl-ljust">High-fuel-consuming sport-utility vehicles (SUVs) and gasoline</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">&#8722;0.28</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-dark">
<td class="tbl-ljust">McDonald&#8217;s burgers and Burger King burgers</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">&#8722;0.82</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tbl-ljust">Butter and margarine</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">&#8722;1.54</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-list-22" type="ordered" block_type="loweralpha">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p111" block_type="cr-que-ans-first">Explain the sign of each of the cross-price elasticities. What does it imply about the relationship between the two goods in question?</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p112" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">Compare the absolute values of the cross-price elasticities and explain their magnitudes. For example, why is the cross-price elasticity of McDonald&#8217;s burgers and Burger King burgers less than the cross-price elasticity of butter and margarine?</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p113" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">Use the information in the table to calculate how a 5&#37; increase in the price of Pepsi affects the quantity of Coke demanded.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p114" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">Use the information in the table to calculate how a 10&#37; decrease in the price of gasoline affects the quantity of SUVs demanded.</p></li>
</list>
</question>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-question-15" block_type="q_prob" number="15">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0415" block_type="cr-que-nl-mid"><phrase block_type="qnum">15.</phrase> A recent report by the U.S. Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC), published in the CDC&#8217;s <em>Morbidity and Mortality Weekly Report,</em> studied the effect of an increase in the price of beer on the incidence of new cases of sexually transmitted disease in young adults. In particular, the researchers analyzed the responsiveness of gonorrhea cases to a tax-induced increase in the price of beer. The report concluded that &#8220;the . . . analysis suggested that a beer tax increase of &#36;0.20 per six-pack could reduce overall gonorrhea rates by 8.9&#37;.&#8221; Assume that a sixpack costs &#36;5.90 before the price increase. Use the midpoint method to determine the percent increase in the price of a six-pack, and then calculate the cross-price elasticity of demand between beer and incidence of gonorrhea. According to your estimate of this cross-price elasticity of demand, are beer and gonorrhea complements or substitutes?</p>
</question>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-question-16" block_type="q_prob" number="16">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0416" block_type="cr-que-nl-mid"><phrase block_type="qnum">16.</phrase> All states impose excise taxes on gasoline. According to data from the Federal Highway Administration, the state of California imposes an excise tax of &#36;0.40 per gallon of gasoline. In 2013, gasoline sales in California totaled 18.4&#160;billion gallons. What was California&#8217;s tax revenue from the gasoline excise tax? If California doubled the excise tax, would tax revenue double? Why or why not?</p>
</question>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-question-17" block_type="q_prob" number="17">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0417" block_type="cr-que-nl-mid"><phrase block_type="qnum">17.</phrase> The U.S. government would like to help the American auto industry compete against foreign automakers that sell trucks in the United States. It can do this by imposing an excise tax on each foreign truck sold in the United States. The hypothetical pre-tax demand and supply schedules for imported trucks are given in this table.</p>
<table id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-untab-12" block_type="un_table" data-href="asset/ch5/tables/untable_5_12.html" data-target="_pop">
<tbody>
<tr class="tbl-hdr-bg">
<td rowspan="2"><strong>Price of<br/>imported truck</strong></td>
<td class="tbl-bborder" colspan="2"><strong>Quantity of imported trucks<br/>(thousands)</strong></td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-hdr-bg">
<td></td>
<td><strong>Quantity demanded</strong></td>
<td><strong>Quantity supplied</strong></td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tbl-rborder">&#36;32,000</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder">100</td>
<td>400</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-dark">
<td class="tbl-rborder">31,000</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder">200</td>
<td>350</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tbl-rborder">30,000</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder">300</td>
<td>300</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-dark">
<td class="tbl-rborder">29,000</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder">400</td>
<td>250</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tbl-rborder">28,000</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder">500</td>
<td>200</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-dark">
<td class="tbl-rborder">27,000</td>
<td class="tbl-rborder">600</td>
<td>150</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-list-23" type="ordered" block_type="loweralpha">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p115" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">In the absence of government interference, what is the equilibrium price of an imported truck? The equilibrium quantity? Illustrate with a diagram.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p116" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">Assume that the government imposes an excise tax of &#36;3,000 per imported truck. Illustrate the effect of this excise tax in your diagram from part a. How many imported trucks are now purchased and at what price? How much does the foreign automaker receive per truck?</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p117" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">Calculate the government revenue raised by the excise tax in part b. Illustrate it on your diagram.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p118" block_type="cr-que-ans-mid">How does the excise tax on imported trucks benefit American automakers? Whom does it hurt? How does inefficiency arise from this government policy?</p></li>
</list>
</question>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-sec1-010" block_type="sum-h" title="" chapter="5" numbered="true" level="1" print_page="171">
<section-metadata><section-title>WORK IT OUT</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_171" block_type="page_start">171</p>
<box numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-exp2-8" block_type="mn2">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0422" block_type="fg1-t"><image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-img-028" alt="image" src="asset/images/launchpad_logo_cmyk.jpg"/> &#124; interactive activity</p>
</box>
<question id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-question-18" block_type="q_prob" number="18">
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0423" block_type="cr-wio-nl-first"><phrase block_type="qnum">18.</phrase> <link href="http://Nile.com">Nile.com</link>, the online bookseller, wants to increase its total revenue. One strategy is to offer a 10&#37; discount on every book it sells. <link href="http://">Nile.com</link> knows that its customers can be divided into two distinct groups according to their likely responses to the discount. The table shows how the two groups respond to the discount.</p>
<table id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-untab-13" block_type="un_table" data-href="asset/ch5/tables/untable_5_13.html" data-target="_pop">
<tbody>
<tr class="tbl-hdr-bg">
<td class="tbl-rborder"></td>
<td class="tbl-rborder"><strong>Group A<br/>(sales per week)</strong></td>
<td><strong>Group B<br/>(sales per week)</strong></td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-light">
<td class="tbl-ljust">Volume of sales before the 10&#37; discount</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">1.55 million</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">1.50 million</td>
</tr>
<tr class="tbl-td-dark">
<td class="tbl-ljust">Volume of sales after the 10&#37; discount</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">1.65 million</td>
<td class="tbl-lborder">1.70 million</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-list-24" type="ordered" block_type="loweralpha">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p119" block_type="cr-wio-ans-first">Using the midpoint method, calculate the price elasticities of demand for group A and group B.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p120" block_type="cr-wio-ans-mid">Explain how the discount will affect total revenue from each group.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p121" block_type="cr-wio-ans-mid">Suppose <link href="http://Nile.com">Nile.com</link> knows which group each customer belongs to when he or she logs on and can choose whether or not to offer the 10&#37; discount. If <link href="http://Nile.com">Nile.com</link> wants to increase its total revenue, should discounts be offered to group A or to group B, to neither group, or to both groups?</p></li>
</list>
</question>
</section>
<section id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-sec1-7a" block_type="business_case" title="" chapter="5" numbered="true" level="1" print_page="172">
<section-metadata><section-title>Business Case</section-title></section-metadata>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-bx5-3" block_type="bcbx5-h">
<box-metadata><box-title><phrase block_type="bc1">BUSINESS</phrase> <phrase block_type="bc2">CASE</phrase></box-title></box-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_172" block_type="page_start">172</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0427" block_type="bx5-t"><strong>An Uber Way to Get a Ride</strong></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0430" block_type="bx5-txt-ni"><phrase block_type="dropcap">I</phrase>n a densely populated city like New York City, finding a taxi is a relatively easy task on most days&#8212;stand on a corner, put out your arm and, usually, before long an available cab stops to pick you up. And even before you step into the car you will know approximately how much it will cost to get to your destination, because taxi meter rates are set by city regulators and posted for riders.</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-fig-021" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="right" width="medium" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-img-0021" alt="image" src="asset/ch5/KrugESS4e_5UN09.jpg"/>
<asset_source>&#169; Mark Avery/ZUMA Wire/Alamy</asset_source>
</figure>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0431" block_type="bx5-txt">But at times it is not so easy to find a taxi&#8212;on rainy days, during rush hour, and at crowded locations where many people are looking for a taxi at the same time. At such times, you could wait a very long while before finding an available cab. As you wait, you will probably notice empty taxis passing you by&#8212;drivers who have quit working for the day and are headed home or back to the garage. There will be drivers who might stop, but then won&#8217;t pick you up because they find your destination inconvenient. Moreover, there are times when it is simply impossible to hail a taxi&#8212;for example, during a snowstorm or on New Year&#8217;s Eve when the demand for taxis far exceeds the supply.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0432" block_type="bx5-txt">In 2009 two young entrepreneurs, Garrett Camp and Travis Kalanick, founded Uber, a company that they believe offers a better way to get a ride. Using a smartphone app, Uber serves as a clearinghouse connecting people who want a ride to drivers with cars who are registered with Uber. Confirm your location using the Uber app and you&#8217;ll be shown the available cars in your vicinity. Tap &#8220;book&#8221; and you receive a text saying your car&#8212;typically a spotless Lincoln Town Car&#8212;is on its way. At the end of your trip, fare plus tip are automatically deducted from your credit card. As of 2014 Uber operates in 60 countries and more than 300&#160;cities and booked &#36;10 billion in rides in 2015.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0433" block_type="bx5-txt">Given that Uber provides personalized service and better quality cars, their fares are somewhat higher than regular taxi fares <em>during normal driving hours</em>&#8212;a situation that customers seem happy with. However, the qualification <em>during normal driving hours</em> is an important one because at other times Uber&#8217;s rates fluctuate. When a lot of people are looking for a car&#8212;such as during a snowstorm or on New Year&#8217;s Eve&#8212;Uber uses what it calls <em>surge pricing,</em> setting the rate higher until everyone who wants a car at the going price can get one. So during a recent New York snowstorm, rides cost up to 8.25 times the standard price. Enraged, some of Uber&#8217;s customers have accused them of price gouging.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0434" block_type="bx5-txt">But according to Kalanick, the algorithm that Uber uses to determine the surge price is set to leave as few people as possible without a ride, and he&#8217;s just doing what is necessary to keep customers happy. As he explains, &#8220;We do not own cars nor do we employ drivers. Higher prices are required in order to get cars on the road and keep them on the road during the busiest times.&#8221; This explanation was confirmed by one Uber driver who said, &#8220;If I don&#8217;t have anything to do and see a surge price, I get out there.&#8221;</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0435" block_type="bx5-nl-h"><strong>QUESTIONS FOR THOUGHT</strong></p>
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-list-24c" type="ordered" block_type="numbered">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p122" block_type="bx5-nl">Before Uber, how were prices set in the market for rides in New York City? Was it a competitive market?</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p123" block_type="bx5-nl">What accounts for the fact that during good weather there are typically enough taxis for everyone who wants one, but during snowstorms there typically aren&#8217;t enough?</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p124" block_type="bx5-nl">How does Uber&#8217;s surge pricing solve the problem described in the previous question? Assess Kalanick&#8217;s claim that the price is set to leave as few people possible without a ride.</p></li>
</list>
</box>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_173" block_type="page_start">173</p>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-bx5-4" block_type="bcbx5-h">
<box-metadata><box-title><phrase block_type="bc1">BUSINESS</phrase> <phrase block_type="bc2">CASE</phrase></box-title></box-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0440" block_type="bx5-t"><strong>Medallion Financial: Cruising Right Along</strong></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0443" block_type="bx5-txt-ni"><phrase block_type="dropcap">B</phrase>ack in 1937, before New York City froze its number of taxi medallions, Andrew Murstein&#8217;s immigrant grandfather bought his first one for &#36;10. Over time, the grandfather accumulated 500 medallions, which he rented to other drivers. Those 500 taxi medallions became the foundation for Medallion Financial: the company that would eventually pass to Andrew, its current president.</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-fig-022" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="right" width="medium" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-img-0022" alt="image" src="asset/ch5/KrugESS4e_5UN10.jpg"/>
<asset_source>The Photo Works</asset_source>
</figure>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0445" block_type="bx5-txt">With a market value of &#36;385 million in late 2013, Medallion Financial shifted its major line of business from renting out medallions to financing the purchase of new ones, lending money to those who want to buy a medallion but don&#8217;t have the sizable amount of cash required to do so. Murstein believes that he is helping people who, like his Polish immigrant grandfather, want to buy a piece of the American dream.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0446" block_type="bx5-txt">Andrew Murstein carefully watches the value of a New York City taxi medallion: the more one costs, the more demand there is for loans from Medallion Financial, and the more interest the company makes on the loan. A loan from Medallion Financial is secured by the value of the medallion itself. If the borrower is unable to repay the loan, Medallion Financial takes possession of his or her medallion and resells it to offset the cost of the loan default. Over the past two decades, the value of a medallion rose 720&#37;, compared to 500&#37; for an index of stocks.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0447" block_type="bx5-txt">But medallion prices can fluctuate, threatening profits. In a very strong economy, such as in 1999 and 2001, the price of New York taxi medallions fell as drivers found jobs in other sectors. When the New York economy tanked in the aftermath of 9/11, the price of a medallion fell to &#36;180,000, its lowest level in 12&#160;years. In 2004, medallion owners were concerned about the impending sale by the New York City Taxi and Limousine Commission of an additional 900&#160;medallions. As Peter Hernandez, a worried New York cabdriver who financed his medallion with a loan from Medallion Financial, said at the time: &#8220;If they pump new taxis into the industry, it devalues my medallion. It devalues my daily income, too.&#8221;</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0448" block_type="bx5-txt"><strong>QUERY:</strong> Edit not clear.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0448" block_type="bx5-txt">Yet Murstein has always been optimistic that medallions would hold their value. He believed that a 25&#37; fare increase would offset potential losses in their value caused by the sale of new medallions. In addition, more medallions would mean more loans for his company.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0449" block_type="bx5-txt">In 2013, Murstein&#8217;s optimism was justified. Because of the financial crisis of 2007&#8211;2009, many New York companies cut back the limousine services they ordinarily provided to their employees, forcing them to take taxis instead. As a result, the price of a medallion nearly doubled, from &#36;550,000 in 2008 to more than a million dollars in 2013.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0450" block_type="bx5-txt">But two years later, in 2015, medallion owners watched prices fall to under &#36;700,000. This time, increased competition from Uber and companies like it was to blame. That same year, the market value of Medallion Financial fell by 50&#37;, to &#36;190 million.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0451" block_type="bx5-nl-h"><strong>QUESTIONS FOR THOUGHT</strong></p>
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-list-24b" type="ordered" block_type="numbered">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p125" block_type="bx5-nl">How does Medallion Financial benefit from the restriction on the number of New York taxi medallions?</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p126" block_type="bx5-nl">What will be the effect on Medallion Financial if New York companies resume widespread use of limousine services for their employees? What is the economic motivation that prompts companies to offer this perk to their employees? (Note that it is very difficult and expensive to own a personal car in New York City.)</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p127" block_type="bx5-nl">Predict the effect on Medallion Financial&#8217;s business if New York City eliminates restrictions on the number of taxis. That is, if the quota is removed.</p></li>
</list>
</box>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-bx5-5" block_type="bcbx5-h">
<box-metadata><box-title><phrase block_type="bc1">BUSINESS</phrase> <phrase block_type="bc2">CASE</phrase></box-title></box-metadata>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e_page_174" block_type="page_start">174</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0456" block_type="bx5-t"><strong>The Airline Industry: Fly Less, Charge More</strong></p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0460" block_type="bx5-txt-ni"><phrase block_type="dropcap">T</phrase>he airline industry is forecast to earn nearly &#36;25 billion in profits in 2015, up from nearly &#36;12 billion in 2013. But in 2008, the industry was teetering on the edge of disaster. According to the International Air Transport Association, the industry lost &#36;11 billion that year. However, by 2009, despite the fact that the economy was still extremely weak and airline traffic was still well below normal, profitability began to rebound. And by 2010, despite continued economic weakness, the airline industry had definitely recovered, achieving an &#36;8.9 billion profit that year.</p>
<figure id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-fig-023" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="right" width="medium" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-img-0023" alt="image" src="asset/ch5/KrugESS4e_5UN11.jpg"/>
<asset_source>June Lloyd/Getty Images</asset_source>
</figure>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0461" block_type="bx5-txt">How did the airline industry achieve such a dramatic turnaround? Simple: fly less and charge more. In 2011, fares were 8&#37; higher than they had been the previous year and 17&#37; higher compared to 2009. Flights were more crowded than they had been in decades, with fewer than one in five seats empty on domestic flights. And that trend continues today.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0462" block_type="bx5-txt">In addition to cutting back on the number of flights&#8212;particularly money-losing ones&#8212;airlines began to vary ticket prices based on time of departure and when the ticket was purchased. For example, the cheapest day to fly is Wednesday, with Friday and Saturday the most expensive days to travel. The first flight of the morning (the one that requires you to get up at 4 a.m.) is cheaper than later flights. And the cheapest time to buy a ticket is Tuesday at 3 p.m. Eastern Standard Time, with tickets purchased over the weekend carrying the highest prices.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0463" block_type="bx5-txt">It doesn&#8217;t stop there. As every beleaguered traveler knows, airlines have tacked on a wide variety of new fees and increased old ones&#8212;fees for food, blankets, baggage, even the right to board first or choose your seat in advance. Airlines have also become more inventive at imposing fees that are hard for travelers to track in advance&#8212;such as a &#8220;holiday surcharge&#8221;&#8212;while claiming that fares have not increased for the holiday. In 2007, airlines collected negligible amounts in fees, but by 2009 the amount had risen to &#36;3.8 billion. By 2013 that number had exploded to &#36;27 billion, a 611&#37; increase from 2009.</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0464" block_type="bx5-txt">But industry analysts question whether airlines can manage to maintain their currently high levels of profitability. In the past, as travel demand picked up, airlines increased capacity&#8212;added seats&#8212;too quickly, leading to falling airfares. &#8220;The wild card is always capacity discipline,&#8221; says an airline industry researcher. &#8220;All it takes is one carrier to begin to add capacity aggressively, and then we follow and we undo all the good work that&#8217;s been done.&#8221;</p>
<p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p0465" block_type="bx5-nl-h"><strong>QUESTIONS FOR THOUGHT</strong></p>
<list id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-list-24a" type="ordered" block_type="numbered">
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p128" block_type="bx5-nl">How would you describe the price elasticity of demand for airline flights given the information in this case? Explain.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p129" block_type="bx5-nl">Using the concept of elasticity, explain why airlines would create such great variations in the price of a ticket depending on when it is purchased and the day and time the flight departs. Assume that some people are willing to spend time shopping for deals as well as fly at inconvenient times, but others are not.</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p130" block_type="bx5-nl">Using the concept of elasticity, explain why airlines have imposed fees on things such as checked bags. Why might they try to hide or disguise fees?</p></li>
<li><p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch5-p131" block_type="bx5-nl">Use an elasticity concept to explain under what conditions the airline industry will be able to maintain its high profitability in the future. Explain.</p></li>
</list>
</box>
</section>
</chapter>
