Questions
is there a book to model after? May answer much of below.
Left side main text, right margin?
Pop figures? including unnumbered? tables?
Expand wider material into margin? - figures, tables
Style Figures and their captions as in PDF? Alternative is to make them all "figure over caption", centered in text area, which most already are. (see page 19, figure 1.9 - left-side figure)(see page 23, figure 1.12 - left-side caption)
Some side figures do exist
Some sidebar text also exists. These could be made central or kept in side margin.
How to style links? table/figure, key terms, section
Key Terms section not to be included or is it made into interactive quiz?
Key terms per chapter and not book?
Problems-sanswers - will these be interactive?
Will there be footnotes? I don't see any in this chapter.
Look at styling on various features for acceptability.

Need to establish page layout: column widths, page number boxes, etc.

Introduction
    Learning Objectives - caps blue sans
        blue square marker list, black list sans
    Chapter Overview - caps blue sans
        title blue sans caps
        body black sans
    TOC
        all blue, sans-serif
        
Subsection
    Title blue, sans: number & title
    Body black serif fill-justified
        First word bold
        links blue
        first para no indent, rest indented
    B-heads
        margin above below
        blue, bold
        
Practice Problems
    Header blue background, white text
    Review Your Knowledge
    Apply Your Knowledge
    XML Notes - Not numbered as in PDF but given as questions. Question 1.1 needs to be 1.01, but can we rely on question numbering, which is done by DF?

    
Summary section
    Different background image, but still blue splotch
    ul with blue circle markers outside - left margin inset from headers
        li left justified
        
Key Terms section
    Not included, right?
    
Chapter Exercises section
    Review Your Knowledge
    Apply Your Knowledge
    some small, italic subtitles along with standard, blue subtitles
 
        
Tables
    Implemented with figures, so ignore below
        header sans
        body serif
        top/bottom borders blue
        other borders black
        sub notes black
        Some with header and first col blue font, header with blue background
    some table images wider than text -- allow this?
    table images have extra text at bottom, between Note and Source
    
Lists
    ul in intro - blue square markers outside
    ul in text - black circle markers outside, fill justify
    ol in text - black number, bold?
    ol in Chapter Exercises
        markers like 1.22, right justified, blue, sans, outside
        li serif, left justified
    ol in Chapter Exercises
        lower alpha, all black, outside
    
    
Marginal material
    Quote
        black border top and bottom
        blue italic font, left justify
    Images
        small unnumbered diagrams (all in one?)
        some numbered figures
        
Figures
    Numbered, caption to right, bottom
    Numbered, caption on bottom, full width, image smaller, centered
    Some numbered with caption to left and in margin
    
Blue box feature in text      bx-1-h
    light blue background
    Q & A blue, title blue, text black, sans
    
Worked Example feature in text
    special styling, whole feature with top and right blue border
    "Worked Example" in left column, blue border
    May contain figures, caption to left, bottom
    
DIY box feature
    blue border
    black text, serif, fill
    
Application Demonstration box feature -- can be more than one page
    left margin polygon with title, connected to box
    box with blue upper and lower borders, light blue fill
    text follows main text styling
    
Math
    many simple, one with square root, some standalone quotients
    some larger, standalone, requiring MathML
    XML -- looks like complex math delivered in images. Any interest in MathML? :)
    
Key Terms
    black, bold
    
    
    
---------------------------------------------------------------
XML Requests

General
    Please consolidate all block_types into one, eliminating all variations.
    Please make model chapter and the remainder of the chapters consistent (i.e. use same block_types for same features.)

Intro section
    put "Chapter" and chapter number in separate <phrase> tags with different block_types, like 
    
    <p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch3-p1" block_type="chapter_number">CHAPTER 3</p>
    
    changes to 
    
    <p id="krugmanwellsessentials4e-ch3-p1" block_type="chapter_number">
        <phrase block_type="chap">CHAPTER</phrase>
        <phrase block_type="chapnum">3</phrase>
    </p>
    
Titles, subtitles
    if there is a number and text components, please surround number with phrase block-type="title_number", or "subtitle_number", or whatever seems appropriate, using the PDF as a guide as needed
    
    Example: 1.1 The Purpose of Statistics
    Add tags: <phrase block_type="sec_num">1.1</phrase><phrase block_type="sec_title">The Purpose of Statistics</phrase>

Figures
    As with titles, please put figure number in separate tag. For example, "Figure 1.13 Order of Operations" is currently just surrounded with a <strong> tag. Instead, please use something like <phrase block_type="fig_text">Figure</phrase><phrase block_type="fig_num">1.13</phrase><phrase block_type="fig_title">Order of Operations</phrase>.
    
    Example: <caption><phrase block_type="fig-label"><strong>Figure 3-14</strong></phrase> Equilibrium and Shifts of the Demand Curve</caption>
    Add tags: <caption><strong><phrase block_type="fig_text">Figure</phrase><phrase block_type="fig_num">1.13</phrase></strong><phrase block_type="fig_title">Order of Operations</phrase></caption>
    
    Mark figures that exceed the text area in width as "xlarge"
    (e.g. <layout align="center" width="xlarge" border="true"/>)

Introduction
    Please place TOC contents in a box.
    
Practice Problems & Apply Your Knowledge - Andy, will these be interactive? If not, maybe not use questions to code them.
    Please include numbering as found in PDF. Currently, these are question divs with the text, but no number, like 1.01, as in the PDF. Please make separate tag for this number, such as <p> or <phrase> with block_type="problem_number".

Chapter Exercises and anywhere there are numbered problems
    Treat with same suggestions as Practice Problems above (i.e. include the problem number within tags and block type)